<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>AP FULL</title><link>https://apnews.com</link><description>ur mom</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 21:12:34 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Jet crash disaster in South Korea marks another setback for Boeing</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/korea-plane-crash-boeing-51abcf86c1a4d01b94ad17b30f5fc774</link><description>WASHINGTON (AP) — A machinists strike. Another safety problem involving its troubled top-selling airliner. A plunging stock price.

2024 was already a dispiriting year for Boeing, the American aviation giant. But when one of the company’s jets crash-landed in South Korea on Sunday, killing all but two of the 181 people on board, it brought to a close an especially unfortunate year for Boeing.

The cause of the crash remains under investigation, and aviation experts were quick to distinguish Sunday’s incident from the company’s earlier safety problems.

Alan Price, a former chief pilot at Delta Air Lines who is now a consultant, said it would be inappropriate to link the incident Sunday to two fatal crashes involving Boeing’s troubled 737 Max jetliner in 2018 and 2019. In January this year, a door plug blew off a 737 Max while it was in flight, raising more questions about the plane.

The Boeing 737-800 that crash-landed in Korea, Price noted, is “a very proven airplane. “It’s different from the Max ...It’s a very safe airplane.’’

For decades, Boeing has maintained a role as one of the giants of American manufacturing. But the the past year’s repeated troubles have been damaging. The company’s stock price is down more than 30% in 2024.

The company’s reputation for safety was especially tarnished by the 737 Max crashes, which occurred off the coast of Indonesia and in Ethiopia less than five months apart in 2018 and 2019 and left a combined 346 people dead. In the five years since then, Boeing has lost more than $23 billion. And it has fallen behind its European rival, Airbus, in selling and delivering new planes.

Last fall, 33,000 Boeing machinists went on strike, crippling the production of the 737 Max, the company’s bestseller, the 777 airliner and 767 cargo plane. The walkout lasted seven weeks, until members of the International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers agreed to an offer that included 38% pay raises over four years.

In January, a door plug blew off a 737 Max during an Alaska Airlines flight. Federal regulators responded by imposing limits on Boeing aircraft production that they said would remain in place until they felt confident about manufacturing safety at the company.

In July, Boeing agreed to plead guilty to conspiracy to commit fraud for deceiving the Federal Aviation Administration regulators who approved the 737 Max. Acting on Boeing’s incomplete disclosures, the FAA approved minimal, computer-based training instead of more intensive training in flight simulators. Simulator training would have increased the cost for airlines to operate the Max and might have pushed some to buy planes from Airbus instead. (Prosecutors said they lacked evidence to argue that Boeing’s deception had played a role in the crashes.)

But the plea deal was rejected this month by a federal judge in Texas, Reed O’Connor, who decided that diversity, inclusion and equity or DEI policies in the government and at Boeing could result in race being a factor in choosing an official to oversee Boeing’s compliance with the agreement.

Boeing has sought to change its culture. Under intense pressure over safety issues, David Calhoun departed as CEO in August. Since January, 70,000 Boeing employees have participated in meetings to discuss ways to improve safety.</description></item><item><title>South Korean authorities seek warrant to detain impeached President Yoon in martial law probe</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/south-korea-yoon-martial-law-detain-rebellion-d00aa71be342df39b9775e49f90f5756</link><description>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) — South Korean law enforcement officials requested a court warrant on Monday to detain impeached President Yoon Suk Yeol as they investigate whether his short-lived martial law decree on Dec. 3 amounted to rebellion.

The Corruption Investigation Office for High-Ranking Officials, which leads a joint investigation with police and military authorities into the power grab that lasted only a few hours, confirmed it requested the warrant from the Seoul Western District Court. They plan to question Yoon on charges of abuse of authority and orchestrating a rebellion.

Yoon Kap-keun, the president’s lawyer, denounced the detention attempt and filed a challenge with the same court, arguing that the warrant request was invalid. He also claimed the anti-corruption agency lacked the legal authority to investigate rebellion charges. Still, he evaded answering how the legal team would respond if the court approved the warrant for the president’s detainment.

“An incumbent president cannot be prosecuted for abuse of power,” the lawyer said. “Of course, there are differing academic opinions on whether a president can be investigated for abuse of power and some assert that investigations are possible. But even when investigations are allowed, the prevailing opinion is that they should be exercised with the utmost restraint.”

The anti-corruption agency didn’t immediately respond to the lawyer’s comments.

Han Min-soo, spokesperson of the liberal opposition Democratic Party, called for the court to issue the warrant, saying Yoon Suk Yeol’s detainment would be the first step toward “ending the rebellion and restoring normalcy.”

The warrant request came after Yoon dodged several requests by the joint investigation team and public prosecutors to appear for questioning and also blocked searches of his offices.

While Yoon has the presidential privilege of immunity from criminal prosecution, such protections don’t extend to allegations of rebellion or treason.

It’s not clear whether the court will grant the warrant or whether Yoon can be compelled to appear for questioning.

Under the country’s laws, locations potentially linked to military secrets cannot be seized or searched without the consent of the person in charge, and it’s unlikely that Yoon will voluntarily leave his residence if he faces detention. There are also concerns about possible clashes with Yoon’s presidential security service if authorities attempt to forcibly detain him.

Yoon’s presidential powers were suspended after the National Assembly voted to impeach him on Dec. 14 over his imposition of martial law, which lasted only hours but has triggered weeks of political turmoil, halted high-level diplomacy and rattled financial markets.

Yoon’s fate now lies with the Constitutional Court, which has begun deliberations on whether to uphold the impeachment and formally remove Yoon from office or reinstate him.

The National Assembly voted last week to also impeach Prime Minister Han Duck-soo, who had assumed the role of acting president after Yoon’s powers were suspended, over his reluctance to fill three Constitutional Court vacancies ahead of the court’s review of Yoon’s case. The country’s new interim leader is Deputy Prime Minister Choi Sang-mok, who is also finance minister.

To formally end Yoon’s presidency, at least six justices on the nine-member Constitutional Court must vote in favor. Three seats are currently vacant following retirements and a full bench could make conviction more likely.

Choi, who has been handling the government’s response to a plane crash on Sunday that killed 179 people, has yet to say whether he intends to appoint the Constitutional Court justices.

In a separate criminal investigation of Yoon, authorities have already arrested his defense minister, police chief and several other military commanders involved in the attempt to enforce the martial law decree, which harkened back to the days of authoritarian leaders the country hasn’t seen since the 1980s.

In theory, the authority to investigate rebellion charges lies solely with the police, following a 2021 reform that redistributed investigative powers among law enforcement agencies and removed rebellion from the list of crimes prosecutors and the anti-corruption office could pursue. But those agencies have still been investigating rebellion accusations against Yoon, allegedly linked to charges related to abuse of power, a type of crime they are authorized to investigate.

Yoon and his military leadership have been accused of attempting to block the National Assembly from voting to end martial law by sending hundreds of heavily armed troops to encircle the building. Lawmakers who managed to get in voted unanimously 190-0 to lift martial law, hours after Yoon declared it in a late-night television address.

Yoon has also been accused of ordering defense counterintelligence officials to detain key politicians, including opposition leader Lee Jae-myung, National Assembly Speaker Woo Won Shik and the ex-leader of his own conservative party, Han Dong-hun, a reformist who supported investigations into corruption allegations against first lady Kim Keon Hee.

Yoon has defended the martial law decree as a necessary act of governance, portraying it as a temporary warning against the liberal opposition Democratic Party, which he has described as an “anti-state” force obstructing his agenda with its majority in the National Assembly. Yoon has claimed he had no intention to paralyze the functioning of the assembly, saying that the troops were sent to maintain order, and also denied planning to arrest politicians.

Yoon’s claims have been denied by Kwak Jong-keun, the now-arrested commander of the Army Special Warfare Command, who testified in the National Assembly that Yoon called for troops to “quickly destroy the door and drag out the lawmakers who are inside” the assembly’s main chamber where the vote occurred. Kwak said he did not carry out Yoon’s orders.

The joint investigation team has also questioned Maj. Gen. Moon Sang-ho, commander of the Defense Intelligence Command who has also been arrested over suspicions that he sent troops to the National Election Commission in the city of Gwacheon after Yoon declared martial law.

Yoon has defended the troop deployment to the election commission, which happened at the same time as the military operation at the National Assembly, saying it was necessary to investigate supposed vulnerabilities in the commission’s computer systems potentially affecting the credibility of election results.

Yoon’s failure to offer any evidence in support of his claims has raised concerns that he was endorsing conspiracy theories on right-wing YouTube channels that April’s parliamentary elections were rigged. The Democratic Party won those elections by a landslide. The election commission rejected Yoon’s allegations, stating there was no basis to suspect election fraud.</description></item><item><title>Brazilian film ‘I’m Still Here’ tops box office, forcing nation to reckon with dictatorship trauma</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/brazil-film-dictatorship-im-still-here-walter-salles-661b0a1d4f313c19c48dac4c1519fe0c</link><description>SAO PAULO (AP) — Brazilian-made dramas rarely last long in local cinemas. But, nearly two months after its release, “I’m Still Here,” a film about a family torn apart by the military dictatorship that ruled Brazil for more than two decades, has drawn millions of moviegoers across the South American country.

The film’s domestic box office success — with nearly 3 million tickets sold, it secured the fifth spot at the 2024 box office by mid December — is rooted in its exploration of a long-neglected national trauma, but it is particularly timely, especially as Brazil confronts a recent near-miss with democratic rupture.

People wait to watch the film “I’m Still Here,” at a movie theater in Sao Paulo, Friday, Dec. 20, 2024. (AP Photo/Andre Penner) People wait to watch the film “I’m Still Here,” at a movie theater in Sao Paulo, Friday, Dec. 20, 2024. (AP Photo/Andre Penner) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Set in the 1970s and based on true events, “I’m Still Here” tells the story of the Paivas, an upper-class family in Rio de Janeiro shattered by the dictatorship. Rubens Paiva, a former leftist congressman, was taken into custody by the military in 1971 and was never seen again. The narrative centers on his wife, Eunice Paiva, and her lifelong pursuit of justice.

The film was nominated for a Golden Globe for best foreign language film and shortlisted for the Oscars in the same category.

“Comedies and other topics are more likely to become mega-successes, but this (the dictatorship) is a very taboo subject for us,” said Brazilian psychoanalyst and writer Vera Iaconelli, adding that she felt a “sense of urgency” after watching the movie last month, even though the dictatorship ended almost four decades ago.

With a mask hanging in the foreground, demonstrators perform as victims in a torture device called pau-de-arara, or parrot’s perch, during a demonstration organized by the Rio de Paz NGO to remember the victims of Brazil’s military dictatorship, on Copacabana beach in Rio de Janeiro, Dec. 10, 2019. (AP Photo/Silvia Izquierdo, File) With a mask hanging in the foreground, demonstrators perform as victims in a torture device called pau-de-arara, or parrot’s perch, during a demonstration organized by the Rio de Paz NGO to remember the victims of Brazil’s military dictatorship, on Copacabana beach in Rio de Janeiro, Dec. 10, 2019. (AP Photo/Silvia Izquierdo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

As the movie was being shown across Brazil, the Federal Police unsealed a report detailing a 2022 plot by military officers to stage a coup to prevent President Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva from taking office, and to keep far-right former army captain Jair Bolsonaro in power. Bolsonaro and his allies have denied any involvement in participating or inciting a coup.

“Even if (director) Walter Salles wanted to plan the timing of the release this precisely, he wouldn’t have gotten it so right,” said Lucas Pedretti, a historian and sociologist whose works address memory and reparations after the military dictatorship.

“The film plays a very important role in telling us: ‘Look, this is what would happen if the coup that was planned by Bolsonaro and his military officers had succeeded.’”

Overdue reckoning

Unlike countries like Argentina and Chile, which established truth commissions and prosecuted former dictators and their henchmen, Brazil’s transition back to democracy was marked by a sweeping amnesty to military officials.

For years, said Pedretti, Brazil’s military promoted the notion that government silence was the best way to bury the past.

It was not until 2011 that Brazil’s then- President Dilma Rousseff — a former guerrilla who was tortured during the dictatorship — established a national truth commission to investigate its abuses.

The commission’s 2014 report detailed harrowing accounts of torture and named perpetrators of human rights violations — none were ever imprisoned. But just as a reckoning of the dictatorship began, calls for a return to military rule emerged in street protests against corruption revelations.

Unidentified men detain a student during a protest in Sao Paulo, Oct. 9, 1968. (AP Photo/Agencia Estado, File) Unidentified men detain a student during a protest in Sao Paulo, Oct. 9, 1968. (AP Photo/Agencia Estado, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

It was then that Marcelo Rubens Paiva, one of Rubens’ sons, decided to share his family’s story in his 2015 book “I’m Still Here.” The book introduced Eunice Paiva to a larger audience, chronicling her journey from a housewife to a relentless advocate for her disappeared husband, and how she raised five children by herself, while also pursuing a law degree.

In the years that followed, far-right, anti-establishment forces increasingly gained traction. Bolsonaro — who has long celebrated the coup and praised dictatorship-era torturers — would go on to ride that wave to a presidential victory in 2018.

A demonstrator holds a sign that reads in Portuguese “Never commemorate. Remember in order to not repeat. Dictatorship never again,” during a protest against Brazil’s 1964 military coup, in Rio de Janeiro, March 31, 2019. (AP Photo/Leo Correa, File) A demonstrator holds a sign that reads in Portuguese “Never commemorate. Remember in order to not repeat. Dictatorship never again,” during a protest against Brazil’s 1964 military coup, in Rio de Janeiro, March 31, 2019. (AP Photo/Leo Correa, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

A fragile memory

Observing the surge of the far-right in Brazil, filmmaker Salles realized the country’s memory of its dictatorship was very fragile. He said he saw a need for his country to confront its trauma in order to prevent history from repeating itself.

“I’m Still Here” isn’t the first Brazilian movie to explore the memory of the dictatorship, but it is the most popular. Unlike other films on the subject that tend to focus on dissidents and armed resistance, Salles chose to frame his as a family drama and how the disappearance of the family patriarch upended their day-to-day lives.

Its climax — spoiler alert! — arrives 25 years after Rubens’ disappearance, when Eunice finally receives his death certificate.

In December, a month after the film’s premiere, the Brazilian government allowed families of dictatorship-era victims to obtain reissued death certificates acknowledging state-sponsored killings.

“It is very symbolic that this is happening amid the international repercussion of ‘I’m Still Here’ ... so younger people can understand a bit of what that period was like,” Brazil’s Human Rights Minister Macaé Evaristo said during the announcement, calling it an important step in the “healing process for Brazilian society.”

Police gather on the other side of a window that was shattered by supporters of former President Jair Bolsonaro who stormed the Planalto Palace in Brasilia, Brazil, Jan. 8, 2023. (AP Photo/Eraldo Peres, File) Police gather on the other side of a window that was shattered by supporters of former President Jair Bolsonaro who stormed the Planalto Palace in Brasilia, Brazil, Jan. 8, 2023. (AP Photo/Eraldo Peres, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Calls for justice

The healing process remains incomplete, as some forces — once again — seek to prevent those who allegedly sought to sabotage democracy from being held to account.

On Nov. 29, Bolsonaro urged Lula and the Supreme Court to grant amnesty for those involved in the 2022 alleged coup plot and, alongside his allies, pushed for legislation to pardon participants in the 2023 anti-democratic riot that aimed to oust Lula and marked an echo of the Capitol insurrection in the U.S.

“The coup is still here. It’s still in people’s minds, it’s still in the minds of the military,” said Paulo Sergio Almeida, a filmmaker and founder of Filme B, a company that tracks Brazil’s national cinema. “We thought this was a thing of the past, but it’s not. The past is still present in Brazil.”

This time around, many Brazilians are calling for the prosecution of those responsible for the attempted coup, believing that justice is essential for national reconciliation and future progress.

On Dec. 14, police arrested Bolsonaro’s 2022 running mate and former defense minister in connection with investigations into the alleged coup plot, becoming the first four-star general arrested by civilians since the end of the dictatorship in 1985.

Brazilian President Jair Bolsonaro, left, and Defense Minister Walter Braga Netto attend a ceremony honoring military athletes who participated in the Tokyo 2020 Olympic Games at the military’s Admiral Adalberto Nunes Physical Education Center in Rio de Janeiro, Sept. 1, 2021. (AP Photo/Silvia Izquierdo, File) Brazilian President Jair Bolsonaro, left, and Defense Minister Walter Braga Netto attend a ceremony honoring military athletes who participated in the Tokyo 2020 Olympic Games at the military’s Admiral Adalberto Nunes Physical Education Center in Rio de Janeiro, Sept. 1, 2021. (AP Photo/Silvia Izquierdo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

“It’s a sign that we are making progress as a constitutional democracy,” leftist Sen. Randolfe Rodrigues wrote on X that day. “Brazil still has a long way to go as a Republic, but today is a HISTORIC day on this journey.”

Brazilians have also embraced the “No amnesty!” rallying cry, which originated at street protests in the aftermath of the capital’s 2023 riot and can still be heard.

Earlier this month, a Supreme Court justice cited “I’m Still Here” while arguing that the 1979 amnesty law shouldn’t apply to the crime of concealing bodies.

“The disappearance of Rubens Paiva, whose body was never found or buried, highlights the enduring pain of thousands of families,” Justice Flávio Dino said.

Striking a chord in Brazil was precisely Marcelo Rubens Paiva’s intent when adapting his book into a film.

“The movie is sparking this debate, and it arrived at the right moment for people to recognize that living under a dictatorship is no longer acceptable,” he said.

On a recent evening in Sao Paulo, 46-year-old Juliana Patrícia and her 16-year-old daughter, Ana Júlia, left a movie theater in tears, touched by “I’m Still Here.”

“We saw all the suffering that Eunice endured, with Rubens being killed and taken from his family in such a brutal way,” Patrícia said. “It made us even more certain that democracy needs to be respected and that, as Brazilians, we must fight harder to ensure that this never happens in our country again.”

Armed forces take part in a ceremony to commemorate the 1964 military coup that began the last Brazilian dictatorship, in Sao Paulo, Brazil, March 28, 2019. (AP Photo/Andre Penner, File) Armed forces take part in a ceremony to commemorate the 1964 military coup that began the last Brazilian dictatorship, in Sao Paulo, Brazil, March 28, 2019. (AP Photo/Andre Penner, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Armed forces take part in a ceremony to commemorate the 1964 military coup that began the last Brazilian dictatorship, in Sao Paulo, Brazil, March 28, 2019. (AP Photo/Andre Penner, File) Armed forces take part in a ceremony to commemorate the 1964 military coup that began the last Brazilian dictatorship, in Sao Paulo, Brazil, March 28, 2019. (AP Photo/Andre Penner, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

____

Follow AP’s coverage of Latin America and the Caribbean at https://apnews.com/hub/latin-america</description></item><item><title>Finnish investigators find an anchor drag mark on the Baltic seabed after suspicious cable damage</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/finland-estonia-russia-cable-undersea-sabotage-nato-c676c2ddb89db3dba60c96cfea4a0679</link><description>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) — Finnish investigators probing the damage to a Baltic Sea power cable and several data cables said they found an anchor drag mark on the seabed, apparently from a Russia-linked vessel that has already been seized.

The discovery heightened concerns about suspected sabotage by Russia’s “shadow fleet” of fuel tankers — aging vessels with obscure ownership acquired to evade Western sanctions amid the war in Ukraine and operating without Western-regulated insurance.

The Estlink-2 power cable, which transmits energy from Finland to Estonia across the Baltic Sea, went down on Dec. 25 after a rupture. It had little impact on services but followed damage to two data cables and the Nord Stream gas pipelines, both of which have been termed sabotage.

Finnish police chief investigator, Sami Paila, said late Sunday the anchor drag trail continued for “dozens of kilometers (miles) ... if not almost 100 kilometers (62 miles).”

Paila added to Finnish national TV broadcaster Yle: “Our current understanding is that the drag mark in question is that of the anchor of the (seized) Eagle S vessel. We have been able to clarify this matter through underwater research.”

Without giving further details, Paila said authorities have “a preliminary understanding of what happened at sea, how the anchor mark was created there,” and stressed that the “question of intent is a completely essential issue to be clarified in the preliminary investigation.”

On Saturday, the seized vessel was escorted to anchorage in the vicinity of the port of Porvoo to facilitate the investigation, officials said. It is being probed under criminal charges of aggravated interference with telecommunications, aggravated vandalism and aggravated regulatory offense.

The Eagle S is flagged in the Cook Islands but was described by Finnish customs officials and the European Union executive commission as part of Russia’s shadow fleet of fuel tankers. Russia’s use of the vessels has raised environmental concerns about accidents given their age and uncertain insurance coverage.

In the wake of the cable rupture, NATO Secretary-General Mark Rutte said last week that the military alliance, which Finland joined last year, will step up patrols in the Baltic Sea region.

The Finnish Coast Guard said Monday that another tanker ship headed for a Russian port has engine failure and drifted, then anchored in the Gulf of Finland south of the Hanko Paninsula. The guard said it was notified Sunday night.

Registered in Panama, the M/T Jazz was en route to Primorsk, Russia, from Sudan, with apparently no oil cargo. Finnish authorities have dispatched a tugboat and a patrol ship to ensure that the vessel does not drift and to prevent any damage to the environment.

Regional director of the Coast Guard, Janne Ryönänkoski, said there was no immediate risk to the seabed infrastructure.

Earlier Monday, EU foreign policy chief Kaja Kallas said that “sabotage in Europe has increased” since Russia’s full-scale invasion of Ukraine in February 2022.

Kallas told the German newspaper Welt that the recent “sabotage attempts in the Baltic Sea are not isolated incidents” but “part of a pattern of deliberate and coordinated actions to damage our digital and energy infrastructure.”

She vowed that the EU would “take stronger measures to counter the risks posed” by vessels of Russia’s shadow fleet.

Finland, which shares a 1,340-kilometer (832-mile) border with Russia, abandoned its decades-long policy of neutrality and joined NATO in 2023, amid Russia’s war against Ukraine.</description></item><item><title>An appeals court upholds a $5 million award in a sexual abuse verdict against President-elect Trump</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/trump-carroll-lawsuit-defamation-trial-78e4196024539653a6de492312770ff2</link><description>NEW YORK (AP) — A federal appeals court on Monday upheld a jury’s finding in a civil case that Donald Trump sexually abused a columnist in an upscale department store dressing room in the mid-1990s.

The 2nd U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals issued a written opinion upholding the $5 million award that the Manhattan jury granted to E. Jean Carroll for defamation and sexual abuse.

The longtime magazine columnist had testified at a 2023 trial that Trump turned a friendly encounter in spring 1996 into a violent attack after they playfully entered the store’s dressing room.

Trump skipped the trial after repeatedly denying the attack ever happened. But he briefly testified at a follow-up defamation trial earlier this year that resulted in an $83.3 million award. The second trial resulted from comments then-President Trump made in 2019 after Carroll first made the accusations publicly in a memoir.

In its ruling, a three-judge panel of the appeals court rejected claims by Trump’s lawyers that trial Judge Lewis A. Kaplan had made multiple decisions that spoiled the trial, including by permitting two other women who had accused Trump of sexually abusing them to testify.

The judge also had allowed the jury to view the infamous “Access Hollywood” tape in which Trump boasted in 2005 about grabbing women’s genitals because when someone is a star, “you can do anything.”

“We conclude that Mr. Trump has not demonstrated that the district court erred in any of the challenged rulings,” the 2nd Circuit said. “Further, he has not carried his burden to show that any claimed error or combination of claimed errors affected his substantial rights as required to warrant a new trial.”

In September, both Carroll, 81, and Trump, 78, attended oral arguments by the 2nd Circuit.

Steven Cheung, a Trump spokesperson, said in a statement that Trump was elected by voters who delivered “an overwhelming mandate, and they demand an immediate end to the political weaponization of our justice system and a swift dismissal of all of the Witch Hunts, including the Democrat-funded Carroll Hoax, which will continue to be appealed.”

Roberta Kaplan, a lawyer who represented Carroll during the trial and is not related to the judge, said in a statement: “Both E. Jean Carroll and I are gratified by today’s decision. We thank the Second Circuit for its careful consideration of the parties’ arguments.”

The first jury found in May 2023 that Trump sexually abused Carroll and defamed her with comments he made in October 2022. That jury awarded Carroll $5 million.

In January, a second jury awarded Carroll an additional $83.3 million in damages for comments Trump had made about her while he was president, finding that they were defamatory. That jury had been instructed by the judge to accept the first jury’s finding that Trump had sexually abused Carroll. The appeal of that verdict has not yet been heard.

Carroll testified during both trials that her life as an Elle magazine columnist was spoiled by Trump’s public comments, which she said motivated some people to send her death threats and leave her fearful to leave the upstate New York cabin where she lives.

Trump testified for under three minutes at the second trial and was not permitted to challenge conclusions reached by the May 2023 jury. Still, he was animated in the courtroom throughout the two-week trial, and jurors could hear him grumbling about the case.

During appeals arguments in September, Trump lawyer D. John Sauer said testimony from witnesses who recalled Carroll telling them about the 1996 encounter with Trump immediately afterward was improper because the witnesses had “egregious bias” against Trump.

And the attorney said the judge also should have excluded the testimony of the two women who said Trump committed similar acts of sex abuse against them in the 1970s and in 2005. Trump has denied those allegations too.

The 2nd Circuit wrote: “In each of the three encounters, Mr. Trump engaged in an ordinary conversation with a woman he barely knew, then abruptly lunged at her in a semi-public place and proceeded to kiss and forcefully touch her without her consent. The acts are sufficiently similar to show a pattern.”

It said the “Access Hollywood” tape was “directly corroborative” of the testimony by the women of the pattern of behavior they experienced.

The Associated Press does not identify people who say they have been sexually assaulted unless they come forward publicly, as Carroll has done.</description></item><item><title>Biden announces nearly $2.5 billion more in military aid for Ukraine</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/ukraine-russia-biden-military-weapons-a34bc2204def6c9f5f17cf2ebfcb6bd8</link><description>WASHINGTON (AP) — President Joe Biden said Monday that the United States will send nearly $2.5 billion more in weapons to Ukraine as his administration works quickly to spend all the money it has available to help Kyiv fight off Russia before President-elect Donald Trump takes office.

The package includes $1.25 billion in presidential drawdown authority, which allows the military to pull existing stock from its shelves and gets weapons to the battlefield faster. It also has $1.22 billion in longer-term weapons packages to be put on contract through the separate Ukraine Security Assistance Initiative, or USAI.

Biden said all longer-term USAI funds have now been spent and that he seeks to fully use all the remaining drawdown money before leaving office.

“I’ve directed my administration to continue surging as much assistance to Ukraine as quickly as possible,” Biden said in a statement. “At my direction, the United States will continue to work relentlessly to strengthen Ukraine’s position in this war over the remainder of my time in office.”

In addition to the weapons support, Treasury Secretary Janet Yellen announced Monday that the U.S. is also providing $3.4 billion in economic assistance to Ukraine to help pay for critical government services during its ongoing fight against Russia. The money will pay salaries for civilian government and school employees, healthcare workers and first responders.

The new military aid comes as Russia has launched a barrage of attacks against Ukraine’s power facilities in recent days, although Ukraine has said it intercepted a significant number of the missiles and drones. Russian and Ukrainian forces are also still in a bitter battle around the Russian border region of Kursk, where Moscow has sent thousands of North Korean troops to help reclaim territory taken by Ukraine.

The Biden administration is pushing to get weapons into Ukraine to give Kyiv the strongest negotiating position possible before Trump’s inauguration on Jan. 20. Trump has talked about getting some type of negotiated settlement between Ukraine and Russia and has praised Russian President Vladimir Putin.

Many U.S. and European leaders are concerned that Trump’s talk of a settlement might result in a poor deal for Ukraine, and they worry that he won’t provide Ukraine with all the weapons funding approved by Congress.

The weapons systems being pulled from existing stockpiles through this latest weapons package include counter-unmanned aerial systems munitions, air defense munitions, ammunition for High Mobility Artillery Rocket Systems (HIMARS), 155mm and 105mm artillery ammunition, air-to-ground munitions, anti-armor systems, tube-launched missiles, fragmentation grenades, and other items and spare parts.

Including Monday’s announcement, the U.S. has provided more than $65 billion in security assistance to Ukraine since Russia invaded its neighbor in February 2022.</description></item><item><title>Argentine judge charges five people over the death of former One Direction star Liam Payne</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/argentina-payne-death-charged-preventive-prison-1f93bf0c9e23e2e3cd520df54d74fde0</link><description>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) — An Argentine judge confirmed charges against five people in connection with the death of Liam Payne, a former member of musical group One Direction, and ordered preventive prison for two of them for having supplied him with drugs.

A judicial officer confirmed Monday the judge’s decision and said that one of the two people ordered to be put under preventive prison — a form of pre-trial detention — was an employee of the hotel in Buenos Aires where Payne stayed until he died after falling from the balcony of his room in October.

The officer said the other person was a waiter Payne met in a restaurant. The officer, who requested not to be identified as a condition to talk about the ruling, said that both face charges for supplying drugs and they need to present themselves before the judge.

The judge also charged three other people with manslaughter, including a businessman who was with Payne in Argentina and two managers of the hotel. The official said that they were not ordered to be held under preventive prison.

In November, prosecutors filed initial charges against three people, but they didn’t reveal their names.

Payne fell from his room’s balcony on the third floor of his hotel in the upscale neighborhood of Palermo in the Argentine capital. His autopsy said he died from multiple injuries and external bleeding.

Prosecutors also said that Payne’s toxicological exams showed that his body had “traces of alcohol, cocaine and a prescribed antidepressant” in the moments before his death.

Payne’s autopsy showed his injuries were caused neither by self-harm nor by physical intervention of others. The document also said that he did not have the reflex of protecting himself in the fall, which suggests he might have been unconscious.

Prosecutors in Argentina also ruled out the possibility that Payne died by suicide.

One Direction was among the most successful boy bands of recent times. It announced an indefinite hiatus in 2016 and Payne — like his former bandmates Zayn Malik, Harry Styles, Niall Horan, and Louis Tomlinson — pursued a solo career.</description></item><item><title>Jimmy Carter made eradicating Guinea worm disease a top mission</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/jimmy-carter-guinea-worm-parasite-16fcaed9fa09b7fbdccfeeba765ed20f</link><description>JARWENG, South Sudan (AP) — Nobel Prize-winning peacemaker Jimmy Carter spent nearly four decades waging war to eliminate an ancient parasite plaguing the world’s poorest people.

Rarely fatal but searingly painful and debilitating, Guinea worm disease infects people who drink water tainted with larvae that grow inside the body into worms as much as 3-feet-long. The noodle-thin parasites then burrow their way out, breaking through the skin in burning blisters.

Carter made eradicating Guinea worm a top mission of The Carter Center, the nonprofit he and his wife, Rosalynn Carter, founded after leaving the White House. The former president rallied public health experts, billionaire donors, African heads of state and thousands of volunteer villagers to work toward eliminating a human disease for only the second time in history.

“It’d be the most exciting and gratifying accomplishment of my life,” Carter told The Associated Press in 2016. Even after entering home hospice care in February 2023, aides said Carter kept asking for Guinea worm updates.

Carter died Sunday at age 100.

Thanks to the Carters’ efforts, the worms that afflicted an estimated 3.5 million people in 20 African and Asian countries when the center launched its campaign in 1986 are on the brink of extinction. Only 14 human cases were reported across four African nations in 2023, according to The Carter Center.

The World Health Organization’s target for eradication is 2030. Carter Center leaders hope to achieve it sooner.

That meant recently returning to Jarweng, in a remote area of South Sudan in northeastern Africa. The village of 500 people hadn’t seen Guinea worm infections since 2014, until Nyingong Aguek and her two sons drank swampy water while traveling in 2022. A fourth person also got infected.

“Having the worm pulled out is more painful than giving birth,” said Aguek, pointing to scars where four worms emerged from her left leg.

The center’s staff and volunteers walked house-to-house distributing water filters and teaching people to inspect dogs, which can also carry the parasite.

“If someone’s hurt, The Carter Center will help,” said villager Mathew Manyiel, listening to a training session while checking his dog for symptoms.

An audacious plan

In the mid-1980s, global health agencies were otherwise occupied and heads of state largely overlooked the illness afflicting millions of their citizens. Carter was still defining the center’s mission when public health experts who had served in his administration approached him with a plan to eliminate the disease.

Only a few years had passed since the WHO declared in 1979 that smallpox was the first human disease to be eradicated worldwide. Guinea worm, the experts told Carter, could become the second.

“President Carter, with a political background, was able to do far more in global health than we could do alone,” said Dr. William Foege, who led the U.S. Centers for Disease Control’s smallpox eradication program and the CDC itself before becoming The Carter Center’s first executive director.

Those who worked closely with Carter suspect Guinea worm’s toll on poor African farmers resonated with the former president, who lived as a boy in a Georgia farmhouse without electricity or running water.

“Nobody was doing anything about it, and it was such a spectacularly awful disease,” said Dr. Donald Hopkins, an architect of the campaign who led the center’s health programs until 2015. “He could sympathize with all of these farmers being too crippled from Guinea worm disease to work.”

Eliminating other diseases

There’s no vaccine that prevents Guinea worm infections or medicine that gets rid of the parasites. Treatment has changed little since ancient Greece. Emerging worms are gently wound around a stick as they’re slowly pulled through the skin. Removing an entire worm without breaking it can take weeks.

So instead of scientific breakthroughs, this campaign has relied on persuading millions of people to change basic behaviors.

Workers from the center and host governments trained volunteers to teach neighbors to filter water through cloth screens, removing tiny fleas that carry the larvae. Villagers learned to watch for and report new cases — often for rewards of $100 or more. Infected people and dogs had to be prevented from tainting water sources.

The goal was to break the worm’s life cycle — and therefore eliminate the parasite itself — in each endemic community, eventually exterminating Guinea worm altogether.

The campaign became a model for confronting a broader range of neglected tropical diseases afflicting impoverished people with limited access to clean water, sanitation and health care. Expanding its public health mission, the center has supplied training, equipment and medicines that helped 22 countries eliminate at least one disease within their borders.

Mali became the latest in May 2023 when the WHO confirmed it had ended trachoma, a blinding eye infection. Haiti and the Dominican Republic are working to eliminate malaria and mosquito-borne lymphatic filariasis by 2030. Countries in Africa and the Americas are pursuing an end to river blindness by 2035.

A personal mission

Having a former U.S. president lead the charge brought big advantages to a nonprofit that relied on private donors to fund its initiatives.

Carter’s fundraising enabled the center to pour $500 million into fighting Guinea worm. He persuaded manufacturers to donate larvicide as well as nylon cloth and specially made drinking straws to filter water. His visits to afflicted villages often attracted news coverage, raising awareness globally.

“He went to so many of the localities where people were afflicted,” said Dr. William Brieger, a professor of international health at Johns Hopkins University who spent 25 years in Africa. “The kind of attention that was drawn to him for getting on the ground and highlighting the plight of individual people who were suffering, I think that made an important difference.”

Carter first saw the disease up close in 1988 while visiting a village in Ghana where nearly 350 people had worms poking through their skin. He approached a young woman who appeared to be cradling a baby in her arm.

“But there was no baby,” Carter wrote in his 2014 book “A Call to Action.” “Instead she was holding her right breast, which was almost a foot long and had a worm emerging from the nipple.”

Carter used his status to sway other leaders to play larger roles. Some heads of state got competitive, spurred by the center’s charts and newsletters that showed which countries were making progress and which lagged behind.

Worms in a war zone

In 1995, Carter intervened when a civil war in southern Sudan made it too dangerous for workers to reach hundreds of hotspots. The ceasefire he negotiated enabled the center and others to distribute 200,000 water filters and discover more endemic villages.

Carter’s efforts not only stopped transmissions in much of what became South Sudan, but also built trust across communities that resulted in a “significant peace dividend,” said Makoy Samuel Yibi, the young nation’s Guinea worm eradication director.

Pakistan in 1993 became the first endemic country to eliminate human cases. India soon followed. By 1997, the disease was no longer found in Asia. By 2003, cases reported worldwide were down to 32,000 — a 99% decline in less than two decades.

Some setbacks frustrated Carter. Visiting a hospital packed with suffering children and adults amid a 2007 resurgence in Ghana, Carter suggested publicly that the disease should perhaps be renamed “Ghana worm.”

“Ghana was deeply embarrassed,” Hopkins said.

Ghana ended transmission within three more years. Even more inspiring: Nigeria, which once had the most cases in the world, reached zero infections in 2009.

“That was a thunderclap,” Hopkins said. “It was important throughout Africa, throughout the global campaign.”

To the last worm

Even after being diagnosed with brain cancer, Carter remained focused: “I’d like the last Guinea worm to die before I do,” he told reporters in 2015.

Despite dwindling cases, total success has proven elusive.

Historic flooding and years of civil war have displaced millions of people who lack clean drinking water across central Africa. Of the 13 total cases reported in 2023, nine occurred in Chad, where infections in dogs have made the worms harder to eliminate.

“These are the most challenging places on planet Earth to operate in,” said Adam Weiss, who has directed the campaign since 2018. “You need eyes and ears on the ground every single day.”

The campaign still relies on about 30,000 volunteers spread among roughly 9,000 villages. Staying vigilant can be difficult now that cases are so rare, Weiss said.

“I would still like to think we will beat the timeline,” Weiss said of the 2030 eradication goal. “The Carter Center is committed to this, obviously, no matter what.”

___

This story has been updated to show there were 14 human Guinea worm cases reported across four African nations in 2023, according to The Carter Center.

—-

Bynum reported from Savannah, Georgia.</description></item><item><title>Jimmy Carter and Playboy: How ‘the weirdo factor’ rocked ’76</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/jimmy-carter-playboy-president-670c9d3533c65a61597ce4454c175bb0</link><description>PLAINS, Ga. (AP) — Jimmy Carter already had drawn months of media scrutiny as a devout Southern Baptist running for president. Then the 1976 Democratic nominee brought up sex and sin as he explained his religious faith to Playboy magazine.

Carter was not misquoted. But he was certainly misunderstood, as his thoughts in the wide-ranging interview were reduced in the popular imagination to utterances about “lust” and “adultery.”

Nearly a half-century later, as Carter was receiving hospice care in the same south Georgia home where he once spoke with Playboy journalists, his interviewer Robert Scheer still believed Carter was treated unfairly. He recalled the former president as a “real” and “serious” figure whose intent was smothered by the intensity of a campaign’s closing stretch.

Then President-elect Jimmy Carter waves to the crowd as he and his wife Rosalynn arrive at the Plains Baptist Church to attend services in Plains, Ga., on Nov. 22, 1976. (AP Photo, File) Then President-elect Jimmy Carter waves to the crowd as he and his wife Rosalynn arrive at the Plains Baptist Church to attend services in Plains, Ga., on Nov. 22, 1976. (AP Photo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Carter died Sunday at age 100.

“Jimmy Carter was a thoughtful guy,” Scheer told The Associated Press. “But that got lost here. I’ve never seen a story like it. It was worldwide. ... It just never went away.”

Political disaster ensued. Rosalynn Carter was suddenly being asked whether she trusted her husband. The fallout, in Carter’s words, “nearly cost me the election.”

Carter spent five-plus hours with Playboy across several months — “more time with you than with Time, Newsweek and all the others combined,” he told Scheer and Playboy editor Barry Golson.

The resulting Q&amp;A spanned 12,000 words, and Scheer added thousands more in an accompanying story. Carter discussed military and foreign policy, racism and civil rights, political journalism and his reputation as a “vague” candidate.

“They weren’t interested in sensationalized stuff,” Scheer said of Playboy.

Hugh Hefner’s publication reached an estimated 20 million-plus readers each month with its pictorials of nude women. But the magazine chronicled American culture as well, with its branded “Playboy Interview” featuring such power players as the Rev. Martin Luther King Jr., John Lennon, Malcom X and leading newsman Walter Cronkite.

Carter, unafraid of nuance, proved he belonged among them, Scheer said.

Carter’s most-remembered comments came at the end of their final session. Standing outside Carter’s front door, Golson pressed Carter on whether his piety would make him a “rigid, unbending president” unable to represent all Americans.

The Baptist deacon responded with an 823-word soliloquy on human imperfection, pride and God’s forgiveness. He said he believed in “absolute and total separation of church and state” and explained his faith as rooted in humility, not judgment of others.

Quoting Matthew 5:27-28, Carter explained that Jesus Christ considered an offending thought equivalent to consummated adultery, and by that standard, he was in no position to judge a man who “shacks up” and “screws lots of women,” because he had “looked on many women with lust” and, thus, “committed adultery many times in my heart.”

Scheer called it a “sensible statement,” reflecting Carter’s Baptist tradition: “He was saying, ‘Look, I’m not going to be some fanatic. ... I’m not this perfect guy.’”

Democratic Presidential candidate Jimmy Carter and his wife Rosalynn Carter greet people after attending church services at the University Baptist Church near the end of his presidential election campaign on Oct. 31, 1976, in Fort Worth, Texas. (AP Photo/John Duricka, File) Democratic Presidential candidate Jimmy Carter and his wife Rosalynn Carter greet people after attending church services at the University Baptist Church near the end of his presidential election campaign on Oct. 31, 1976, in Fort Worth, Texas. (AP Photo/John Duricka, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Playboy realized Carter provided explosive material — and not just about sex. Citing President Lyndon Johnson’s handling of Vietnam, Carter included the last Democratic president alongside disgraced Republican Richard Nixon as guilty of “lying, cheating and distorting the truth.”

The magazine decided to send the full Q&amp;A text to about 1,000 media outlets in late September, before the usual October publication date for the November edition.

The idea, Scheer explained, was to allow time for fair coverage rather than drop bombshells days before the election.

Headline writers, satirists and late-night television pounced anyway, labeling it Carter’s “lust in my heart” interview. “Saturday Night Live,” then a fledgling NBC sketch comedy show, had a field day. One political cartoonist depicted Carter lusting after the Statue of Liberty.

He lamented to NPR in 1993 that the Playboy interview morphed into “the No. 1 story of the entire 1976 campaign.”

“I was explaining Jesus’ Sermon on the Mount,” Carter wrote wistfully in a 2015 memoir.

Carter’s faith had endeared him to many fellow white evangelicals and cultural conservatives. That made him a difficult foil for Republicans, who wanted to cast Democrats as out of step with most of America. The flip side, Scheer noted, was that many young voters and urban liberals — key Democratic constituencies — “wondered if he was this Southern square.”

Jimmy Carter speaks to a crowd of supporters during his presidential campaign on the Van Ryswyk farm in Des Moines, Iowa, Aug. 24, 1976. (AP Photo, File) Jimmy Carter speaks to a crowd of supporters during his presidential campaign on the Van Ryswyk farm in Des Moines, Iowa, Aug. 24, 1976. (AP Photo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

“Hamilton Jordan (Carter’s campaign manager) had always called Carter’s faith ‘the weirdo factor,’” said Amber Roessner, a University of Tennessee media historian who has written extensively on Carter. “Talking to Playboy was their way to prove he wasn’t some kind of prude.”

Scheer, who was with Carter as part of his traveling press corps, said Playboy’s early text release sparked a frenzy.

“Reporters were scrambling, asking me, ’Bob, what is this?” he recalled.

The press traveling with Carter focused initially on Carter’s criticism of Johnson, who died in 1973. It was a juicy detail because Carter was headed Texas to campaign with LBJ’s widow.

Carter initially told reporters his criticisms of LBJ were taken out of context. Scheer “ran back to the plane to get the tapes,” and effectively caught the nominee violating his pledge never to make a “misleading statement.”

Lady Bird Johnson skipped Carter’s Texas events, Scheer said. Carter apologized to her by telephone.

When his commentary on adultery ballooned, Carter insisted the exchange had been off-the-record, throwaway banter as Scheer and Golson prepared to leave.

“He was still wearing the mic!” Scheer told AP.

The way the story morphed “ended up making Carter seem like a creep,” Roessner said.

President-elect Jimmy Carter, left, with his wife Rosalynn Carter on Dec. 3, 1976. (AP Photo/Charles Harrity, File) President-elect Jimmy Carter, left, with his wife Rosalynn Carter on Dec. 3, 1976. (AP Photo/Charles Harrity, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Rosalynn Carter fashioned a pat response: “Jimmy talks too much, but at least people know he’s honest and doesn’t mind answering questions.” And, no, she never worried about his fidelity.

“The only lust I worried about was that of the press,” she wrote in 1984, recounting how her discipline finally cracked when a reporter asked whether she ever committed adultery.

“If I had,” she replied, “I wouldn’t tell you.”

The front page of a publication mailed to rural Iowans by then-President Gerald Ford’s campaign committee is seen on Oct. 26, 1976, in Des Moines, Iowa. The cartoon shows Carter in the pulpit waving the Bible and copy of Playboy magazine. (AP Photo, File) The front page of a publication mailed to rural Iowans by then-President Gerald Ford’s campaign committee is seen on Oct. 26, 1976, in Des Moines, Iowa. The cartoon shows Carter in the pulpit waving the Bible and copy of Playboy magazine. (AP Photo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

President Gerald Ford, who had been gaining on Carter but still trailed badly, leveraged the story. The Republican president was an Episcopalian, soft-spoken about religion, but he invited leading evangelical pastors to the White House the day after the interview’s release, including the Rev. W.S. Criswell of Dallas First Baptist Church.

Criswell later declared from his pulpit that he had asked Ford: “Mr. President, if Playboy magazine were to ask you for an interview, what would you do?” Ford’s reply, according to Criswell: “I was asked by Playboy magazine for an interview — and I declined with an emphatic ‘No’!”

Thousands of his parishioners roared.

The Rev. Billy Graham, then the nation’s top evangelist, and the Rev. Jerry Falwell, the rising leader of the so-called Religious Right, also blitzed Carter. National media, including The AP, highlighted criticism from Christian pastors from around the country.

Roessner, the daughter of a Protestant pastor, said Carter’s Playboy comments were clumsy, “but if anyone should have understood the context ... it should have been the ministers.”

She recalled Carter’s resentment during a 2014 interview she conducted with him. Decades of global humanitarian work had by that time afforded the former president a profile above politics, yet “almost 40 years later, it was clearly something he held on to,” she said. He was “still incredibly frustrated by what he felt was unfair coverage and response.”

The 1976 campaign was the first after Richard Nixon’s resignation, driven by reporting from The Washington Post, and many journalists were demonstrating a new level of distrust of politicians, especially one Scheer described as “wearing his religion on his sleeve.”

Those same news organizations largely ignored what the soon-to-be president said about them, Roessner noted.

“The traveling press have zero interest in any issue unless it’s a matter of making a mistake,” Carter told Playboy. “There’s nobody in the back of this plane who would ask an issue question unless he thought he could trick me into some crazy statement.”

Scheer, at least, asked plenty of policy questions, and, looking back, he pointed to Carter’s narrow victory just weeks later.

“Whatever they said, I think it did exactly what they wanted to accomplish,” Scheer said. “That doesn’t mean they weren’t nervous.”

___

This story was first published April 16, 2023, and has been updated with news of Carter’s death.</description></item><item><title>Chinese hackers accessed workstations and documents in a ‘major’ cyber incident, Treasury says</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/china-hacking-treasury-department-8942106afabeac96010057e05c67c9d5</link><description>WASHINGTON (AP) — Chinese hackers remotely accessed several U.S. Treasury Department workstations and unclassified documents after compromising a third-party software service provider, the agency said Monday.

The department did not provide details on how many workstations had been accessed or what sort of documents the hackers may have obtained, but it said in a letter to lawmakers revealing the breach that “at this time there is no evidence indicating the threat actor has continued access to Treasury information.” The hack was being investigated as a “major cybersecurity incident,” it added.

“Treasury takes very seriously all threats against our systems, and the data it holds,” a department spokesperson said in a separate statement. “Over the last four years, Treasury has significantly bolstered its cyber defense, and we will continue to work with both private and public sector partners to protect our financial system from threat actors.”

In Beijing, a Foreign Ministry spokesperson gave China’s standard response to hacking allegations.

“We have repeatedly stated our position on such groundless accusations that lack evidence,” Mao Ning said at a daily briefing. “China consistently opposes all forms of hacking, and we are even more opposed to the dissemination of false information against China for political purposes.”

The incident comes as U.S. officials are continuing to grapple with the fallout of a massive Chinese cyberespionage campaign known as Salt Typhoon that gave officials in Beijing access to private texts and phone conversations of an unknown number of Americans. A senior White House official said Friday that the number of telecommunications companies confirmed to have been affected by the hack has now risen to nine.

The Treasury Department said it learned of the latest problem on Dec. 8, when a third-party software service provider, BeyondTrust, flagged that hackers had stolen a key “used by the vendor to secure a cloud-based service used to remotely provide technical support” to workers. That key helped the hackers override the service’s security and gain remote access to several employee workstations.

The compromised service has since been taken offline, and there’s no evidence that the hackers still have access to department information, Aditi Hardikar, an assistant Treasury secretary, said in the letter Monday to leaders of the Senate Banking Committee.

The department said it was working with the FBI and the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency and others to investigate the impact of the hack, and that the hack had been attributed to Chinese state-sponsored culprits. It did not elaborate.

___

Associated Press writer Ken Moritsugu in Beijing contributed to this report.</description></item><item><title>Times Square ball takes final test for New Year’s Eve</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/times-square-new-years-eve-ball-test-ffc39fae74a728a384fdafc4cb3bf0db</link><description>NEW YORK (AP) — The crystal-covered ball that descends down a pole in Times Square to ring in the new year was taken for a test run Monday, as New York City officials laid out their plans for the iconic New Year’s Eve event.

Officials flipped a switch to light up the dazzling geodesic sphere — weighing almost 6 tons (5.4 metric tons) and featuring 2,688 crystal triangles — which then successfully ran up and down a 139-foot (42-meter) pole atop the One Times Square skyscraper.

Monday’s rehearsal was just one of many pre-ball drop promotional events: On Sunday, fistfuls of confetti were flung toward crowds in the square in anticipation of the 3,000 pounds (1,360 kilograms) of brightly colored paper that will fill the air at midnight on New Year’s Eve. Some of those pieces will include wishes written by people ahead of 2025.

“This is the crossroads of the entire planet right here in New York City,” New York City Mayor Eric Adams said earlier Monday as he and law enforcement leaders discussed their plans for security at the celebration. “People tune in at different locations and celebrate as we do the countdown for the New Year.”

Police Commissioner Jessica Tisch said that although there were “no specific credible threats” to the Times Square celebrations, “the public can expect to see a tremendous amount of police resources deployed throughout the area and across the city.” Plans range from “dedicated pickpocket teams” patrolling the square to sealing off all mailboxes and vending machines in the area.

A New Year’s Eve ball has dropped in Times Square for nearly 120 years, with the exception of 1942 and 1943 when nightly “dimouts” occurred during World War II to protect the city from attacks.</description></item><item><title>South Korean court issues warrants to detain impeached President Yoon and search his office</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/south-korea-president-martial-law-yoon-warrant-4cf80153a9bd333147afb746adb49433</link><description>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) — A South Korean court issued warrants Tuesday to detain impeached President Yoon Suk Yeol and search his office and residence over allegations of rebellion in connection with his short-lived declaration of martial law.

It’s the first time a warrant has been issued to detain a sitting South Korean president. But experts say there is little chance of detention or searches unless Yoon is formally removed from office.

The Seoul Western District Court issued warrants to detain Yoon and to search the presidential office and residence in central Seoul, according to a statement from the Corruption Investigation Office for High-Ranking Officials, which is leading a joint investigation with police and military authorities.

The agency says it’s been investigating whether Yoon’s Dec. 3 declaration amounted to rebellion.

Under South Korean law, the leader of a rebellion can face the death penalty or life imprisonment if convicted. Yoon has presidential immunity from most criminal prosecutions, but the privilege does not extend to allegations of rebellion or treason.

Yoon’s powers have been suspended since the opposition-controlled National Assembly voted to impeach him on Dec. 14 over his imposition of martial law, during which hundreds of troops and police officers were deployed at the assembly. By law, a president in South Korea is allowed to declare martial law only during wartime or similar emergencies and has no right to suspend parliament’s operations even under martial law.

Yoon has argued his decree was a legitimate act of governance, calling it a warning to the main liberal opposition Democratic Party — which he has called “a monster” and “anti-state forces” — that has used its legislative majority to impeach top officials, undermine the government’s budget, and which he claims sympathizes with North Korea.

The Constitutional Court is to determine whether to dismiss Yoon as president or reinstate him.

Experts said Yoon is likely to ignore the warrants. He’s already dodged repeated requests by investigative authorities to appear for questioning, and the presidential security service has blocked attempts to search his office and residence citing a law that bans raids on sites with state secrets.

Yoon Kap-keun, a lawyer for the president, called the detainment warrant “invalid” and “illegal,” saying the anti-corruption agency lacks legal authority to investigate rebellion charges. The presidential security service said it will provide security to Yoon in accordance with the law.

The anti-corruption agency said it has no immediate plans on when it would proceed with the warrants.

“Unless Yoon voluntarily lets them detain him, there is no way to detain him,” said Choi Jin, director of the Seoul-based Institute of Presidential Leadership. “Should investigators have hand-to-hand fights with the security service?”

Choi said that investigators were still likely to visit Yoon’s residence to show they are strictly and fairly carrying out their work.

Park Sung-min, president of Seoul-based political consulting firm MIN Consulting, said the push for an arrest warrant is likely an attempt to pressure Yoon to cooperate with investigations.

Former President Park Geun-hye, who was thrown out of office in 2017 following an impeachment over a corruption scandal, also refused to meet with prosecutors while in office. She underwent questioning by them and was arrested after the Constitutional Court removed her from office.

Yoon’s imposition of martial law lasted only six hours but triggered huge political turmoil, halting high-level diplomacy and rattling financial markets. Despite Yoon’s deployment of troops and police, enough lawmakers managed to enter the assembly chamber to overturn it unanimously.

Yoon’s defense minister, police chief and several top military commanders have already been arrested over their roles in the martial law enactment.

Yoon has claimed he wasn’t trying to stop the functioning of the assembly, saying that the troops were sent to maintain order, and also denied planning to arrest politicians. But comments by now-arrested commanders of military units sent to the assembly have contradicted this claim.

Kwak Jong-keun, the commander of the Army Special Warfare Command, testified at the National Assembly that Yoon called on troops to “quickly knock down the door and drag out the lawmakers who are inside.” Kwak said he did not carry out Yoon’s orders.

The country’s political crisis deepened last Friday, when the Democratic Party and other small opposition parties voted to impeach acting President Han Duck-soo as well over wrangling over his refusal to fill in three justice seats at the nine-member Constitutional Court. Observers say adding more justices could increase prospects for the court’s endorsement of Yoon’s impeachment as that requires support from at least six justices.

The deputy prime minister and finance minister, Choi Sang-mok, has become South Korea’s new interim leader. On Tuesday, Choi appointed two new justices, saying he feels the urgency to resolve political uncertainty and national divide.

Choi’s moves drew rebukes from both the ruling and opposition parties. The governing People Power Party accused him of surrendering to the opposition’s political offensive, while the main liberal opposition Democratic Party urged Choi to quickly appoint the remaining ninth justice.</description></item><item><title>Jimmy Carter sought to expand democracy worldwide long after he left the White House</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/jimmy-carter-democracy-elections-monitoring-e89d2cf6917bc92cd56b5394580da389</link><description>HARARE, Zimbabwe (AP) — Amid everything else on his desk — the Iran hostage crisis, domestic economic turmoil, the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan and a grueling 1980 reelection fight — President Jimmy Carter elevated the independence of a country in southern Africa as a top agenda item.

Carter hosted then-Zimbabwean leader Robert Mugabe at the White House soon after his country achieved independence and later described Zimbabwe’s adoption of democracy as “our greatest single success.”

Three decades later, Carter, who was long out of office, found the door slammed shut when he and other dignitaries sought to visit Zimbabwe on a humanitarian mission to observe reported human rights abuses after a violent disputed election in 2008. He had become a critic of Mugabe’s regime and was denied a visa.

Carter didn’t give up. From neighboring South Africa, he relied on emissaries from Zimbabwe for testimony on violence and allegations of electoral fraud. The effort reflected the former president’s long commitment to promoting democracy worldwide.

Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter, background second right, former U.N. head Kofi Annan, background right, and Graca Machel, the wife of former South African President Nelson Mandela, background second from left, watch children perform during a visit to the Central Methodist Church in Johannesburg, South Africa, Nov. 23, 2008. The diplomats were barred entry into Zimbabwe on a humanitarian visit over the weekend. (AP Photo/Denis Farrell, File) Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter, background second right, former U.N. head Kofi Annan, background right, and Graca Machel, the wife of former South African President Nelson Mandela, background second from left, watch children perform during a visit to the Central Methodist Church in Johannesburg, South Africa, Nov. 23, 2008. The diplomats were barred entry into Zimbabwe on a humanitarian visit over the weekend. (AP Photo/Denis Farrell, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

This “more than anything else cemented Carter’s legacy” as an advocate for free and fair elections across Africa, said Eldred Masunungure, a former political science lecturer at the University of Zimbabwe.

“Carter didn’t change. Zimbabwe did. Mugabe swayed from the democratic ideals that Carter held so dear,” he said. “The incident demonstrates Carter’s consistency, the steadfastness.”

Zimbabwe’s evolution toward autocracy turned out to be the kind of scenario that the Carter Center has long sought to prevent by deploying observers and developing voting standards in countries struggling to form democracies.

Established in 1982, two years after Carter lost his bid for a second term, the center has been Carter’s signature effort to promote fair elections as a vehicle for peace. It has sent observers to monitor some 125 elections in 40 countries and three tribal nations, and has been credited with helping expand democracy across the globe.

Carter’s “moral authority, the trust people put in him and the credibility of someone who had both won and lost an election” contributed to these successes, David Carroll, head of the center’s democracy program, told The Associated Press.

Carter, who died Sunday at 100, was awarded a Nobel Peace Prize in 2002 for the center’s work supporting elections, promoting human rights and helping developing countries cultivate economic, social and public health institutions.

Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter stands in a polling station at San Miguelito, Panama, as part of an international delegation of observers under the Council of Freely-Elected Heads of Government on May 7, 1989. (AP Photo/Luis Romero, File) Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter stands in a polling station at San Miguelito, Panama, as part of an international delegation of observers under the Council of Freely-Elected Heads of Government on May 7, 1989. (AP Photo/Luis Romero, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Its elections work began in Panama, where Carter became concerned about the 1989 elections after reports of armed militia members in civilian clothes confiscating voting records during the night.

The Carter Center had just decided to expand its mission of conflict resolution and human rights to include vote monitoring, concluding that democratic elections were essential to resolving political disputes.

“In my fumbling Spanish, I stood up on a table, and I denounced the election as fraudulent,” Carter recalled in a 2015 video marking the center’s 100th election observer mission. “There was later another election, which was honest and fair, and that was the birth of real democracy in Panama.”

Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter meets with Bhoj Raj Pokhrel, Nepal’s chief election official, on April 8, 2008, in Katmandu, Nepal. (AP Photo/Ed Wray, File) Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter meets with Bhoj Raj Pokhrel, Nepal’s chief election official, on April 8, 2008, in Katmandu, Nepal. (AP Photo/Ed Wray, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

The center also helped rescue a peace process in Nepal, then oversaw the country’s twice-postponed elections in 2008 to elect an assembly that would be tasked with writing a constitution. Carter made several trips to the South Asian nation, holding marathon negotiations with former rebels and top politicians to keep the peace process on track.

“There was deadlock in the country. Political parties were not sitting together, and there was no way out on how the process will move on,” said Bhojraj Pokharel, Nepal’s chief election commissioner in 2008, who later worked with Carter in Congo and Myanmar.

On Nepal’s election day, Carter traveled to dozens of polling stations talking to voters. Polling was peaceful despite earlier fears of violence.

“His presence itself was a message to the Nepalese population and voters about the integrity of the election,” Pokharel said.

Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter speaks at a news conference in Katmandu, Nepal, on April 1, 2013. (AP Photo/Niranjan Shrestha, File) Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter speaks at a news conference in Katmandu, Nepal, on April 1, 2013. (AP Photo/Niranjan Shrestha, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter, center, visits a polling station in Katmandu, Nepal, on Nov. 19, 2013. (AP Photo/Niranjan Shrestha, File) Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter, center, visits a polling station in Katmandu, Nepal, on Nov. 19, 2013. (AP Photo/Niranjan Shrestha, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

The Carter Center often works in countries with little or no experience in representative government and where trust has all but evaporated because of violence.

After Bolivia held elections in 2019 that the Organization of American States said were marred by fraud, the country’s electoral tribunal invited the Carter Center to observe elections the following year. The center deployed a team to Bolivia and later commended the country for elections it called impartial and transparent.

The Carter Center’s “evaluation was important not only for how the international community viewed us but also for how Bolivian society evaluated the electoral process,” said Salvador Romero, the tribunal’s president at the time.

Similar results have been difficult to obtain recently in Africa, where many countries emerging from decades of colonialism have seen forceful takeovers and disputed elections.

Nigerian head of state Gen. Abdulsalami Abubakar shakes hands with former U.S. President Jimmy Carter after a meeting at the Nigerian Presidential Villa in the capital Abuja, on Feb. 28, 1999. (AP Photo/Danny Wilcox Frazier, File) Nigerian head of state Gen. Abdulsalami Abubakar shakes hands with former U.S. President Jimmy Carter after a meeting at the Nigerian Presidential Villa in the capital Abuja, on Feb. 28, 1999. (AP Photo/Danny Wilcox Frazier, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

In Nigeria, Tunisia, Zambia and Ivory Coast, Carter Center observers noted violence, killings, vote-buying, uneven playing fields for political parties and candidates, and a general lack of trust in elections.

In Tunisia, frustration has replaced the wave of hope brought by the 2010 Arab Spring uprising. A new parliament was convened in March 2023, two years after President Kais Saied suspended parliament and started legislating by decree. The 11% turnout for parliamentary elections marked “a low point” for the country’s democracy, The Carter Center said, and some election observer groups were denied accreditation for the October 2024 presidential contest.

At times, Carter personally intervened to keep African peace processes on track by trying to persuade warlords and rebels to support elections, rather than the use of force, in their quests for power.

In recent years, the Carter Center’s elections work turned toward the U.S.

Its teams deployed to Oklahoma in 2017 at the request of the Cheyenne and Arapaho tribes following elections plagued with problems. In 2013, ballots had been moved from office to office and stored without proper security, eroding confidence in the integrity of the vote. A recount then overturned the results, tribal Gov. Reggie Wassana said.

The Carter Center’s presence in the later election made “a huge difference, and it restored some faith among tribal members,” Wassana said.

Until 2020, the center tried to stay away from broader political issues in the United States, according to Carroll. But the center noticed threats to American democracy were increasing, which prompted a decision to expand programs within the U.S.

A volunteer election observer reviews training materials on Nov. 6, 2022, at the Carter Center in Atlanta. (AP Photo/Jeff Amy, File) A volunteer election observer reviews training materials on Nov. 6, 2022, at the Carter Center in Atlanta. (AP Photo/Jeff Amy, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter, center, speaks with journalists and voting station authorities outside a polling station near Juba, southern Sudan, April 13, 2010. (AP Photo/Pete Muller, File) Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter, center, speaks with journalists and voting station authorities outside a polling station near Juba, southern Sudan, April 13, 2010. (AP Photo/Pete Muller, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter stands in a polling station at San Miguelito, Panama, as part of an international delegation of observers under the Council of Freely-Elected Heads of Government on May 7, 1989. (AP Photo/Luis Romero, File) Former U.S. President Jimmy Carter stands in a polling station at San Miguelito, Panama, as part of an international delegation of observers under the Council of Freely-Elected Heads of Government on May 7, 1989. (AP Photo/Luis Romero, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

“If we saw the same conditions in another country that we were seeing in the U.S. — the lack of trust in election institutions, polarization and growing concern of political violence — it is exactly the kind of country we would prioritize to see if we could play a constructive role,” Carroll said.

Faith in U.S. elections, most notably among a large segment of Republican voters, eroded after the 2020 election amid former President Donald Trump’s false claims that Democrats had rigged the vote. There was no evidence of widespread fraud or manipulation of voting machines in that election.

In the 2024 presidential election, which Trump won, the center did some limited observation in New Mexico, Montana and Fulton County, Georgia. In many U.S. states, election observers are limited to political party representatives, with no provisions for nonpartisan, independent groups. The center is working to change that.

Carter’s leadership on democracy issues remains a north star for the center, Carroll said.

“You can help strong systems be in place, but they need to be watched continually. You can never rest on your record on democracy and elections. You always have to be vigilant and keep an eye on the process,” he said.

___ Cassidy reported from Atlanta. Associated Press writers Paola Flores in La Paz, Bolivia; Binaj Gurubacharya in Kathmandu, Nepal; Sean Murphy in Oklahoma City; and Daniel Politi in Buenos Aires, Argentina, contributed to this report.</description><enclosure url="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/852ef70/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3297x2197+0+1/resize/767x511!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F95%2F37%2F58c2c730a5d14287a74598ead5e5%2Fb8f5a0ef56974285a663e981612e9bc9" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/></item><item><title>AP WAS THERE: Carter announces Middle East peace agreement</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/jimmy-carter-camp-david-israel-egypt-6cc9a593003f717df4eb8f7576d37398</link><description>WASHINGTON (AP) — ___

EDITORS: As part of its coverage of the death of former President Jimmy Carter, The Associated Press is looking back at major events in his life. Carter’s success at Camp David negotiating a Mideast Peace agreement between Egypt and Israel was one of his crowning achievements. AP Diplomatic Writer Barry Schweid covered Carter’s announcement in this Sept. 17, 1978, story.

—-

President Carter announced to the world Sunday night that a “framework for peace” in the Middle East had been reached at his summit meeting with Egypt’s Anwar Sadat and Israel’s Menachem Begin.

Flanked by President Sadat and Prime Minister Begin, he said documents signed by the two leaders “will provide that Israel may live in peace within secure borders.”

The far-reaching accord commits Egypt and Israel to work to conclude a peace treaty within three months. The treaty would be the first formal recognition of the Jewish state by any of its Arab neighbors since the creation of Israel in 1948.

President Jimmy Carter stands in front of the billowing flags of Egypt, on the left, and Israel as the national anthems of the three countries are played before the signing of the peace treaty at the White House in Washington, March 26, 1979. (AP Photo, File) President Jimmy Carter stands in front of the billowing flags of Egypt, on the left, and Israel as the national anthems of the three countries are played before the signing of the peace treaty at the White House in Washington, March 26, 1979. (AP Photo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Begin, in a friendly challenge to Sadat, urged that the treaty be concluded before three months elapse. Sadat applauded the overture and nodded in agreement.

Carter said Israel would withdraw its forces from the West Bank of the Jordan River. The agreement allows the Israelis to maintain a security presence in specified bases while ending its military rule of the territory, taken in the Six-Day War of 1967.

Administration officials, who declined to be identified, said no American troops would be involved in the security arrangements negotiated at the summit, although they did not rule out American involvement sometime in the future.

The 1.1 million Palestinian Arabs living on the West Bank and in the Gaza Strip on the Sinai “will have the right to participate in the determination of their own future,” Carter said.

On the Sinai front, Carter said, Israel would withdraw its forces quickly, with the result being establishment of diplomatic relations between the two old foes in a 30-year conflict.

President Jimmy Carter, Israeli Premier Menachem Begin and Egyptian President Anwar Sadat gather with their aides during discussions on Middle East problems at Camp David, Md., in September 1978. (AP Photo, File) President Jimmy Carter, Israeli Premier Menachem Begin and Egyptian President Anwar Sadat gather with their aides during discussions on Middle East problems at Camp David, Md., in September 1978. (AP Photo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Carter’s appearance with Sadat and Begin at the White House was nationally televised. Flags of the United States, Israel and Egypt stood behind them.

The U.S. president, looking back on 13 days of “long negotiation,” acknowledged that at times the talks faltered and it seemed that the patience of Sadat and Begin would run out.

But Carter said results exceeded all expectations.

Sadat, speaking next at a ceremony in the White House East Room, thanked Carter for fulfilling his commitment to serving as a “full partner” in the talks.

Sadat expressed gratitude to Carter for his “spirit and dedication” and concluded with a prayer that the “spirit of Camp David” would mark a new chapter in Middle East history.

Begin, in a tribute to Carter, said “he worked harder than our forefathers did in building the pyramids of Egypt.”

The gentle reference to the Biblical period of Jewish slavery drew appreciative chuckles from the dignitaries on hand.

“The president of the United States won the day,” Begin said. “Peace now celebrates a great victory for the nations of Egypt and Israel and for all mankind.”

President Jimmy Carter, center, is flanked by Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin and Egypt’s President Anwar Sadat as they faced newsmen at the conclusion of their discussions toward Middle East Peace moves at Carter’s Camp David retreat in Maryland in September 1978. (AP Photo, File) President Jimmy Carter, center, is flanked by Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin and Egypt’s President Anwar Sadat as they faced newsmen at the conclusion of their discussions toward Middle East Peace moves at Carter’s Camp David retreat in Maryland in September 1978. (AP Photo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

But before there is peace, Begin noted, Israel and Egypt have three months of negotiations ahead to conclude a peace treaty.

“Mr. President,” Begin said to Carter, “you inscribed your name forever in the history of two ancient people, the people of Egypt and the people of Israel.”

Turning to Sadat, the Israeli prime minister said there was no point in recounting the “saga” of their differences during the negotiations.

“Everything belongs to the past,” Begin said.

Now, once again, Begin said, he could refer to Sadat as “my friend.” Begin and saluted Sadat as a friend after the Egyptian leader’s historic visit to Jerusalem last November. But when the differences deepened after their talk at Ismailia, Egypt, in December, Begin no longer used the phrase.

When Begin concluded his remarks, he embraced Carter and then Sadat. The three leaders then signed the “framework for peace.”

Carter said the framework can be used later by Israel to negotiate peace treaties with her other Arab neighbors, Syria, Jordan and Lebanon.

In this photo provided by the White House, the principals in the Middle East Summit, from left, Egyptian President Anwar Sadat, U.S. President Jimmy Carter, and Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin, meet for the first time at Camp David, Md., Sept, 6, 1978. (White House via AP, File) In this photo provided by the White House, the principals in the Middle East Summit, from left, Egyptian President Anwar Sadat, U.S. President Jimmy Carter, and Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin, meet for the first time at Camp David, Md., Sept, 6, 1978. (White House via AP, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

After signing the documents, the three leaders shook hands.

Although differences remain, the prospect of peace between Egypt and Israel by Christmas was a stunning surprise, made even more dramatic by the deep secrecy imposed during the negotiations.

One question mark remaining was whether the concessions offered by Israel to the Palestinian Arabs living on the West Bank of the Jordan into the peace process.

Carter said he hoped “the foresight and wisdom” demonstrated by Sadat and Begin will guide all nations “as they continue to strive toward peace.”

The three leaders smiled and waved as they boarded a jet helicopter to depart Camp David for Washington. Carter climbed in first. Begin deferred to Sadat and urged the Egyptian leader to board second. The three men and the helicopter were lit by the glare of floodlights.

When the helicopter touched down on the White House south lawn, the three leaders were greeted by some 50 dignitaries and members of the White House staff. Each of the three got a kiss from the president’s wife, Rosalynn.

Senate Majority Leader Robert C. Byrd said Carter asked to explain the agreements to a joint session of Congress at 8 p.m. EDT on Monday.

The administration officials, who declined to be identified, said the documents “provide a framework for continuing negotiations” and not a completed agreement.

Forty issues remain unresolved after the 12-day summit, including the ultimate fate of Israeli settlements in the Sinai and the nature of the final arrangement for the West Bank and the Gaza Strip.

The agreement on the Sinai comes closer to being a final settlement, the officials said. It provides that Israel eventually restore Egyptian sovereignty “throughout the Sinai” and that Egypt will make peace and establish normal relations with Israel.

President Anwar Sadat of Egypt, U.S. President Jimmy Carter and Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin stand for the playing of their National Anthems at the White House in Washington, March 26, 1979, before the signing of the peace treaty between Israel and Egypt. (AP Photo, File) President Anwar Sadat of Egypt, U.S. President Jimmy Carter and Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin stand for the playing of their National Anthems at the White House in Washington, March 26, 1979, before the signing of the peace treaty between Israel and Egypt. (AP Photo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

The Sinai agreement calls for phased withdrawal of Israeli troops, starting as soon as six months from Sunday night and the return of Sinai airfields to Egyptian civilian control.

It commits both Israel and Egypt to agreeing to a treaty within three months, with a major Israeli withdrawal three to nine months after the treaty is signed.

After the first Israeli withdrawal, the two countries agreed to establish normal diplomatic relations, the administration officials said.

The final Israeli withdrawal is to take place two to three years after the signing of the peace treaty. The treaty also is designed to provide security zones for Israel in the Sinai as well as a program of arms reduction in the area.

The major disagreement on the Sinai is the fate of Israeli settlements in captured territory. The officials said Egypt demands that Israel remove the settlements.

Israeli negotiators wanted the issue to be decided during the negotiations, the officials said. But they added that the Israel is agreed to let their parliament decide within two weeks on how the question should be resolved.

The agreement on the West Bank and Gaza Strip is much less specific, reflecting the difficulties in that area.

In that agreement, the officials said, Egypt and Israel agree to a five year transition period during which “the inhabitants will attain full autonomy,” but Israel will be able to station troops in specified bases in both the West Bank and Gaza areas.

The framework leaves unsettled the issues of the final borders between Israel and the new Palestinian entity and whether that entity will be a state, an affiliate of Jordan or something else.

The countries involved will invite Jordan to join their negotiations along with representatives of the Palestinians living in the two territories. Jordan also will be invited to play a “security role” during the period. Israel committed itself to establishing no new settlements in those territories during the negotiations, the officials said.

If and when a final agreement is reached, elected representatives of West Bank and Gaza inhabitants, predominately Palestinians, will have an opportunity to pass judgment on it, the officials said.

They said Israel and Egypt could agree only to exchanging letters on the emotional issue of the fate of Jerusalem. The officials would not disclose what was to be said in those letters.

The fact that Carter was meeting side-by-side with Sadat and Begin suggested that the summit had not ended in failure.

The White House appearance was arranged after Carter had mounted an all-out, 11th hour effort to narrow differences between Egypt and Israel on a peace formula.

As Carter drove for an agreement, facing a Sunday night deadline concurred in by all three leaders, officials of Egypt, Israel and the United States privately indicated he was making progress.

George Sherman, a State Department spokesman, disclosed the arrangement for the joint appearance after a day of negotiating at all levels in the summit delegations.

Declining to say whether the Camp David summit had concluded, Sherman declared he had been authorized to make only a “procedural announcement.”

In his final effort, Carter shuttled between Sadat and Begin and back again. But no three-way meeting was reported before the leaders appeared together for their wrapup announcement.

Carter went to Sadat’s quarters at Camp David for a 45-minute meeting Sunday morning. Then, the White House said, Carter spent six minutes - from 3:27 p.m. to 3:33 p.m. EDT - with Begin.

That session was followed by a second Carter-Sadat meeting. It lasted an hour and 50 minutes.

Israeli sources said, meanwhile, that Sadat also met with Israeli Defense Minister Ezer Weizman.

A White House announcement said “intensive consultations within and among the three delegations continued.”

No plans for a Carter-Begin-Sadat meeting were announced, however. They last met formally on Sept. 7.

In Washington, the president’s wife, Rosalynn, told a White House meeting of Hispanic leaders that Carter “says today Sunday is the last day. It might go to midnight. He just doesn’t know . . . He needs your prayers in these last hours of the summit meeting at Camp David.”

However, in Atlantic City, N.J., President Lloyd McBride of the United Steelworkers Union told a news conference that Carter had put off speaking to the union’s convention from Tuesday to Wednesday. A White House aide, Robert Neuman, said the delay is “due to the summit.”

At Camp David, a White House official confirmed that Carter had postponed his speech one day. The official, who asked that his name not be used, said Carter would be involved in post-summit details even if the summit was concluded by Tuesday.

Asked how Carter would report summit results to the nation, the official said the president had not yet decided. Congressional sources have said the White House has considered a presidential address to Congress or a nationally televised news conference.

Begin declined an invitation to speak, in person or by telephone, to a Sunday afternoon meeting of an Israel Bonds leadership conference in Washington.

A spokesman for the group, Gunther Lawrence, said Begin wanted to maintain a news blackout at the summit as long as the talks were in progress.

While there was no word on specifics, Israeli sources expressed “cautious optimism” after Carter and Begin ended a 45-hour session past midnight Saturday.

One source, who declined to be identified, said “a good atmosphere” characterized the session.

An Egyptian editor, Moussa Sabry of Al Akhbar, reported -- without offering any details -- that an earlier, 2 1/2-hour session between Carter and Sadat had produced a “dramatic development.”

Those upbeat outlooks contrasted with pessimism reflected by the Egyptian press when summit spokesman Jody Powell first announced the 12-day conference would end by Sunday night.

Powell said the leaders were likely to meet again in a three-way session — the first in 10 days -- before the end of the summit. Among items under discussion in the final hours was a wrapup communique. Powell indicated there might be more than one.

As the final countdown began, Carter attended Sunday services conducted at Camp David by Cecil Reed, a Protestant chaplain from nearby Ft. Ritchie, Md.

When Carter set up his separate meetings with Sadat and Begin, sources close to all three delegations reported the negotiations were at a delicate and critical stage.

At that point, Powell said, there was still no agreement on a “framework” for future negotiations between Egypt and Israel. That was Carter’s minimal goal when he invited Sadat and Begin to his secluded retreat in Maryland’s Catoctin Mountains.

Apart from procedural disputes, the two sides apparently had not settled any of the key issues. These center on whether Begin was willing to commit Israel to a withdrawal from the West Bank of the Jordan River and on how Israel’s security would be protected.

Sen. Henry M. Jackson, D-Wash., chairman of the arms control subcommittee, told the Israeli Bonds conference that efforts to include a West Bank settlement in an overall Middle East agreement was a mistake and doomed to failure.

“I am convinced that the Israelis are prepared to return the Sinai to Egypt in exchange for peace,” Jackson said.

Carter proposed the Sunday night deadline and Sadat and Begin concurred, according to Powell, spokesman for all three governments. He said the decision grew out a shared conclusion that the issue in dispute “had been certainly aired.”

Sadat and Begin have not had a face-to-face negotiating session since Sept. 7. Since then, Carter has shuttled between them. Sadat has met with Israeli Foreign Minister Moshe Dayan and Defense Minister Ezer Weizman.

American officials have tried to minimize the long time since the last formal meeting between Sadat and Begin. Still, there were persistent rumors of personal differences between the two leaders. Powell has not denied the rumors directly.

“I simply have not tried to keep a running tab on the personal feelings of these two men,” he said on Friday.</description></item><item><title>Trans trailblazer Sarah McBride navigates a brutal reception in Congress with grace</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/sarah-mcbride-congress-transgender-lgbtq-delaware-9cce7f778e6b57dfdb08986d7410404e</link><description>DOVER, Del. (AP) — It was her last day in session as a Delaware state senator, and Sarah McBride sat in her tiny office at the state Capitol, preparing farewell remarks.

She had made history here, as the first openly transgender state senator in the country. Now she was making history again, recently elected as the first openly transgender member of Congress.

Her political promotion has come during a reckoning for transgender rights, when legislation in Republican-governed states around the country aims to curb their advance. During an election where a deluge of campaign ads and politicians demeaned trans people, McBride still easily won her blue state’s only seat in the U.S. House of Representatives.

But even before she is sworn in on Friday, her reception from congressional Republicans has been tumultuous. Rep. Nancy Mace of South Carolina targeted her by proposing to ban transgender people from U.S. Capitol restrooms that correspond to their gender identity — a ban that House Speaker Mike Johnson, R-La., enacted.

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., celebrates with Assistant Secretary of the Senate Daniel Yngstrom, left, on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., celebrates with Assistant Secretary of the Senate Daniel Yngstrom, left, on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

For her part, McBride tried to defuse the situation, saying she would follow the rules. “I’m not here to fight about bathrooms,” the 34-year-old wrote in a statement.

While some activists want her to fight harder, to those who know her, the move was classic Sarah — a pragmatist with a reputation of bipartisanship, a person who values diplomacy over pugilism.

“There is so much joy and so much awe in having this opportunity, and I will not let anyone take that away from me,” McBride told The Associated Press. “I am simply there to do the job just like anyone else.”

Her political home of the last four years, the Delaware Senate, is small — just 21 members — much like the state itself, not even 100 miles (155 kilometers) from north to south. That proximity creates the kind of collegiality that, while not constant, is often lacking these days in Washington.

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., gives her farewell speech on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., gives her farewell speech on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., lower right corner, at her desk on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., lower right corner, at her desk on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

“We’re a family,” said state Sen. Brian Pettyjohn, a Republican colleague who walked over to hug McBride. “We’re going to disagree on a lot of things, but we don’t have the vitriol.”

In the Delaware chamber, there were last-minute nominees to confirm, and mundane business to finish during the Dec. 16 special session.

In between votes, McBride sat on her office’s burgundy couch, typing on her laptop. A staffer went through papers on her desk. The next day they would remove art from the walls and pack up prized mementos: a wedding photo with McBride’s late husband; a letter from former President Barack Obama; a photograph with the most famous Delaware politician, President Joe Biden.

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., laughs with fellow lawmakers after her farewell speech on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., laughs with fellow lawmakers after her farewell speech on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Back down the hall, on the state Senate floor, McBride’s colleagues in the general assembly sent her off like the popular classmate at graduation. She opened the day with a prayer about “new beginnings and bittersweet endings.”

She ended with a speech of gratitude for her fellow state lawmakers.

“I take with me the hope that I have found here that despite the rancor and the toxicity that we too often see in our politics, that we do genuinely have more in common than what divides us,” McBride said.

She continued, “We can have a politics of grace and not of grandstanding, a politics of progress, not pettiness.”

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., right, is greeted by Alexis Wrease, Delaware Senate majority deputy communications director, center, and Jenna Greenlee, Delaware Senate majority digital communications specialist, left, as she arrives for her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., right, is greeted by Alexis Wrease, Delaware Senate majority deputy communications director, center, and Jenna Greenlee, Delaware Senate majority digital communications specialist, left, as she arrives for her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Early promise and a meteoric rise

Growing up in Wilmington, McBride was the type of child who practiced Democratic political speeches in her bedroom at a makeshift podium.

By high school, she had worked on multiple campaigns, including that of Beau Biden, the president’s late son and former Delaware attorney general.

“She combines a passion for public service with a great intellect, with extraordinary political judgment and messaging ability,” said Jack Markell, the U.S. ambassador to Italy, a former Delaware governor and McBride’s mentor.

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., center, talks with Delaware Senate Republican Minority Whip Brian Pettyjohn from the 19th district on the Senate floor on McBride’s last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., center, talks with Delaware Senate Republican Minority Whip Brian Pettyjohn from the 19th district on the Senate floor on McBride’s last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Though she seemed destined to work in politics, McBride once felt revealing her gender identity would derail those ambitions.

She was 21 and the president of American University’s student government when she came out as transgender, first to her friends and family and later in a public post that went viral.

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., walks from the Senate floor on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., walks from the Senate floor on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Sitting in her Wilmington condo, McBride said, “Coming out was without question the hardest thing that I had ever done up until that point. And yet it was still relatively easy compared to the experiences of so many people.”

Her parents have been her biggest supporters, but they worried for her. One of their first calls after McBride came out was to their pastor, the Rev. Gregory Knox Jones of Westminster Presbyterian, a progressive church where Sarah was a youth elder and Jill Biden is a member.

“We talked about the fact that this was your child. You love your child,” Jones recalled. “You can’t think of losing a son. You’ve gained a daughter.”

David McBride, Sarah’s father, said that kind of support has made all the difference for their family. “Our life and Sarah’s life have been made by the response that we and she got first from our friends, our church, our community.”

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., right, poses for a photo with Delaware State Democrat Senator Marie Pinkney from District 13 on McBride’s last day as a Delaware state senator at Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., right, poses for a photo with Delaware State Democrat Senator Marie Pinkney from District 13 on McBride’s last day as a Delaware state senator at Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

McBride would go on to forge a trail through a rapid series of firsts. During college, she became the first openly transgender woman to intern at the White House. At a reception there, she met and later fell in love with a young lawyer, Andrew Cray, a trans man and LGBTQ+ health policy advocate.

As an activist at 22, McBride was instrumental in helping pass a transgender nondiscrimination law in Delaware. She worked as the spokesperson for the Human Rights Campaign, a leading LGBTQ-rights group. In 2016, she became the first openly trans person to speak at the Democratic National Convention.

To be a first, a historic first, is a privilege and a burden. McBride is quick to point out that she’s more than just the headlines about her gender identity.

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., works in her office on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., works in her office on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More The Rev. Dr. Gregory Knox Jones pauses during an interview with the Associated Press at Westminster Presbyterian Church in Wilmington, Del., Wednesday, Dec. 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) The Rev. Dr. Gregory Knox Jones pauses during an interview with the Associated Press at Westminster Presbyterian Church in Wilmington, Del., Wednesday, Dec. 18, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

“The reality is that I didn’t run to be a first. I didn’t run to make history with an election,” she said.

Her focus is to be the best member of Congress she can be for all of Delaware and the country.

It’s the “only way that I can guarantee that while I may be a first, I’m not the last.”

A photo of U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., with her husband Andy Cray is seen on a shelf in her Wilmington, Del., home, Wednesday, Dec. 18, 2024. Cray died from cancer in 2014. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) A photo of U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., with her husband Andy Cray is seen on a shelf in her Wilmington, Del., home, Wednesday, Dec. 18, 2024. Cray died from cancer in 2014. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

A show pony and a work horse

Before working with McBride, Democratic state Sen. Elizabeth Lockman thought “she was probably a bit of a show pony, so good at presenting herself, public speaking,” and already destined for a larger stage.

“Ok, she is the show pony, but can she be a work horse?” Lockman recalled thinking. “What I like to tell her is that she proved to us that she’s both. She’s probably one of the hardest-working people.”

McBride rarely stops to eat on busy days, instead subsisting on a steady diet of coffee, heavy on the cream and sweetener.

David and Sally McBride, parents of U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., talk during a television interview with the Associated Press at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) David and Sally McBride, parents of U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., talk during a television interview with the Associated Press at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More Dave McBride looks to his daughter, U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Dave McBride looks to his daughter, U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., signs her desk drawer on the Senate floor on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., signs her desk drawer on the Senate floor on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., photographs her desk nameplate on the Senate floor on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., photographs her desk nameplate on the Senate floor on her last day as a Delaware state senator at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

And nowhere is her boundless energy more evident than when she talks about the minutiae of policymaking. She likes kitchen table issues: health care, paid family leave, childcare and affordable housing. In the state Senate, she chaired the health committee and helped expand access to Medicaid and dental care for underserved communities. Most of her bills got bipartisan support.

Pettyjohn, her Republican colleague, appreciated that McBride would often seek conservative members’ input on legislation. “She’s always one to come over, to make that effort to get outside that echo chamber and say, ‘What can we do to polish it up some, to make it better?’”

Her signature accomplishment was helping pass paid family and medical leave in Delaware. It was personal for McBride.

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., gives her farewell speech on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., gives her farewell speech on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Her partner Cray was 27 when he was diagnosed with oral cancer. Within a year, the prognosis was terminal. They moved up their wedding plans. They asked the Rev. Gene Robinson, a friend and the first openly gay Episcopal bishop, to officiate.

They married on the rooftop of their apartment building in August 2014. Cray died four days later at the hospital.

“The experience serving as a caregiver to him left me profoundly changed,” McBride said.

“I think about all of the people who have to deal with what we dealt with or worse, without health insurance, without family support, without paid leave, without jobs that allowed them to continue to pay their rent,” she said. “I just cannot imagine getting through even a fraction of what we went through without the support we had. It is a moral failing of our society and our country.”

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., acknowledges applause after her farewell speech on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., acknowledges applause after her farewell speech on the Senate floor during a special session, her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

A politics of grace

The word “grace” comes up a lot with McBride.

She does everything “with a lot of grace and patience,” Lockman said.

“She handled that with far more grace than I would have shown,” said Mat Marshall, a friend since high school, referencing McBride’s reaction to the congressional bathroom bill.

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., left, and her incoming Deputy Chief of Staff &amp; Communications Director, Michaela Kurinsky-Malos, move out of McBride’s Delaware State Senate office at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Tuesday, Dec. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., left, and her incoming Deputy Chief of Staff &amp; Communications Director, Michaela Kurinsky-Malos, move out of McBride’s Delaware State Senate office at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Tuesday, Dec. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

In her 2018 memoir, McBride wrote a chapter titled “Amazing grace,” about “beautiful acts of kindness” she witnessed during the last weeks of Cray’s life.

“A lot of times when people go through loss, it can be either faith-crushing or faith-affirming. And for me, it was faith-affirming,” she said.

In the room where Cray died, McBride felt God’s presence in a tangible way, like a hand on her shoulder — a comforting manifestation of God’s love that has never left her.

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., center, incoming Deputy Chief of Staff and Communications Director, Michaela Kurinsky-Malos, left, and former field organizer for McBride’s campaign, Sophie Douglas, move out of McBride’s Delaware State Senate office at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Tuesday, Dec. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., center, incoming Deputy Chief of Staff and Communications Director, Michaela Kurinsky-Malos, left, and former field organizer for McBride’s campaign, Sophie Douglas, move out of McBride’s Delaware State Senate office at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Tuesday, Dec. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

In the decade since, she often asks herself, “What would Andy do?” And she seeks to follow his example of compassion and “principled grace” toward anti-LGBTQ politicians. “His kindness, his decency has provided for me a North Star.”

Some activists have criticized McBride for not fighting back more forcefully against the Capitol bathroom ban. She agrees it’s important for transgender people to access public facilities.

“But the people who are talking about bathrooms aren’t trans people,” she said. “The people who are obsessing about bathrooms are right-wing Republicans who are seeking to stoke division and to distract.”

Michaela Kurinsky-Malos, incoming Deputy Chief of Staff and Communications Director for U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., looks through letters for McBride as they pack her office on her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Michaela Kurinsky-Malos, incoming Deputy Chief of Staff and Communications Director for U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., looks through letters for McBride as they pack her office on her last day as a Delaware state senator, at the Delaware Legislative Hall in Dover, Del., Monday, Dec. 16, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

She said she will continue to respond with grace.

“At the end of the day, our ability to have a pluralistic, diverse democracy requires some foundation of kindness and grace,” McBride said. “And I believe in that so strongly that even when it’s difficult, I will seek to summon it.”

U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., speeds her incoming Deputy Chief of Staff and Communications Director, Michaela Kurinsky-Malos, through the halls of Delaware Legislative Hall on a moving cart as they move out of McBride’s Delaware state senate office in Dover, Del., Tuesday, Dec. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) U.S.-Rep.-elect Sarah McBride, D-Del., speeds her incoming Deputy Chief of Staff and Communications Director, Michaela Kurinsky-Malos, through the halls of Delaware Legislative Hall on a moving cart as they move out of McBride’s Delaware state senate office in Dover, Del., Tuesday, Dec. 17, 2024. (AP Photo/Carolyn Kaster) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

___

Associated Press religion coverage receives support through the AP’s collaboration with The Conversation US, with funding from Lilly Endowment Inc. The AP is solely responsible for this content.

___

The Associated Press’ women in the workforce and state government coverage receives financial support from Pivotal Ventures. AP is solely responsible for all content. Find AP’s standards for working with philanthropies, a list of supporters and funded coverage areas at AP.org.</description><enclosure url="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/dd05399/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4964x3307+0+1/resize/767x511!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2Fe5%2Fb1%2Fd9c6beaa769fc440d97cb0548f7d%2Fd50e568f2cd04aafbe997d8e6efc82aa" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/></item><item><title>Trump calls it the ‘center of the universe.’ Mar-a-Lago is a magnet for those seeking influence</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/trump-maralago-musk-brand-bukele-golf-elon-zuckerberg-4a7dfb1cec7607962ed5ca8d3ddfa347</link><description>PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) — The cars begin lining up early in the morning to be screened by Secret Service agents under white tents near the fence that surrounds President-elect Donald Trump’s vast south Florida estate.

Famous figures such as Meta CEO Mark Zuckerberg, Canadian Prime Minister Justin Trudeau and Tesla and X owner Elon Musk pop up at breakfasts, luncheons and other social gatherings held daily at the opulent Mar-a-Lago club.

Over the weekend, Mike Love, one of the original members of the Beach Boys, performed the band’s greatest hits under an outdoor tent there as Trump, trailed by Secret Service agents, wandered through the crowd, swinging his fists to the music, according to videos posted online. At other parts of the evening, he stood next to his wife, Melania, near the pool, bobbing his head to the music.

The resort is the “Center of the Universe,” Trump declared on social media Friday, adding, “Bill Gates asked to come, tonight.” Representatives for Trump and Gates didn’t clarify if the Microsoft co-founder did indeed join the parade of figures making the trip to Mar-a-Lago.

But the president-elect’s post reflects the way his resort, where he’s largely been holed up since the election, has become a salon and celebration for his movement. For the people he’s selected for his administration — and those who seek to get jobs or curry favor with the incoming president — it’s the place to be.

Sightings of those turning up there, usually in photos posted online or in the occasional public event, offer a glimpse into the workings of Trump’s incoming White House and how he is setting priorities for office.

They are also renewing concerns about transparency as the meetings are largely shrouded in secrecy, and raising questions about how Trump benefits financially as club members seeking to influence the new administration stay and eat there.

“It’s kind of unreal,” said James Fishback, an investor who has in recent days launched an investment fund in the club’s tea room and dined at the courtyard. “This is the power center.”

He recalled standing by the pasta table exchanging words with Robert F. Kennedy Jr., whom Trump has chosen to lead the Health Department.

The winter holidays have been another occasion for Trump’s celebrations and for big names to come visit.

A representative for Zuckerberg confirmed he joined Trump for a dinner the night before Thanksgiving. A Christmas Eve video showed Trump in one of the resort’s ballrooms full of guests, dancing to one of his favorite songs, the Village People’s “Y.M.C.A.,” while his daughter Ivanka sat in a gilded chair nearby.

The club held a New Year’s Eve bash Tuesday night that featured Trump, who spoke briefly to reporters near a red carpet rolled out for the occasion. He appeared briefly onstage addressing revelers, who included Love and many of his choices for Cabinet and other posts in his upcoming administration.

Trump said he thought 2025 would be a “great year” and “we’re going to do fantastically well as a country.”

During dinners with friends and family, Trump uses the Spotify account on his tablet to play many of the same tunes that were ubiquitous at his campaign rallies. One night, his guest of honor was Sara Netanyahu, the wife of Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu. Another night, the honor went to Akie Abe, the widow of slain Japanese Prime Minister Shinzo Abe. And, yes, that was Argentine President Javier Milei doing Trump’s “Y.M.C.A.” dance between the tables at a gala dinner.

During the day, Trump often golfs at his nearby course with friends, relatives and allies, like Sen. Lindsey Graham of South Carolina.

Overall, the vibe is a mix of south Florida’s monied social scene overlaid with the power dynamics of an executive job fair.

“He’s surrounded by a lot of old friends,” Graham said. “I just know that everybody I know wants some job.”

Musk has been a constant presence at the club, so much so that Trump’s granddaughter, Kai, wrote on X that he was “achieving uncle status.” Trump has tasked Musk and biotech entrepreneur Vivek Ramaswamy with leading the Department of Government Efficiency, a nongovernmental task force formed to find ways to fire federal workers, cut programs and slash federal regulations.

Kevin Roberts, president of the think tank behind Project 2025, spoke at a December event with investors at the club. One of the guests at the small function was health care executive Dr. Peter Lamelas, later tapped by Trump to be U.S. ambassador to Argentina.

Sometimes Trump relaxes for dinner alongside club members and guests under the yellow and white awnings in the courtyard. Other times, he will address large groups for black-tie events in the ballrooms. At a recent gala for a nonprofit led by Lt. Gen Michael Flynn, the song ″God Bless the U.S.A.,” a favorite of Trump’s, cued the president-elect’s entrance.

“We’re off to a really good start,” Trump told people gathered for the event. He then inquired about the whereabouts of Tom Homan, whom he has tapped to be border czar, and joked that Homan was from “central casting.”

“Just relax, Tom. I want you to relax and get ready for the big push,” Trump said.

Trump shared with the party guests that Mexican President Claudia Sheinbaum, whom he threatened with a 25% tariff on all imported goods unless she does more to tackle illegal border crossings and drug flows, “has made progress.”

At another recent event at Mar-a-Lago, this one hosted by the America First Policy Institute, the ballroom was full of recognizable Trump-world figures such as Kellyanne Conway, who served as counselor to the president, and Charlie Kirk, a conservative activist and founder of Turning Point Action. A copy of the president-elect’s latest book was sitting on the chairs for guests as they arrived in gowns and tuxedos.

As he entered the ballroom, Musk was swarmed by guests, including Kash Patel, whom Trump would later select to lead the FBI, before the tech billionaire took his seat at the center table of the ballroom. Musk was later joined there by Trump and Vice President-elect JD Vance.

“It’s the place to be and the place to be seen,” said Damian Merlo, a political strategist who advises the Salvadoran president, Nayib Bukele. Merlo was at that event as well as another event hosted by the Conservative Political Action Committee.

At a news conference Trump held recently at Mar-a-Lago, the president-elect noted the changed mood compared with his first term, saying, “Everybody wants to be my friend.”

Besides Zuckerberg, Trump has hosted other Silicon Valley executives, including Apple CEO Tim Cook, Google co-founder Sergey Brin, Google CEO Sundar Pichai and Amazon founder Jeff Bezos.

“The top executives, the top bankers, they’re all calling,” Trump said. “It’s like a complete opposite.”

Actor Russell Brand traveled this month to the club to speak at an event, where he sat with actor Mel Gibson, former Fox News personality Tucker Carlson and others. Later in the evening, he stood by a palm tree on the lawn, listening to a bagpiper in a kilt.

Brand later posted a video to X about his experience.

“Pretty amazing,” he said. “Is this real life, or am I in a dream?”

___

Associated Press writer Mary Claire Jalonick in Washington contributed to this report.</description></item><item><title>The rise in mail voting comes with a price, as mismatched signatures lead to ballot rejections</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/voting-elections-mail-ballots-signature-match-6194c3c76b26b0c2737c899f10f89f0b</link><description>HONOLULU (AP) — As with many voters on Maui, Joshua Kamalo thought the race for president wasn’t the only big contest on the November ballot. He also was focused on a hotly contested seat for the local governing board.

He made sure to return his ballot in the virtually all vote-by-mail state early, doing so two weeks before Election Day. A week later, he received a letter telling him the county couldn’t verify his signature on the return envelope, jeopardizing his vote.

And he wasn’t the only one. Two other people at the biodiesel company where he works also had their ballots rejected, as did his daughter. In each case, the county said their signatures didn’t match the ones on file.

“I don’t know how they fix that, but I don’t think it’s right,” said Kamalo, a truck driver who persevered through traffic congestion and limited parking options to get to the county office so he could sign an affidavit affirming that the signature was indeed his.

He said he probably wouldn’t have bothered to fix it if the South Maui county council race wasn’t so close. The co-founder of his employer, Pacific Biodiesel, was the candidate who ended up on the losing side.

Kamalo’s experience is part of a broader problem as mail voting rises in popularity and more states opt to send ballots to all voters. Matching signatures on returned mail ballot envelopes to the official ones recorded at local voting offices can be a tedious process, sometimes done by humans and sometimes through automation, and can lead to dozens, hundreds or even thousands of ballots being rejected.

If the voter can’t correct it in time, the ballot won’t count.

“There’s been a big push toward mail voting over the last few years, and I think the tradeoffs aren’t always clear to voters,” said Larry Norden, an elections and government expert at the Brennan Center for Justice.

He said it’s important for states and local governments to have procedures that ensure large numbers of eligible mail ballot voters aren’t being disenfranchised.

The use of mail ballots exploded in 2020 as states looked for ways to accommodate voters during the COVID-19 pandemic. Eight states and the District of Columbia now have universal mail voting, in which all active registered voters are mailed a ballot unless they opt out.

At least 30 states require election officials to notify voters if there is a problem with their mail ballot and give them a chance to fix — or “cure” — it. Some have complained that the timeframe allowed to do that is too short.

Nevada, a key presidential battleground, is among the states that mails a ballot to all registered voters. In November, county election offices rejected about 9,000 mail ballots primarily because of signature problems.

That didn’t affect the outcome of the state’s presidential race, which Donald Trump won by 46,000 votes, but it could have changed the outcome in some down ballot races. Some state legislative seats in Clark County, which includes Las Vegas and had more than half of the rejected mail ballots, were decided by just several hundred votes. The North Las Vegas City Council race, also in Clark County, was decided by just nine votes.

“We’ve had signature curing problems since we adopted universal mail-in voting during the pandemic in 2020, and it seems to be getting worse,” said Sondra Cosgrove, history professor at the College of Southern Nevada in Las Vegas and executive director of Vote Nevada, a civic organization. “This is something that’s a crisis level that needs to get fixed.”

The potential for signature match problems to affect closes races has led some voting rights groups in the the state to call for an overhaul of the verification process.

“We have to find the best option going forward for people that is more accessible, that gets their votes and ballots counted on time, because it’s crazy when you think about the difference-maker being eight or nine votes,” said Christian Solomon, the state director of Rise Nevada, a youth-led civic engagement group.

Nevada voters already took one step toward a potential fix in November when they approved — by 73% — a constitutional amendment that will require voters to present identification to vote. When voting with a mailed ballot, a driver’s license or Social Security number will be required in addition to the signature. Voters will need to approve the amendment a second time in two years for it to take effect.

Dave Gibbs, president of the Repair the Vote PAC, which wrote the amendment, said he was inspired by a a law passed in 2021 in another presidential swing state, Georgia.

That state ended its signature check process and instead now requires voters to submit their driver’s license number or state identification card number when returning a mailed ballot, said Mike Hassinger, spokesman for the Georgia Secretary of State’s office. Most voting there is done early but in-person.

Critics say such ID requirements would be too burdensome for states, like Hawaii, where mailed ballots account for the vast majority of voting.

On Maui, the number of rejected mail ballots prompted a lawsuit challenging the results of the local county council election, where the winning margin was just 97 votes.

The lawsuit alleges that hundreds of ballots weren’t counted because the county clerk wrongly claimed they arrived in envelopes with signatures that didn’t match the one on file. Attorney Lance Collins said his clients wanted a new election in the race between Tom Cook and his client, Kelly King.

Six voters submitted declarations saying they were told their ballot envelope signature was deficient when, in their view, there was nothing wrong with it.

Collins said under the state’s administrative rules, a returned ballot envelope is presumed to be that of the voter and should be counted unless there is evidence to suggest it’s not the voter’s. He also said the county’s rejection rate was significantly higher than the national average.

Maui County’s attorneys responded in a court filing that its signature verification process followed the law. On Dec. 24, the state Supreme Court unanimously agreed and declared Cook the winner. The justices said the clerk provided voters with reasonable notice and opportunity to correct the deficiency on their ballot envelopes.

Even so, many voters on Maui have shared similar stories about being informed their signatures didn’t match. Resident Grace Min, who was not part of the lawsuit, was among those who received one of the letters.

“I just find it highly unusual that my (ballot) signature would not have matched my signature,” she said.

She had been paying particular attention to the county government race that she knew would be close, so it was important for her to make sure her vote was counted. She emailed an affidavit confirming the ballot was hers, but also had questions about the verification process and was concerned the time allowed for curing ballots was so short.

“I just have to imagine there had to have been people who didn’t fix their signature,” Min said, “and that doesn’t seem very fair.”

___

The Associated Press receives support from several private foundations to enhance its explanatory coverage of elections and democracy. See more about AP’s democracy initiative here. The AP is solely responsible for all content.</description></item><item><title>Pentagon chief loses bid to reject 9/11 plea deals</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/sept-11-plea-deals-guantanamo-austin-279abd0342a84dc2694941c07f51c6bb</link><description>WASHINGTON (AP) — A military appeals court has ruled against Defense Secretary Lloyd Austin’s effort to throw out the plea deals reached for Khalid Sheikh Mohammed and two other defendants in the 9/11 attacks, a U.S. official said.

The decision puts back on track the agreements that would have the three men plead guilty to one of the deadliest attacks on the United States in exchange for being spared the possibility of the death penalty. The attacks by al-Qaida killed nearly 3,000 people on Sept. 11, 2001, and helped spur U.S. invasions of Afghanistan and Iraq in what the George W. Bush administration called its war on terror.

The military appeals court released its ruling Monday night, according to the U.S. official, who was not authorized to discuss the matter publicly and spoke on condition of anonymity.

Military prosecutors and defense attorneys for Mohammed, the accused mastermind of the attacks, and two co-defendants reached the plea agreements after two years of government-approved negotiations. The deals were announced late last summer.

Supporters of the plea agreements see them as a way of resolving the legally troubled case against the men at the U.S. military commission at Guantanamo Bay naval base in Cuba. Pretrial hearings for Mohammed, Walid bin Attash and Mustafa al-Hawsawi have been underway for more than a decade.

Much of the focus of pretrial arguments has been on how torture of the men while in CIA custody in the first years after their detention may taint the overall evidence in the case.

Within days of news of the plea deal this summer, Austin issued a brief order saying he was nullifying them.

He cited the gravity of the 9/11 attacks in saying that as defense secretary, he should decide on any plea agreements that would spare the defendants the possibility of execution.

Defense lawyers said Austin had no legal authority to reject a decision already approved by the Guantanamo court’s top authority and said the move amounted to unlawful interference in the case.

The military judge hearing the 9/11 case, Air Force Col. Matthew McCall, had agreed that Austin lacked standing to throw out the plea bargains after they were underway. That had set up the Defense Department’s appeal to the military appeals court.

Austin now has the option of taking his effort to throw out the plea deals to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit. The Pentagon did not immediately respond to a request for comment.

Separately, the Pentagon said it had repatriated one of the longest-held detainees at the Guantanamo military prison, a Tunisian man who U.S. authorities approved for transfer more than a decade ago.

Ridah bin Saleh al-Yazidi’s return to Tunisia leaves 26 men at Guantanamo. That’s down from a peak population of about 700 Muslim men detained abroad and brought to the prison in the years after the Sept. 11 attacks.

Al-Yazidi’s repatriation leaves 14 men awaiting transfer to other countries after U.S. authorities waived any prosecution and cleared them as security risks.

The Biden administration, pressed by rights groups to free remaining Guantanamo detainees held without charge, transferred out three other men this month. The U.S. says it is searching for suitable and stable countries willing to receive the remaining 14.

In a statement, the U.S. military said it had worked with authorities in Tunisia for the “responsible transfer” of al-Yazidi. He had been a prisoner at Guantanamo since 2002, when the U.S. began sending Muslim detainees taken abroad there.

Al-Yazidi is the last of a dozen Tunisian men once held at Guantanamo.

Of those remaining at Guantanamo, seven — including Mohammed and his 9/11 co-defendants — face active cases. Two others of the 26 total have been convicted and sentenced by the military commission.

___

AP reporter Tara Copp contributed from Washington.</description></item><item><title>Woman burned to death in New York subway is identified as 57-year-old from New Jersey</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/new-york-subway-burning-woman-688e2ebd46f0eb8f5c9e3430cf2b4bd5</link><description>NEW YORK (AP) — The woman who died after being set on fire in a New York subway train this month was a 57-year-old from New Jersey, police announced Tuesday.

The woman, Debrina Kawam, had worked at the pharmaceutical giant Merck in from 2000 until 2002, but her life at some point took a rocky turn. She had briefly been in a New York homeless shelter after moving to the city recently, the Department of Social Services said. It did not say when.

Police had an address for Kawam in Toms River, a community on the Jersey Shore, and authorities said they notified her family about her Dec. 22 death. The Associated Press left messages Tuesday for possible relatives.

“Hearts go out to the family — a horrific incident to have to live through,” Mayor Eric Adams said at an unrelated news briefing.

It came hours before another harrowing act of violence on the nation’s busiest subway system.

A 45-year-old man was pushed onto the tracks ahead of an oncoming train at a station under Manhattan’s Chelsea neighborhood about 1:30 p.m., police said. The man was taken to a hospital in critical condition, and police said they had a person of interest in custody.

Personal safety in the subways is generally comparable to safety in the city as a whole. But life-threatening crimes such as stabbings and shoves spread alarm about the trains that have carried more than 1 billion riders over the course of this year.

Police figures show major crimes on subways were down this year through November, compared with the same period last year, but killings rose from five to nine.

In Karam’s case, prosecutors have said she was asleep on a subway train that was stopped at a station in Brooklyn’s Coney Island when her clothes were set ablaze by a stranger, Sebastian Zapeta.

Zapeta, 33, allegedly fanned the flames with a shirt, engulfing her in the blaze, before sitting on a platform bench and watching as she burned.

New York City Mayor Eric Adams held an end of year press conference on Tuesday, addressing the incident where a woman died after being set on fire while inside a New York subway train.

Identifying the victim proved to be a challenge, and authorities said Friday that they were still using forensics and video surveillance to trace her.

AP AUDIO: New York Police identify woman burned to death inside subway train AP correspondent Julie Walker reports New York Police have identified the woman burned to death inside a subway train as a 57-year-old from New Jersey.

Zapeta has been been indicted on murder and arson charges. He has not entered a plea, and his lawyer has declined to comment outside court.

Federal immigration officials say Zapeta is from Guatemala and entered the U.S. illegally. An address for him given by police matches a shelter that provides housing and substance abuse support.

Zapeta was arrested after police circulated images of a suspect and received a tip from a group of high school students.

Prosecutors have said Zapeta subsequently told police that he was the man in surveillance photos and videos of the fire being ignited, but that he drinks a lot of liquor and does not know what happened.

He is currently jailed, and his next court date is Jan. 7.

While it is not clear why Kawam was asleep in a subway car, New York’s subways often unofficially function as a refuge for homeless people. In theory, legal settlements give homeless individuals a broad right to shelter in the city, but some turn to the trains if they are unable to stay in shelters or fearful about safety in them.

On the morning of the fire, temperatures were around 20 degrees Fahrenheit (minus 6.5 Celsius) and had been below freezing for 24 hours, according to data from nearby Brooklyn weather stations.

“No matter where she lived, that should not have happened,” the mayor said.

The social services department said it would amplify its efforts to reach and help homeless people on streets and subways and encourage them to use shelters.

___

This story has corrected Kawam’s age based on updated information from the police. She was 57, not 61.</description></item><item><title>The dill of a lifetime? In a nation that’s enduring its own sour patch, the pickle dominated 2024</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/pickle-trends-2024-dill-food-snack-44e8539f7e16d86c3ccf625e61553262</link><description>SHARPSBURG, Pa. (AP) — When did we know for sure?

Was it April, when Nature Made introduced its pickle-flavored gummy vitamins? Was it November, when Petco’s “Pickle Mania” promotion offered 26 different pickle-themed toys for dogs and cats? Maybe it was the December day that a food scholar was heard to utter, “Everyone can kind of see their needs met by pickles.”

Or perhaps it was just a couple weeks ago, when Instagram chef itsmejuliette (no stranger to online pickle activities) posted a cheeky challenge on her “cooking with no rules” feed: “this is your sign to surprise your neighbor with a pickle wreath.” More than 70,000 people liked her style, or at least her post.

At the intersection of health and edginess, traditionalism and hipsterism, global culture and the American stomach, the pickle in 2024 found itself caught in a mealstrom of words like “viral” and “trending” just as its food-as-fetish-object cousins — bacon and ranch dressing, notably — experienced in years past. Prepared Foods, an industry newsletter, said it outright in September: “The pickle obsession is at an all-time high.”

Tangy Pickle Doritos. Grill Mates Dill Pickle Seasoning for your steak. Portable pouches of pickles. Pickle mayonnaise, pickle hummus, pickle cookies, pickle gummies. Spicy pickle challenges. Pickleback shots at the bar. Pickle juice and Dr. Pepper, heaven help us. Corn puffs colored and flavored like pickles and called, naturally, Pickle Balls. In Pittsburgh, the cradle of the modern American pickle (talkin’ to you, H.J. Heinz), a summer festival called Picklesburgh that draws aficionados of the sour and the puckery from several states away for copious amounts of pickle beer washed down by brine, or vice versa.

As 2025 begins, two possible conclusions present themselves. First: The previously nobrow pickle has embedded its sour self at the nucleus of the American gastro-zeitgeist for the foreseeable future. Second: This maybe has played itself out, and the pickle has (to mix a metaphor) jumped the shark.

But let’s not get ahead of ourselves.

More of us are living the life of brine

“I think pickling in general has had a resurgence,” says Emily Ruby, who would know. She is a curator and expert on the history of the Heinz company for the Heinz History Center in Pittsburgh, a couple miles downriver from this industrial borough where Henry J. Heinz churned out his first packaged pickles in the 19th century. Indeed, pickles are now a $3.1 billion annual market in the United States and growing consistently.

Let’s dispense with the obvious hanging question. In short: Sour nation, sour mood, sour foods? Maybe just a little.

“It’s been a scary few years for a lot of people. In 2024 we needed something we could agree on. Maybe it’s pickles,” says Alex Plakias, an associate professor at Hamilton College in New York who teaches the philosophy of food.

“I was surprised at how the pickle could be all things to all people,” says Plakias, whose most recent book is about awkwardness. “All these different food identities in 2024, and no matter who you think of, pickles can be for them.”

To see how that might have happened, we can look to the potent pathways of marketing and social media.

The garden-variety American cucumber pickle is crunchy and sour, with an aggressive taste of its own but a clear elasticity that accommodates other “flavor profiles” (Ghost pepper pickles! Garlic pickles! Horseradish pickles! Bread and butter chips!). They’re also absurdly low fat — the rare food trend that’s not outright bad for you — and some offer the probiotic benefits of fermentation. Key marketing points all.

From a positioning perspective, somehow the pickle exists at the crossroads of homey-slash-traditional (Mom, Lower East Side, preserves, harvests) and edgy-slash-slightly subversive (sour, intense flavors, startup pickle factories in reclaimed industrial neighborhoods).

“It’s not like I come from a long line of picklers. But I realized that a cucumber is a blank slate and you get to paint it with all kinds of different brines and spices and salts and sugars,” says John Patterson, who founded Pittsburgh Pickle with his brothers out of a church kitchen a decade ago.

“A pickle is something you can rely on and count on,” he says. “A pickle is always funny, for some reason. A pickle is never nefarious or mean. It’s a peaceful, wholesome business to be in.”

(Of the cucumber itself, he has this to say: “It’s almost like God intended them to be pickled.”)

The pickle is becoming an immersive experience

The pickle is also, let’s be candid, usually green and bumpy and intrinsically unattractive. That means even social-video newbies don’t need precision lighting to crank out reasonably compelling pickle content.

Credit — or blame — TikTok for some of the frenzy. Watching the meticulous chronicling of pickle-cake baking, pickle-wreath making and pickle-pizza crafting, you get the sense the social platform was made as much for dills as for dancing. Pickle videos there regularly top 2 million viewers, and as of this week TikTok reported more than 251 million pieces of pickle content for the snacking.

Then there is the Great Glickle Surge of 2024 — another social media oddity that involves someone pouring “edible glitter” (who knew?) into a jar of pickles and making “glickles” — ostensibly a sexier, blingier, even Instagrammier version of pickles (again, who knew?).

Finally, COVID likely played a pivotal role. After years of rising locavore ethos, the pandemic’s forced inward focus in 2020 and 2021 led many Americans to revisit DIY approaches to food, including baking sourdough bread and, yes, pickling things. It’s what Nora Rubel, who researches food and culture, calls “an embrace of ‘grandmothercore’ culture” by, well, grandchildren. “Gen Z is taking pickles as their thing. This is the new avocado toast,” says Rubel, a professor of Jewish studies at the University of Rochester.

“Pickles are also kind of funny. They’re just sort of goofy. You can make a lot of puns about pickles. It’s intense flavor, but there’s also a kind of silliness about them,” Rubel says. (She also was heard to say: “The sweet pickle is something that’s very deceptive and upsetting to me.”)

If you’re seeing a thread emerging, it’s this — not entirely new, but worth repeating: Packaged food is no longer positioned as merely something to eat. Instead, like the most immersive restaurants, these days it often presents itself as a multimedia experience — something to be talked about and reveled in, to join likeminded communities over, to incorporate into your own personality. Lifestyle pickles, as it were.

“It symbolizes how we engage with food in daily life and with each other in 2024,” says MinJi (MJ) Kim, an assistant professor of communication at Flagler College in Florida who studies how media affects people’s food choices.

“Sour has duality. When milk or meat or vegetables develop a sour smell, it signals spoilage. It’s a natural warning system. We equate sourness with risk,” Kim says. “On the other hand, when sourness is intentional — lemons, cider vinegar, greek yogurt — it becomes a marker of health and appeal. It shifts the perception of sourness from risk to something acceptable.”

There you have it: sourness as acceptable, delicious, even worthy of obsession.

So as the popularity of pickleball — no direct relation — continues to spike, as fried pickles transcend their novelty status and become bar-food stalwarts across the land, and as someone’s pet plays with one of 26 pickle holiday toys, we’ll leave you with two dueling thoughts as America crunches its way into a new year.

From Rubel, this: “You can get pickle everything now. This is really my time.”

And from Delish, the food website, this: “Can we give pickles a break in 2025? They’re tired. And we’re tired for them.”

___

Ted Anthony, director of new storytelling and newsroom innovation at The Associated Press, writes frequently about food.</description></item><item><title>A new year dawns on a Middle East torn by conflict and change</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/middle-east-syria-lebanon-gaza-war-israel-3480c8519737dcdde8a32b624bc528a9</link><description>DAMASCUS (AP) — In Damascus, the streets were buzzing with excitement Tuesday as Syrians welcomed in a new year that seemed to many to bring a promise of a brighter future after the unexpected fall of Bashar Assad’s government weeks earlier.

While Syrians in the capital looked forward to a new beginning after the ousting of Assad, the mood was more somber along Beirut’s Mediterranean promenade, where residents shared cautious hopes for the new year, reflecting on a country still reeling from war and ongoing crises.

War-weary Palestinians in Gaza who lost their homes and loved ones in 2024 saw little hope that 2025 would bring an end to their suffering.

The last year was a dramatic one in the Middle East, bringing calamity to some and hope to others. Across the region, it felt foolish to many to attempt to predict what the next year might bring.

In Damascus, Abir Homsi said she is optimistic about a future for her country that would include peace, security and freedom of expression and would bring Syrian communities previously divided by battle lines back together.

“We will return to how we once were, when people loved each other, celebrated together whether it is Ramadan or Christmas or any other holiday — no restricted areas for anyone,” she said.

But for many, the new year and new reality carried with it reminders of the painful years that came before.

Abdulrahman al-Habib, from the eastern Syrian city of Deir el-Zour, had come to Damascus in hopes of finding relatives who disappeared after being arrested under Assad’s rule. He was at the capital’s Marjeh Square, where relatives of the missing have taken to posting photos of their loved ones in search of any clue to their whereabouts.

“We hope that in the new year, our status will be better ... and peace will prevail in the whole Arab world,” he said.

In Lebanon, a tenuous ceasefire brought a halt to fighting between Israel and the Hezbollah militant group a little over a month ago. The country battered by years of economic collapse, political instability and a series of calamities since 2019, continues to grapple with uncertainty, but the truce has brought at least a temporary return to normal life.

Some families flocked to the Mzaar Ski Resort in the mountains northeast of Beirut on Tuesday to enjoy the day in the snow even though the resort had not officially opened.

“What happened and what’s still happening in the region, especially in Lebanon recently, has been very painful,” said Youssef Haddad, who came to ski with his family. “We have great hope that everything will get better.”

On Beirut’s seaside corniche, Mohammad Mohammad from the village of Marwahin in southern Lebanon was strolling with his three children.

“I hope peace and love prevail next year, but it feels like more (challenges) await us,” he said.

Mohammad was among the tens of thousands displaced during more than a year of conflict between Hezbollah and Israel. Now living in Jadra, a town that was also bombarded during the conflict, he awaits the end of a 60-day period, after which the Israeli army is required to withdraw under the conditions of a French and U.S.-brokered ceasefire.

“Our village was completely destroyed,” Mohammad said. His family would spend a quiet evening at home, he said. This year “was very hard on us. I hope 2025 is better than all the years that passed.”

In Gaza, where the war between Hamas and Israel has killed more than 45,500 Palestinians, brought massive destruction and displaced most of the enclave’s population, few saw cause for optimism in the new year.

“The year 2024 was one of the worst years for all Palestinian people. It was a year of hunger, displacement, suffering and poverty,” said Nour Abu Obaid, a displaced woman from northern Gaza.

Obaid, whose 10-year-old child was killed in a strike in the so-called “humanitarian zone” in Muwasi, said she didn’t expect anything good in 2025. “The world is dead,” she said. “We do not expect anything, we expect the worst.”

The war was sparked by the Oct. 7, 2023 Hamas-led attack on southern Israel in which militants killed around 1,200 people and abducted some 250 others.

Ismail Salih, who lost his home and livelihood, expressed hopes for an end to the war in 2025 so that Gaza’s people can start rebuilding their lives.

The year that passed “was all war and all destruction,” he said. “Our homes are gone, our trees are gone, our livelihood is lost.”

In the coming year, Salih said he hopes that Palestinians can “live like the rest of the people of the world, in security, reassurance and peace.”

___

Shurafa reported from Muwasi, Gaza and Jo from Beirut. Associated Press writers Sally Abou AlJoud and Abby Sewell in Beirut and Fadi Tawil in Kfardebian, Lebanon, contributed to this report.</description></item><item><title>Chief Justice John Roberts defends judicial independence, says it is under threat in several ways</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/supreme-court-chief-justice-john-roberts-1e11fa540245a8c629c90772674ea8f7</link><description>WASHINGTON (AP) — Chief Justice John Roberts issued a defense Tuesday of judicial independence, which he said is under threat from intimidation, disinformation and the prospect of public officials defying court orders.

Roberts laid out his concerns in his annual report on the federal judiciary. It was released after a year where the nation’s court system was unusually enmeshed in a closely fought presidential race, with then-Republican presidential candidate Donald Trump assailing the integrity of judges who ruled against him as he faced criminal charges for which he denied wrongdoing.

Trump won the race following a landmark Supreme Court immunity decision penned by Roberts that, along with another high court decision halting efforts to disqualify him from the ballot, removed obstacles to his election.

The immunity decision was criticized by Democrats like President Joe Biden, who later called for term limits and an enforceable ethics code following criticism over undisclosed trips and gifts from wealthy benefactors to some justices.

Roberts, for his part, introduced his letter by recounting a story about King George III stripping colonial judges of lifetime appointments, an order that was “not well received.”

Trump is now readying for a second term as president with an ambitious conservative agenda, elements of which are likely to be legally challenged and end up before the court whose conservative majority includes three justices appointed by Trump during his first term.

Roberts and Trump clashed in 2018 when the chief justice rebuked the president for denouncing a judge who rejected his migrant asylum policy as an “Obama judge.”

In 2020, Roberts criticized comments made by Senate Democratic leader Chuck Schumer while the Supreme Court was considering a high-profile abortion case.

Roberts didn’t mention Trump, Biden or any other specific leader in this year’s annual report. Instead, he wrote generally that even if court decisions are unpopular or mark a defeat for a presidential administration, other branches of government must be willing to enforce them to ensure the rule of law.

He pointed to the Brown v. Board of Education decision that desegregated schools in 1954 as one that needed federal enforcement in the face of resistance from southern governors.

“It is not in the nature of judicial work to make everyone happy,” he wrote.

The chief justice also decried elected officials across the political spectrum who have “raised the specter of open disregard for federal court rulings.”

“Attempts to intimidate judges for their rulings in cases are inappropriate and should be vigorously opposed,” he wrote.

While public officials and others have the right to criticize rulings, they should also be aware that their statements can “prompt dangerous reactions by others.”

Threats targeting federal judges have more than tripled over the last decade, according to U.S. Marshals Service statistics. State court judges in Wisconsin and Maryland were killed at their homes in 2022 and 2023, Roberts wrote.

“Violence, intimidation, and defiance directed at judges because of their work undermine our Republic, and are wholly unacceptable,” he wrote.

Roberts also pointed to disinformation about court rulings as a threat to judges’ independence, saying that social media can magnify distortions and even be exploited by “hostile foreign state actors” to exacerbate divisions.

Against a backdrop of those heightened divisions, Americans’ confidence in the country’s judicial system and courts has dropped to a record low of 35%, a Gallup poll found.</description></item><item><title>Trump says he is planning to attend Jimmy Carter’s funeral</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/trump-carter-funeral-new-years-eve-2d7fc241ff0be4eb99b9c6547010bd03</link><description>PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) — President-elect Donald Trump said Tuesday that he’s planning to attend the funeral of former President Jimmy Carter.

Asked about it as he walked into a New Year’s Eve party at his Mar-a-Lago club in Florida, Trump responded, “I’ll be there.” Pressed on whether he’d spoken to members of Carter’s family, Trump said he’d rather not say.

Funeral services honoring Carter, who died Sunday at 100, will be held in Georgia and Washington, beginning Jan. 4 and concluding Jan. 9.

Trump was a frequent and fierce critic of Carter on the campaign trail ahead of November’s election, using the rising inflation rates of the 1970s to unfavorably compare President Joe Biden to Carter and his administration.

But the president-elect was gracious about the former president in posts on his social media site after Carter’s death Sunday, writing that the nation “owed him a debt of gratitude.”

“While I strongly disagreed with him philosophically and politically, I also realized that he truly loved and respected our Country, and all it stands for,” Trump wrote of Carter. “He worked hard to make America a better place, and for that I give him my highest respect.”

Wearing a tuxedo as he entered the festivities, Trump took a few minutes of questions from reporters on various topics. He was asked about the possibility of a ceasefire in Israel’s war with Hamas in Gaza, but said only, “We’re going to see what happens.”

The president-elect added of hostages seized more than a year ago by Hamas, “I’ll put it this way: They better let the hostages come back soon.”

Trump also said he thought 2025 would be a “great year” and “we’re going to do fantastically well as a country.”

“There’s a whole light over the whole world, not just our country. They’re a lot of happy people,” Trump said of recent weeks.

Asked about his resolutions for the new year, Trump said, “I just want everybody to be happy, healthy and well.”

Trump later took the stage to briefly address the crowd ringing in the new year at Mar-a-Lago and promised “to do a great job as your president.”

Biden, for his part, spent New Year’s Eve celebrating the wedding of his niece Missy Owens in Greenville, Delaware, followed by the reception in Kennett Square, Pennsylvania. Biden and first lady Jill Biden cut short their traditional holiday trip to the U.S. Virgin Islands to attend the ceremony.

__

Associated Press writer Darlene Superville in Greenville, Delaware, contributed.</description></item><item><title>South Korea air crash investigators extract black box data as grieving families mourn the victims</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/korea-plane-crash-bereaved-families-boeing-904b15ec24a543c99e3c8e416af3a0a7</link><description>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) — Grieving relatives of the victims of the South Korea plane crash gathered at the site to pay respects to their loved ones on New Year’s Day, as officials said they’ve extracted data from one of the retrieved black boxes to find the exact cause of the crash.

All but two of the 181 passengers and crew on board the Boeing 737-800 operated by Jeju Air died when it crashed at Muan International Airport, in southern South Korea, on Sunday.

Video showed the aircraft without its landing gear deployed landing on its belly at high speed and then skidding off the end of the runaway into a concrete fence and bursting into flames. The footage showed the plane was experiencing an apparent engine problem in addition to the landing gear malfunction.

Investigators say the pilot received a warning from air traffic controllers of possible bird strikes and the plane issued a distress signal before the crash.

The Transport Ministry said in a statement Wednesday that it has completed works to extract data from the cockpit voice recorder — one of the two black boxes recovered from the wreckage. It said the data would be converted into audio files. A damaged flight data recorder will be sent to the United States for an analysis, the ministry added.

All of the victims were South Korean, except for two Thais nationals, with many returning from Bangkok after Christmas holidays.

The bereaved families visited the site on Wednesday for the first time since the crash for an emotional memorial service. They were bused to the site where they took turns laying white flowers. Many knelt and bowed deeply before a memorial table laid with food, including “ddeokguk,” a Korean rice cake soup eaten on New Year’s Day.

The Transport Ministry said authorities have completed the complicated process of identifying all 179 victims. It said the government has so far handed over 11 bodies to relatives.

The country is observing seven days of national mourning following the deadliest disaster in South Korea’s aviation history in decades.

The government has begun safety inspections of all 101 Boeing 737-800s operated by the country’s domestic airlines. On Tuesday, a team of U.S. investigators, including representatives from Boeing, examined the crash site.

Officials have said they will consider whether the airport’s localizer — a set of antennas housed in a concrete fence at the end of the runway designed to guide aircraft during landings — should have been constructed with lighter materials that would break more easily upon impact.</description></item><item><title>Ukraine halts transit of Russian gas to Europe after a prewar deal expired</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/russia-ukraine-war-gas-transit-supplies-gazprom-7775fea34a7be9723b991d835a7ebd6f</link><description>KYIV, Ukraine (AP) — Ukraine on Wednesday halted Russian gas supplies to European customers through its pipeline network after a prewar transit deal expired at the end of 2024 and almost three years into Moscow’s all-out invasion of its neighbor.

Even as Russian troops and tanks moved into Ukraine in February 2022, Russian natural gas kept flowing through the country’s pipeline network — set up when Ukraine and Russia were both part of the Soviet Union — to Europe, under a five-year agreement.

Russia’s state-owned energy giant Gazprom earned money from the gas and Ukraine collected transit fees.

Ukraine’s energy minister, Herman Halushchenko, confirmed Kyiv had stopped the transit “in the interest of national security.”

“This is a historic event. Russia is losing markets and will incur financial losses,” Halushchenko said Wednesday on the Telegram messaging app. “Europe has already decided to phase out Russian gas, and (this) aligns with what Ukraine has done today.”

At a summit in Brussels last month, Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy vowed that Kyiv would not allow Moscow to use the transits to earn “additional billions ... on our blood, on the lives of our citizens.” However, he briefly held open the possibility of the gas flows continuing if payments to Russia were withheld until the war ends.

Gazprom said in a statement Wednesday it “has no technical and legal possibility” of sending gas through Ukraine, due to Kyiv’s refusal to extend the deal.

Before the war, Russia supplied nearly 40% of the European Union’s pipeline natural gas. Gas flowed through four pipeline systems, one under the Baltic Sea, one through Belarus and Poland, one through Ukraine and one under the Black Sea through Turkey to Bulgaria.

After the war started, Russia cut off most supplies through the Baltic and Belarus-Poland pipelines, citing disputes over a demand for payment in rubles. The Baltic pipeline was blown up in an act of sabotage, but details of the attack remain murky.

The Russian cutoff caused an energy crisis in Europe. Germany had to shell out billions of euros to set up floating terminals to import liquefied natural gas that comes by ship, not by pipeline. Users cut back as prices soared. Norway and the United States filled the gap, becoming the two largest suppliers.

Europe viewed the Russian cutoff as energy blackmail and has outlined plans to completely eliminate Russian gas imports by 2027.

Zelenskyy said Wednesday that halting the transits would see Moscow lose “one of the most profitable and geographically accessible markets” for its gas. In a post on X, he said Russia was “resorting to cynical blackmail of partners.”

Russia’s share of the EU pipeline natural gas market dropped sharply to about 8% in 2023, according to data from the EU Commission. The Ukrainian transit route served EU members Austria and Slovakia, which long got the bulk of their natural gas from Russia but have recently scrambled to diversify supplies.

Gazprom halted supplies to Austria’s OMV in mid-November over a contractual dispute, but gas flows through Ukraine’s pipelines continued as other customers stepped in. Slovakia this year inked deals to begin buying natural gas from Azerbaijan, and also to import U.S. liquefied natural gas through a pipeline from Poland.

Among the hardest-hit will be EU candidate country Moldova, which was receiving Russian gas via Ukraine and has brought in emergency measures as residents brace for a harsh winter and looming power cuts.

Separately from Kyiv’s decision to let the transit deal expire, Gazprom said last month it will halt gas supplies to Moldova starting on Jan. 1, citing unpaid debt. Gazprom has said Moldova owes close to $709 million for past gas supplies, a figure the country has fiercely disputed.

Heating and hot water supplies were abruptly cut off Wednesday to households in Transnistria, Moldova’s breakaway region that has for decades hosted Russian troops, as Russian natural gas stopped flowing to the territory, local transit operator Tiraspoltransgaz-Transnistria said.

In an online statement, the company urged residents to gather household members together in a single room, hang blankets over windows and balcony doors, and use electric heaters. It said some key facilities, including hospitals, were exempt from the cuts.

On Dec. 13, Moldova’s parliament voted in favor of imposing a state of emergency in the energy sector, as fears mounted that the gas shortages could trigger a humanitarian crisis in Transnistria, for decades dependent on Russian energy supplies.

Many observers have predicted that the looming energy shortage could force people in the separatist territory to travel to Moldova proper, seeking basic amenities to get through the harsh winter and placing further strain on resources.

Moldova, Ukraine and EU politicians have repeatedly accused Moscow of weaponizing energy supplies.

On Wednesday, Polish Foreign Minister Radek Sikorski called Ukraine’s move to halt supplies a win for those opposed to the Kremlin’s policies. In a post on X, Sikorski accused Moscow of systematic attempts to “blackmail Eastern Europe with the threat of cutting off gas supplies,” including through a Baltic pipeline bypassing Ukraine and Poland and running directly to Germany.

Slovakian Prime Minister Robert Fico claimed Wednesday the end of gas flows via Ukraine “will drastically affect us all in the EU but not Russia.”

Fico, whose views on Russia have sharply differed from the European mainstream, has previously criticized Kyiv’s refusal to extend the transit deal, and threatened to end electricity supplies to Ukraine in response.

Moscow can still send gas to Hungary, as well as non-EU states Turkey and Serbia, through the TurkStream pipeline across the Black Sea.

The steady reduction of Russian gas supplies to European countries has also spurred them to hasten the integration of Ukraine’s energy grids with its neighbors to the west.

Last week, private Ukrainian energy utility DTEK said it had received its first shipment of liquefied natural gas from the U.S., delivered through a newly expanded network spanning six countries from Greece to Ukraine — a significant step in reducing regional dependence on Russian energy.

Separately, overnight into New Year’s Day, Russia launched a drone strike on Kyiv that left two people dead under the rubble of a damaged building, according to the city administration. At least six people were wounded across the Ukrainian capital, according to Mayor Vitali Klitschko.

Russian shelling also killed a man and wounded two women in Ukraine’s southern city of Kherson, regional authorities reported.

___

Kozlowska reported from London. Associated Press writers Derek Gatopoulos in Athens, Greece, and Karel Janicek in Prague contributed to this report.</description></item><item><title>Islamic State-inspired driver expressed desire to kill before deadly New Orleans rampage, Biden says</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/new-orleans-car-bourbon-street-63a1b43d615af365cb8ba6f5f0583eca</link><description>NEW ORLEANS (AP) — A U.S. Army veteran driving a pickup truck that bore the flag of the Islamic State group wrought carnage on New Orleans’ raucous New Year’s celebration, killing 15 people as he steered around a police blockade and slammed into revelers before being shot dead by police.

The FBI said it was investigating the attack early Wednesday as a terrorist act and did not believe the driver acted alone. Investigators found guns and what appeared to be an improvised explosive device in the vehicle, along with other devices elsewhere in the city’s famed French Quarter.

President Joe Biden said Wednesday evening that the FBI found videos that the driver had posted to social media hours before the attack in which he said he was inspired by the Islamic State group and expressed a desire to kill.

The rampage turned festive Bourbon Street into a macabre mayhem of maimed victims, bloodied bodies and pedestrians fleeing for safety inside nightclubs and restaurants. In addition to the dead, dozens of people were hurt. A college football playoff game at the nearby Superdome was postponed until Thursday.

Zion Parsons, 18, of Gulfport, Mississippi, said he saw the truck “barreling through, throwing people like in a movie scene, throwing people into the air.”

“Bodies, bodies all up and down the street, everybody screaming and hollering,” said Parsons, whose friend Nikyra Dedeaux was among the people killed.

“This is not just an act of terrorism. This is evil,” New Orleans Police Superintendent Anne Kirkpatrick said.

The driver “defeated” safety measures in place to protect pedestrians, Kirkpatrick said, and was “hell-bent on creating the carnage and the damage that he did.”

The FBI identified the driver as Shamsud-Din Jabbar, 42, a U.S. citizen from Texas, and said it was working to determine any potential associations with terrorist organizations.

EDS NOTE: GRAPHIC CONTENT - Security personnel investigate the scene on Bourbon Street after a vehicle drove into a crowd on New Orleans’ Canal and Bourbon Street, Wednesday Jan. 1, 2025. (AP Photo/Gerald Herbert) EDS NOTE: GRAPHIC CONTENT - Security personnel investigate the scene on Bourbon Street after a vehicle drove into a crowd on New Orleans’ Canal and Bourbon Street, Wednesday Jan. 1, 2025. (AP Photo/Gerald Herbert) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

“We do not believe that Jabbar was solely responsible,” FBI Assistant Special Agent in Charge Alethea Duncan said at a news conference.

Investigators found multiple improvised explosives, including two pipe bombs that were concealed within coolers and wired for remote detonation, according to a Louisiana State Police intelligence bulletin obtained by The Associated Press.

A black flag with white lettering lies on the ground rolled up behind a pickup truck that a man drove into a crowd on Bourbon Street in New Orleans, killing and injuring a number of people, early Wednesday morning, Jan. 1, 2025. The FBI said they recovered an Islamic State group flag, which is black with white lettering, from the vehicle. (AP Photo/Gerald Herbert) A black flag with white lettering lies on the ground rolled up behind a pickup truck that a man drove into a crowd on Bourbon Street in New Orleans, killing and injuring a number of people, early Wednesday morning, Jan. 1, 2025. The FBI said they recovered an Islamic State group flag, which is black with white lettering, from the vehicle. (AP Photo/Gerald Herbert) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

A driver behind the wheel of a pickup truck raced into a crowd in New Orleans on New Year’s Day, killing at least 10 people in what the FBI is investigating as an act of terrorism. An Islamic State group flag was recovered in the vehicle used by the attacker.

The bulletin, relying on preliminary information gathered soon after the attack, also cited surveillance footage that it said showed three men and a woman placing one of the devices, but federal officials did not immediately confirm that detail and it wasn’t clear who they were or what connection they had to the attack, if any.

Jabbar drove a rented pickup truck onto a sidewalk, going around a police car that was positioned to block vehicular traffic, authorities said. A barrier system meant to prevent vehicle attacks was being repaired in preparation for the Super Bowl in February.

Jabbar was killed by police after he exited the truck and opened fire on responding officers, Kirkpatrick said. Three officers returned fire. Two were shot and are in stable condition.

A New Orleans police officer searches the area near a crime scene after a vehicle drove into a crowd on Canal and Bourbon Street earlier, Wednesday Jan. 1, 2025. (AP Photo/Jack Brook) A New Orleans police officer searches the area near a crime scene after a vehicle drove into a crowd on Canal and Bourbon Street earlier, Wednesday Jan. 1, 2025. (AP Photo/Jack Brook) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More A coroner's van is parked on the corner of Bourbon St. and Canal St, after a vehicle raced into a crowd of revelers early on New Year's Day, in New Orleans on Wednesday, Jan. 1, 2025. (AP Photo/Jack Brook) A coroner's van is parked on the corner of Bourbon St. and Canal St, after a vehicle raced into a crowd of revelers early on New Year's Day, in New Orleans on Wednesday, Jan. 1, 2025. (AP Photo/Jack Brook) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Investigators recovered a handgun and AR-style rifle, according to a law enforcement official who was not authorized to discuss the investigation publicly and spoke on condition of anonymity.

There were also deadly explosions in Honolulu and outside a Las Vegas hotel owned by President-elect Donald Trump. Biden said the FBI was looking into whether the Las Vegas explosion was connected to the New Orleans attack but had “nothing to report” as of Wednesday evening.

A photo circulated among law enforcement officials showed a bearded Jabbar wearing camouflage next to the truck after he was killed. The intelligence bulletin obtained by the AP said he was wearing a ballistic vest and helmet. The flag of the Islamic State group was on the truck’s trailer hitch, the FBI said.

“For those people who don’t believe in objective evil, all you have to do is look at what happened in our city early this morning,” U.S. Sen. John Kennedy, a Louisiana Republican, said. “If this doesn’t trigger the gag reflex of every American, every fair-minded American, I’ll be very surprised.”

Jabbar joined the Army in 2007, serving on active duty in human resources and information technology and deploying to Afghanistan from 2009 to 2010, the service said. He transferred to the Army Reserve in 2015 and left in 2020 with the rank of staff sergeant.

Hours after the attack, several coroner’s office vans were parked on the corner of Bourbon and Canal streets, cordoned off by police tape with crowds of dazed tourists standing around, some trying to navigate their luggage through the labyrinth of blockades.

Louisiana Gov. Jeff Landry urged people to avoid the area, which remained an active crime scene.

“We looked out our front door and saw caution tape and dead silence and it’s eerie,” said Tessa Cundiff, an Indiana native who moved to the French Quarter a few years ago. “This is not what we fell in love with, it’s sad.”

Nearby, life went on as normal in the city known to some for a motto that translates to “let the good times roll.” At a cafe a block from where the truck came to rest, people crowded in for breakfast as upbeat pop music played. Two blocks away, people drank at a bar, seemingly as if nothing happened.

Biden, speaking from the presidential retreat at Camp David, called the attack a “despicable” and “heinous act.” Addressing the victims and the people of New Orleans, he said: “I want you to know I grieve with you. Our nation grieves with you as you mourn and as you heal.”

“My heart goes out to the victims and their families who were simply trying to celebrate the holiday,” Biden said in an earlier written statement. “There is no justification for violence of any kind, and we will not tolerate any attack on any of our nation’s communities.”

The attack is the latest example of a vehicle being used as a weapon to carry out mass violence and the deadliest IS-inspired assault on U.S. soil in years.

FBI officials have repeatedly warned about an elevated international terrorism threat due to the Israel-Hamas war. In the last year, the agency has disrupted other potential attacks, including in October when it arrested an Afghan man in Oklahoma for an alleged Election Day plot targeting large crowds.

___

Tucker reported from Washington, D.C. and Mustian reported from Black Mountain, North Carolina. Associated Press reporters Stephen Smith, Chevel Johnson and Brett Martel in New Orleans; Jeff Martin in Atlanta; Alanna Durkin Richer, Tara Copp and Zeke Miller in Washington, D.C.; Darlene Superville in New Castle, Delaware; Colleen Long in West Palm Beach, Florida; and Michael R. Sisak in New York contributed to this report.</description><enclosure url="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/bbfb44a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1999+0+1/resize/767x511!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2F1c%2F2d%2F161ea90a4a4ca113ba8e77975cce%2Fap25001550108143.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/></item><item><title>Movies in 2024: Lessons from a turbulent year at the box office</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/movie-box-office-lessons-2024-cbdff5fc420047d187987d2aeed4db9f</link><description>Movie ticket sales took a bit of a hit in 2024. The annual domestic box office is expected to end up at around $8.75 billion, down more than 3% from 2023, according to estimates from Comscore.

It’s not as dire as it was in the pandemic years, but it’s also not even close to the pre-pandemic norm when the annual box office regularly surpassed $11 billion.

This is the year the business felt the effects of the Hollywood strikes of 2023, the labor standoff that delayed productions and releases and led to a depleted calendar for exhibitors and moviegoers. And yet it’s not as bad as it could have been, or at least as bad as analysts projected at the start of the year.

“This has been a really incredible comeback story for the industry,” said Paul Dergarabedian, the senior media analyst for Comscore. “Just a couple of months ago it was a question of whether we would even hit $8 billion for the year.”

Hollywood continues to learn lessons about what moviegoers really want, what works and what doesn’t. Here are the biggest takeaways from 2024.

The strike fallout was real

The Hollywood strikes might have ended in 2023, putting productions back into full swing and sending stars out on the promotional circuit again — but the ripple effect of the work stoppages and contract standoffs showed their real effects on the 2024 release calendar.

The first two quarters were hit hardest, with tentpoles pushed later in the year (“Deadpool &amp; Wolverine,” for one) or even into 2025 (like “Mission: Impossible 8”). With no Marvel movie kicking off the summer moviegoing season, the box office was down a devastating 27.5% from 2023 right before “Inside Out 2” opened in June.

“It’s an unpredictable business but it thrives on stability,” Dergarabedian said. “When the release calendar is thrown off, the momentum stops.”

The PG rating (and animation) ruled

Sequels and franchises dominated the top 10 movies of the year, as has often been the case in the past 15 years. But this year, films carrying a PG rating did especially well, starting with the biggest movie of 2024: “Inside Out 2,” which also became the biggest animated movie of all time, not accounting for inflation.

Family films with a PG rating — including “Despicable Me 4,”“Moana 2,”“Wicked,” “Kung Fu Panda 4,” “Sonic the Hedgehog 3,” “Mufasa” and “The Wild Robot” — grossed over $2.9 billion this year, accounting for around 33% of the annual box office, according to Comscore. Movies rated PG-13, by contrast, made up about 30% of ticket sales.

The Disney impact

After a quieter 2023 and several years without a film at the very top of the charts, the Walt Disney Co. came back roaring in 2024 with three of the top five movies of the year: “Inside Out 2,” “Deadpool &amp; Wolverine” and “Moana 2.” In mid-December, it crossed the $2 billion domestic mark, the second time any studio has done so since 2019 (that was also Disney, in 2022). Its 20th Century division also played an important part with “Alien: Romulus” and “Kingdom of the Planet of the Apes.”

“It’s a different industry when Disney commits to theatrical releases,” said Daniel Loria, an executive at the movie data and analytics trade The Boxoffice Company.

Looking at ‘flops’ a different way

Every year has high-profile flops and disappointments, and this was no exception. Sony had a rough go with its “Spider-Man” adjacent titles like “Madame Web” and “Kraven the Hunter” (but this also seems to be the fate lately for anyone not named “Deadpool”). Universal had higher hopes for “The Fall Guy,” as did Warner Bros. for “Furiosa: A Mad Max Saga” and “Joker: Folie à Deux.”

Then there were the filmmaker-driven (and financed) passion projects that failed to take off like Kevin Costner’s “Horizon: An American Saga — Chapter 1” and Francis Ford Coppola’s “Megalopolis.”

“It’s a reductive way of thinking about those passion projects,” Loria said. “Those movies didn’t come out with huge expectations, meaning theaters didn’t clear out the house and give them three auditoriums per site in hopes for money to come in.”

This was, however, part of the problem with “Joker 2,” which was expected to be more in line with the first which made over $1 billion. But even that has a caveat, Loria thinks.

“It wasn’t just that ‘Joker’ didn’t perform, it’s that there was nothing coming in behind it to make up that momentum,” Loria said. “That’s more the fault of a release schedule where one movie is supposed to carry a month. That model doesn’t work anymore.”

Audiences crave options and a diverse lineup

What does work, Loria said, is a diverse lineup, with the Thanksgiving and Christmas successes being the perfect example. At Thanksgiving, there was “Wicked,” “Gladiator II” and “Moana 2.” Christmas had “Mufasa,” “Sonic 3,” and a lot of adult offerings too, including “Nosferatu,” “A Complete Unknown” and “Babygirl.”

Horror is often the safest bet for theatrical, but this year had even veterans pleasantly surprised by just how enthusiastic that audience can be, with hits like “Longlegs,” “Nosferatu,” “Terrifier 3” and “Smile 2” getting people out of the house.

The Blake Lively drama “It Ends With Us,” which had its share of ongoing off-screen drama as well, also became an event. Audiences turned out for smart thrillers, like “Conclave” as well as unexpected originals including “Anora,” “The Substance” and “The Brutalist.”

Nostalgia and the allure of a re-release

Re-releases of movies in theaters that are also widely available in the home thrived this year. Some of the biggest successes included Christopher Nolan’s “Interstellar,”“Coraline” and “The Phantom Menace.”

“It just shows our industry once again that audiences truly understand the difference between a communal, big screen theatrical experience that they crave even on films that they’ve had the opportunities to see in the home,” Nolan said in December. “That theatrical experience that we all know and love is so powerful and so exciting. It’s a very clear demonstration of it.”

Viral marketing moments

As silly as it sounds, this is the year the novelty popcorn bucket became a star. It started with the accidentally suggestive “Dune: Part 2” creation, which “Deadpool &amp; Wolverine” latched onto in a less accidental way. More recently, the “Nosferatu” coffin buckets have been fetching high resale prices.

For Loria, it’s all part of a trend that theaters have been noticing since reopening during the pandemic: Moviegoers aren’t back in pre-pandemic numbers, but those who did come back were spending more on concessions and premium tickets (like IMAX and other large format screens) than ever before.

2025 looks bright

Everyone is optimistic for the film business in 2025, and the offerings for moviegoers — which include at least 110 films projected to open on over 2,000 screens — according to the National Association of Theatre Owners. And the momentum is there.

“There’s been a huge amount of box office generated in the last six weeks of the year,” Dergarabedian said. “This is the best opening act 2025 could have.”</description></item><item><title>No. 6 Ohio State routs top-ranked Oregon 41-21 in the Rose Bowl, advances to CFP semifinals</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/cfp-rose-bowl-2025-oregon-ohio-state-8030a2a37d45c1a6d7dd15b51ae6c098</link><description>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) — Second chances don’t come around often in life, Ohio State coach Ryan Day told his players in a team meeting before the Rose Bowl.

After a season in which they fell short at too many key moments, the Buckeyes all knew they had one of those second chances when they stepped onto this famous turf for another shot at the top-ranked, unbeaten Oregon Ducks.

Ohio State seized it with a vengeance.

Jeremiah Smith caught two of Will Howard’s three long touchdown passes during a sensational 34-point first half, and the No. 6 Buckeyes roared into the College Football Playoff semifinals with a 41-21 victory in the 111th Rose Bowl on Wednesday night.

“You can see the potential of where we’re at, when we play in all three phases the way we did,” Day said.

Howard passed for 319 yards, Emeka Egbuka also caught a long TD pass and TreVeyon Henderson made a 66-yard touchdown run in a redemptive Rose Bowl for the Buckeyes (12-2, CFP No. 8 seed), who lost a 32-31 heartbreaker to the Ducks in Eugene in October. Ohio State then lost to archrival Michigan in humiliating fashion to conclude a regular season in which its performances didn’t always measure up to its formidable talent.

The inaugural 12-team College Football Playoff created a way for the Buckeyes to erase their mistakes — and from the opening minute in Pasadena, they took out every frustration on the outclassed Ducks.

“I think nobody has gone through more scrutiny than probably the team here,” Egbuka said. “Five weeks ago, you know, people on the scene getting death threats, our head coach getting cussed out, people saying he should never come to Ohio again, all that type of stuff. And I’m sure by the end of (tonight), when you scroll Twitter, Instagram, everyone’s going to be singing our praises. We just know what to say true to in our building.”

Facing the tournament’s No. 1 seed in the Granddaddy of Them All, the Buckeyes scored on six of their first seven drives — with four scoring plays longer than 40 yards — to take a 34-0 lead late in the second quarter on the nation’s only remaining unbeaten team.

Henderson’s second TD run late in the third essentially put it away for Ohio State, which is headed to the Cotton Bowl on Jan. 10 to face No. 4 Texas for a berth in the national title game. The Longhorns barely advanced earlier Wednesday, holding off Arizona State 39-31 in a double-overtime Peach Bowl.

“I’m proud of the resilience of these guys,” Day said. “Still got a lot of football ahead of us.”

Smith, the Buckeyes’ standout freshman playmaker, had a remarkable bowl debut with seven receptions for a season-high 187 yards — including five catches for 161 yards in the first half alone, hauling in scoring passes of 45 and 43 yards. Egbuka compared Smith favorably to Jaxon Smith-Njigba, who had a record 347-yard, three-touchdown Rose Bowl performance three years ago.

“I would say legendary,” Egbuka said. “I was able to witness Jaxon’s game in the Rose Bowl and the pure dominant performance that that was, but even though (Smith’s) stats might not reflect the exact same thing that Jaxon has, I don’t think it was too far off in terms of dominance. He’s a very special talent, and I’m so excited to keep watching him grow.”

Dillon Gabriel passed for 299 yards and hit Traeshon Holden for two touchdowns for the Ducks (13-1, CFP No. 1 seed), whose dreams of their first national title were flattened on the famed Rose Bowl turf. Oregon’s 14-game winning streak also ended.

“We really didn’t have the ability to stop them, and we didn’t have the ability to get something going for us on offense,” Oregon coach Dan Lanning said. “We haven’t faced a lot of moments like this all year. (Ohio State) is an unbelievable team.”

Eleven days after routing Tennessee to open the Playoff, Ohio State dominated the Ducks. Along with the Buckeyes’ offensive fireworks, the Ohio State defense that couldn’t sack Gabriel in the teams’ first meeting dropped the Heisman Trophy finalist eight times in the rematch.

The Big Ten champion Ducks failed to create any of the big plays that carried them to victory last time. Oregon also played without receiver Evan Stewart, who caught seven passes for 149 yards in the first meeting, but was ruled out of the Rose Bowl with a back injury.

“They brought the fight, and we got hit in the mouth,” Oregon receiver Tez Johnson said. “They won the game from the first snap.”

Following the usual pregame pageantry in Arroyo Seco’s 70-degree sunshine, Ohio State needed just three plays and 49 seconds to strike first. Howard threw a short play-action screen pass to Smith, who motored through Oregon’s secondary for a 45-yard score.

On the Buckeyes’ third drive, Howard feathered an exceptional long pass over three Ducks to the sprinting Egbuka for a 42-yard TD. Howard finished the first quarter with a career-best 212 yards passing, surpassing his 160 yards against Tennessee.

Early in the second quarter, Smith got so open near the Ducks’ goal line that he had two seconds to settle under Howard’s long throw like an outfielder with a fly ball, scoring a 42-yard TD untouched.

When Henderson broke a 66-yard TD run down the Oregon sideline for a 31-0 lead, both sides of the Rose Bowl stands rippled with disbelief.

Oregon finally got moving on its final drive before halftime. Gabriel found Holden for a 5-yard TD pass at the gun to salvage something from its horrific half.

Takeaways

Ohio State: It was the Buckeyes’ biggest margin of victory over a No. 1 team in school history. No doubt about it, they look like the best team still playing.

Oregon: Having 3 1/2 weeks off with their first-round bye proved to be dangerous. This disconcerting flop doesn’t completely ruin a breakthrough Big Ten debut, but the season will always loom as a missed opportunity in Oregon history — and a good argument for changing the CFP rules to introduce reseeding between rounds.

Up next

Ohio State: The Cotton Bowl will be a preview of both teams’ 2025 season opener, with Texas visiting Ohio Stadium on Aug. 30.

Oregon: The 2025 season opener is at home against Montana State, which faces North Dakota State in the FCS title game Monday night.

___

Get poll alerts and updates on the AP Top 25 throughout the season. Sign up here. AP college football: https://apnews.com/hub/ap-top-25-college-football-poll and https://apnews.com/hub/college-football</description></item><item><title>Carter reflected on 1980 Olympic boycott: ‘A bad decision’</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/jimmy-carter-olympics-boycott-9ba0aad38e01013bd0f40ce554317caf</link><description>COLORADO SPRINGS, Colo. (AP) — It was a decision that robbed hundreds of athletes of their once-in-a-lifetime chance at Olympic glory, and for more than four decades, it weighed heavily on the man who made it — Jimmy Carter.

Carter’s passing Sunday has unearthed memories from his 1977-1981 presidency. Somewhere between his greatest foreign-policy success (the Camp David Accords between Israel and Egypt) and his greatest failure (the Iran hostage crisis) sits the U.S. boycott of the 1980 Olympics in Moscow.

It was Carter who called for that boycott — a Cold War power play intended to express America’s disdain for the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan. In his 1980 State of the Union Address, Carter said the invasion “could pose the most serious threat to world peace since the second World War.”

A wide-angle lens captures the assembled members of Congress in the House Chamber for Carter’s State of The Union address in Washington on Jan. 23, 1980. (AP Photo, File) A wide-angle lens captures the assembled members of Congress in the House Chamber for Carter’s State of The Union address in Washington on Jan. 23, 1980. (AP Photo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

From left, Belgian representative to the International Olympic Committee (IOC), Prince Alexandre de Merode, President of the Belgian Olympic Committee Raoul Mollet, General Secretary of the U.S. Olympic Committee Col. F. Don Miller, and President of the West German Olympic Committee Willi Daume, are seen during a meeting of officials from 18 Western European Olympic committees to discuss a possible boycott of the MOscow Olympic games on March 22, 1980, in Brussels. (AP Photo/Pierre Thielemans, File) From left, Belgian representative to the International Olympic Committee (IOC), Prince Alexandre de Merode, President of the Belgian Olympic Committee Raoul Mollet, General Secretary of the U.S. Olympic Committee Col. F. Don Miller, and President of the West German Olympic Committee Willi Daume, are seen during a meeting of officials from 18 Western European Olympic committees to discuss a possible boycott of the MOscow Olympic games on March 22, 1980, in Brussels. (AP Photo/Pierre Thielemans, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More F. Don Miller, executive director of the U.S. Olympic Committee, reads a resolution adopted by the U.S. Olympic Committee's House of Delegates to boycott the 1980 Summer Games in Moscow, in Colorado Springs, Colo., April 12, 1980. At left is Robert Kane, president of the U.S. Olympic Committee. (AP Photo/Ed Andrieski, File) F. Don Miller, executive director of the U.S. Olympic Committee, reads a resolution adopted by the U.S. Olympic Committee's House of Delegates to boycott the 1980 Summer Games in Moscow, in Colorado Springs, Colo., April 12, 1980. At left is Robert Kane, president of the U.S. Olympic Committee. (AP Photo/Ed Andrieski, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

The boycott garnered more than two-thirds support from the 2,400 members of the unwieldy U.S. Olympic Committee house of delegates, the governing body that made the official move to keep the athletes out of Moscow. In short time, that move came to be seen as the textbook example of the risks, confusion and low success rate of injecting politics into sports.

“We were not allowed to go for a not-so-clear reason,” said Edwin Moses, the hurdling great who won 122 straight races between 1977 and 1987, which included the Olympic gold-medal contests in 1976 and 1984.

For decades, members of the 1980 U.S. Olympic team — recognized as Olympians at home but not by the International Olympic Committee abroad — told stories about opportunities missed and dreams unfulfilled because of the trip to Moscow they never took. Of the 474 athletes who had qualified for the team in 1980, 227 would not get another chance to compete in the Olympic Games.

Many athletes told stories of meeting Carter at a White House visit in the summer of 1980 that served as a tepid substitute. In Washington, the athletes received the highest honor civilians can receive from Congress: the Congressional gold medal. But those medals were only gold-plated bronze, not pure gold, and they weren’t recorded in the Congressional record until a push was made nearly three decades later.

Swimmer Jesse Vassallo, a reigning world champion in multiple events at the time, told Swimming World Magazine about meeting Carter in the reception line.

Carter “reached out to shake my hand and he said ‘How would you have done in Moscow?’” Vassallo recalled. “And I said, ‘I would have won two golds and a silver.’ And he just gave me this (pained) look. He didn’t ask anybody else that question.” Wrestler Jeff Blatnick, a champion on the 1984 Olympic team, met Carter on an airplane years later. According to an essay written by the late USOC spokesman Mike Moran, Blatnick said: “He looks at me and says, ‘Were you on the 1980 hockey team?’ I say, ‘No sir, I’m a wrestler, on the summer team.’ He says, ‘Oh, that was a bad decision, I’m sorry.’”

Anita DeFrantz, spokeswoman for the U.S. Olympic Committee’s Athletes Advisory Council, flanked by Larry Hough, left, and Fred Newhouse right, answers questions from reporters outside the White House in Washington on April 4, 1980, after White House officials rejected a proposal that would have allowed American athletes to compete at the summer Olympic Games in Moscow. (AP Photo, File) Anita DeFrantz, spokeswoman for the U.S. Olympic Committee’s Athletes Advisory Council, flanked by Larry Hough, left, and Fred Newhouse right, answers questions from reporters outside the White House in Washington on April 4, 1980, after White House officials rejected a proposal that would have allowed American athletes to compete at the summer Olympic Games in Moscow. (AP Photo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Flag and sign bearers march around Moscow's Lenin Stadium during closing ceremonies of the XXII Summer Olympic Games in Moscow, on Aug. 3, 1980. (AP Photo/File) Flag and sign bearers march around Moscow's Lenin Stadium during closing ceremonies of the XXII Summer Olympic Games in Moscow, on Aug. 3, 1980. (AP Photo/File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More Passersby examine the new Olympic billboard reading, "Sport Serves Peace," erected after the United States announced it was boycotting the games in Moscow on April 23, 1980. (AP Photo/Yurchenko, File) Passersby examine the new Olympic billboard reading, "Sport Serves Peace," erected after the United States announced it was boycotting the games in Moscow on April 23, 1980. (AP Photo/Yurchenko, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

In his 2021 biography on the 39th President, Kai Bird writes that the boycott was a byproduct of a hard line Carter decided to take against the Soviets at the urging of his national security advisor, Zbigniew Brzezinski, who had been in a long-running struggle with the less-hawkish Secretary of State, Cyrus Vance, to influence Carter’s thinking. “History would prove Vance correct; Brzezinski’s ‘Carter Doctrine’ never amounted to much more than a cover for wasteful arms exports,” Bird wrote.

And Carter’s boycott did nothing to deter the Soviets. They stayed in Afghanistan for another nine years, while further disrupting the Olympic movement and America’s own turn as an Olympic host four years later. The Soviets and 13 other countries, mostly from the Eastern Bloc, boycotted the Los Angeles Olympics in 1984 in retaliation for what the Americans had done to Moscow four years earlier.

Forty-four years after Carter’s fateful decision, the Olympics remain every bit as politicized and polarized as they were back then. And for the past several years, the world has grappled with Russia’s place in international sports in the wake of another invasion — this time, into neighboring Ukraine.

How that war is resolved will help define Russia’s role when the Olympics come back to Los Angeles in 2028.</description><enclosure url="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/db5fe8b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1999+0+30/resize/767x511!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2Ffc%2Ff8%2F21188a01348ae8be335357e51d70%2F89c9c03d0fec43019d0acdaa2dee4023" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/></item><item><title>Giuliani fights to save his Yankees World Series rings from $148 million defamation verdict</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/giuliani-yankees-world-series-rings-defamation-election-trump-3515aed30e385a3612c06383c5b9119c</link><description>NEW YORK (AP) — Ruth. Gehrig. DiMaggio. Mantle. Giuliani?

As Rudy Giuliani’s life gets stripped for parts to satisfy a $148 million defamation verdict, the former New York City mayor is fighting to keep one gleaming set of sports memorabilia in the family: Yankees World Series rings bestowed to him by the team’s late owner, George Steinbrenner.

A lifelong Bronx Bombers fan, Giuliani contends that the rings — bejeweled behemoths commemorating the team’s four championships in five years while he was mayor — now belong to his son, Andrew, and shouldn’t be given up.

In sworn testimony made public this week, ahead of a pair of key court dates, Giuliani described the 1996, 1998, 1999 and 2000 World Series rings as something of a family heirloom and Yankees good-luck charm.

He recounted how he and Andrew would each put one on for “a special Yankee occasion,” like the team’s last World Series win in 2009.

Giuliani testified that when Steinbrenner gave him the rings in 2002, he insisted on paying for them and told the owner, “These are for Andrew.” He said he then invited his son — a teenager at the time — to take one for himself while he held the others for safekeeping.

Realizing he wasn’t wearing them as much as the Yankees’ fortunes ebbed, Giuliani testified, he decided to give the rest to Andrew at a birthday party in 2018. He estimated that the rings, the same as the players received, were worth about $27,000.

“They are now yours,” Giuliani recalled saying. “These are your rings. I don’t know what I’m keeping them for. They belong to you.”

The ex-mayor took his swings at a Dec. 27 deposition, a week before the start of a courtroom doubleheader in a tug-of-war over assets sought by the two former Georgia election workers who sued him over his lies about them in the wake of President-elect Donald Trump’s 2020 election loss. A transcript was posted to the court docket on Monday.

Up first is Giuliani’s contempt hearing in Manhattan federal court Friday over what lawyers for the Georgia women say was his failure to turn over property in a timely fashion, such as his New York City apartment lease.

Then, on Jan. 16, Judge Lewis J. Liman will hold a trial to decide what happens not only to Giuliani’s World Series rings but also his condominium in Palm Beach, Florida. Giuliani claims the condo, estimated to be worth more than $3 million, is his primary residence and should be exempt.

For Giuliani, once heralded as “America’s Mayor” for his post-9/11 leadership, it’s the legal equivalent of two strikes, two out in the bottom of the ninth.

Lawyers for the former election workers, mother and daughter Ruby Freeman and Wandrea “Shaye” Moss, argue that Giuliani has engaged in a “consistent pattern of willful defiance” of court orders to turn over items.

In a Monday filing, lawyer Aaron Nathan said Giuliani’s compliance has been spotty, noting that while he finally surrendered a Mercedes previous owned by actor Lauren Bacall, he failed to provide the vehicle’s title.

After listing 26 watches in a bankruptcy filing, Giuliani now claims without explanation that 18 watches he turned over to Freeman and Moss are all he has, Nathan wrote. He added that Giuliani also claims not to know the whereabouts of a shirt signed by Joe DiMaggio or a photo signed by Reggie Jackson, both Yankees legends.

Freeman and Moss asked the judge in August to award them the World Series rings, but the judge demurred and scheduled a trial after Andrew Giuliani, now 38, said they belong to him.

Giuliani’s eight hours of deposition testimony offered a vivid portrait of a still-proud, combative and downtrodden man who has lost almost everything and remains convinced that it has been unjustly taken.

Recalling his days as a two-term Republican mayor, he boasted that he “cured” homelessness in the city while acknowledging that he is now rejected by most clubs he would like to join, except for two.

Questioned by Nathan, he spoke at length about the rings, his ties to Trump and the Yankees, and his dismay over his once-beloved Big Apple’s liberal politics — a factor he said drove him to relocate to Florida and register to vote there last May.

“Frankly, I wanted my vote to count,” Giuliani testified.

Asked why it was important to him to cast a vote for president, Giuliani replied: “Because I am a very, very strong supporter of Donald Trump, which is the reason why you are doing all of this to me.”

Before Trump, it was the Yankees. Giuliani, who saw them win 10 titles during his childhood and college years, regularly cheered the team as mayor, often sitting next to the dugout.

“I was a very ardent Yankee fan,” he testified. “When I was the mayor, I was described as New York’s No. 1 Yankee fan.”

After the team triumphed in 1996 to snap a 15-year drought, Steinbrenner thought “New York’s No. 1 Yankee fan” deserved a World Series ring — but Giuliani wasn’t having it.

“I didn’t think it was appropriate that a mayor get a ring,” Giuliani testified.

By the time he left office in 2002, the Yankees had three more championships.

At spring training that year in Tampa, Florida, Steinbrenner presented him with a plaque and three World Series rings, Giuliani testified, each engraved with his name.

“I was very touched and moved by that,” he said.

The Yankees also gave him the 1996 ring that he turned down, he said. He recalled showing all four rings to his son and telling him: “These are going to be yours.”

Each ring was bigger and more extravagant than the last, Giuliani testified, so much so that “you’d look crazy wearing it.”

Giuliani lamented that his rings didn’t bring the Yankees more success, noting their 2003 World Series loss to the Marlins and 2004 playoff collapse against the hated Red Sox.

“I stopped wearing them after the Yankees stopped winning because it was no longer working,” he said. “And then I wasn’t using them anymore.”</description></item><item><title>Meet the Danish-Swedish farmdog, the newest breed in the American Kennel Club’s lineup</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/danishswedish-farmdog-breed-american-kennel-club-8e238bb973e47cafd3de303a45a3c2aa</link><description>NEW YORK (AP) — Say hello to the latest dog in the American Kennel Club’s lineup of recognized breeds. Or you might say “hej.”

The Danish-Swedish farmdog — yep, that’s the official name — joined the pack Thursday. The designation makes the breed eligible to compete for many best in show trophies, and it likely augurs more widespread interest in the small, sprightly dogs. The prospect both gladdens and concerns their biggest fans.

“We’re excited about it. We’re looking forward to it,” said Carey Segebart, one of the people who worked to get Danish-Swedish farmdogs recognized by the AKC. She proudly plans to debut one of her own at a dog show this month near her Iowa home.

Still, she thinks increased exposure is “a double-edged sword” for the fleet, versatile pups.

“We don’t want the breed to just explode too quickly,” she said.

Called the farmdog or DSF for short, the breed goes back centuries in parts of what are now Denmark, southern Sweden and some other European countries, according to the Danish-Swedish Farmdog Club of America.

“They’re interesting, fun little dogs,” said Segebart, who has owned them since 2011 and is the club’s incoming president. “They’re essentially up for anything. They succeed at most everything.”

In their original homelands, the dogs’ main job was rodent patrol, but they also would herd a bit, act as watchdogs and play with farmers’ children. Some even performed in circuses, according to the club.

After Denmark and Sweden became more urban and suburban in the 20th century, farmdog fanciers set out to secure the breed’s place in both nations (where “hej” translates to the English “hello”). Kennel clubs there began registering farmdogs in 1987.

In the U.S., many of the just about 350 farmdogs nationwide compete in agility, obedience or other canine sports that are open to all dogs, including mixed breeds.

But until now, farmdogs couldn’t enter the traditional breed-by-breed judging that leads to best in show prizes at events including the prominent Westminster Kennel Club dog show in New York. The entry deadline has passed for February’s Westminster show, so farmdogs will have to wait for 2026 there, but they may well appear later this year at two other major, televised shows, the National Dog Show and AKC National Championship.

The Danish-Swedish farmdog is the AKC’s 202nd breed and “a wonderful addition to a family that is able to provide it with the exercise and mental stimulation that it needs,” said the club’s Gina DiNardo.

The AKC is the United States’ oldest purebred dog registry and essentially a league for many dog competitions. Registration is voluntary, and requirements for breed recognition include at least 300 pedigreed dogs spread through at least 20 states. Some breeds are in other kennel clubs or none at all.

Danish-Swedish farmdog fanciers deliberated for several years before pursuing AKC recognition and the attention that’s likely to come with it, Segebart said. The number of farmdog puppy-seekers has grown substantially over the last decade; each of the few breeders receives multiple inquiries a week, and the typical wait for a puppy is a year or more, she said.

Farmdog folk fear that their appealing, relatively easy-care breed could quickly become too popular for its own good. They’re not the first to worry: Much fur has flown in dogdom over the rise of the French bulldog, which the AKC now ranks as the most popular breed in the country.

Some animal rights activists echo those concerns to argue against dog breeding in general. They say purebred popularity trends divert people from adopting shelter animals, fuel puppy mills and prize dogs’ appearance over their health.

The AKC says it promotes responsibly “breeding for type and function” to produce dogs with at least somewhat predictable traits, whether as basic as size or as specialized as bomb-sniffing skills. The club says it has given over $35 million since 1995 to its canine health research charity.</description></item><item><title>Puerto Rico swears in new governor days after major blackout hit island</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/puerto-rico-jenniffer-gonzalez-new-governor-sworn-84afbbfa537b23f35494df0127b20c2d</link><description>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) — Jenniffer González Colón was sworn in Thursday as Puerto Rico’s new governor during a normally ebullient ceremony held amid widespread anger over a blackout that hit the U.S. territory days ago.

González, a Republican who backs President-elect Donald Trump and whose pro-statehood New Progressive Party secured a historic third consecutive term after she won the Nov. 5 election, has pledged to stabilize the Caribbean island’s crumbling power grid.

“There are many challenges facing our island,” she said in her first public address as governor as she acknowledged the blackout in a speech to a crowd gathered in front of the seaside Capitol. “That is precisely what moves me to address that first challenge with a sense of urgency.”

She pledged to improve Puerto Rico’s infrastructure, hospitals and schools, adding that she intends to boost bilingual education.

“I’m going to fulfill my promises to you,” she said. “I am not going to govern only for those who voted for me. I am going to be the governor of all Puerto Ricans.”

Before the start of a ceremony to celebrate her swearing in, González attended Mass surrounded by family and supporters.

“What better than to come first to thank God and to ask God to give me the wisdom, the fortitude and the tools to fulfill everything I promised the people of Puerto Rico,” she told reporters.

A protester with her face covered interrupted the Mass at Parroquia Santa Teresita in San Juan. She yelled, “Jenniffer, we came for you! Puerto is without power.”

Meanwhile, a small group of protesters gathered at the Capitol before González’s arrival. They were especially rankled that a well-known, outspoken activist elected to Puerto Rico’s Senate for the first time was not allowed inside the Capitol, with the elections commission noting he had not yet been officially certified.

Protesting the ceremony was Yara Humarán Martínez, an aquatic physical therapist whose 83-year-old mother remains without power.

“I don’t have any hope that she will change anything,” she said of the new governor.

González has promised to appoint an energy “czar” to review potential contractual breaches while another operator is found to possibly replace Luma Energy, a private company that oversees the transmission and distribution of power in Puerto Rico.

However, no contract can be canceled without prior approval from Puerto Rico’s Energy Bureau and a federal control board that oversees the island’s finances.

Outages were still being reported on Thursday as crews tried to stabilize the grid following the blackout that hit early Tuesday, leaving 1.3 million customers in the dark as Puerto Ricans prepared for New Year’s Eve.

While electricity had been restored to 99% of the utility’s 1.47 million total customers, more than 600,000 were temporarily left without power on New Year’s Day when part of the system collapsed again, according to Luma.

“The stability of the system is fragile,” Luma said late Wednesday as it warned of more outages on Thursday given an ongoing lack of generation. “We know and understand how frustrating it is for our clients to be without service for long periods of time.”

Backup generators were put in place to ensure a smooth swearing-in ceremony on Thursday given that renowned musicians were scheduled to perform.

The anticipated revelry was characteristic of González, a 48-year-old attorney and recent mother of twins who prior to the election showed up at her party’s assembly wearing a Wonder Woman tiara and cuffs. She also made the news after peeling out of one of her party’s conventions in an off-road vehicle earlier this year.

Supporters and critics gathered for the ceremony, some clutching umbrellas to shield themselves from the blistering sun.

“Because she’s a woman, she’s going to be a great governor,” said Amanda Sánchez León, a retired government employee, who arrived two hours early to secure a spot outside an area reserved for guests. She said she was hopeful that González would reduce violent crimes and improve education and health, “especially for us older people.” She also believed the power crisis would improve and that González would see her promises through.

“The people are suffering,” Sánchez said.

Also supporting the new governor was Lizbeth Rodríguez, a school nurse, who believed that as a mother, González would prioritize the island’s weak education system and tackle crime.

But Rodríguez remains rankled at what she believes is the misspending of government money.

“That’s what bothers the people. You’re doing fine, sure, but look at us,” she said.

González, of the pro-statehood New Progressive Party, had beat former Gov. Pedro Pierluisi during their party’s primary in June.

At the time, she was Puerto Rico’s representative in Congress and had run on Pierluisi’s ticket four years ago.

After beating him, she won the Nov. 5 general election with more than 526,000 votes, or 41%. Trailing her was Juan Dalmau, who represented Puerto Rico’s Independence Party and the Citizen Victory Movement.

It was the first time that the Popular Democratic Party, which supports the island’s territorial status quo and is one of Puerto Rico’s two main parties, came in third in a gubernatorial race.

While González’s immediate challenge is Puerto Rico’s fragile power grid, she also inherits a feeble economy that has slowly been strengthening since the U.S. territory’s government declared in 2015 that it was unable to pay its more than $70 billion public debt load.

In 2017, it filed for the biggest U.S. municipal bankruptcy in history.

All but one government agency has since restructured its debt, with Puerto Rico’s Electric Power Authority still struggling to do so. It holds more than $9 billion in debt, the largest of any government agency.

Experts warn the island will keep struggling to attract investors until the debt is restructured and the power grid strengthened.

González also will have to work alongside a federal control board that U.S. Congress created in 2016 to oversee Puerto Rico’s finances and supervise the ongoing reconstruction after Hurricane María slammed into the island in September 2017 as a powerful Category 4 storm, razing the electrical grid.

She also faces pressure to create affordable housing, lower power bills and the general cost of living, reduce violent crime, boost Puerto Rico’s economy, with the island locked out of capital markets since 2015, and improve a limping health care system as thousands of doctors flock to the U.S. mainland.

Like other governors of the pro-statehood party, González has said she would push for Puerto Rico to become the 51st state, but such a change would require approval from U.S. Congress and the U.S. president.

A nonbinding referendum held during the Nov. 5 election, the seventh of its kind, asked voters to choose one of three options: statehood, independence and independence with free association, under which issues like foreign affairs, U.S. citizenship and use of the U.S. dollar would be negotiated.

With 63% of voters participating, statehood earned more than 615,000 votes, or 59%, with independence coming in second for the first time with more than 309,000 votes, or 29%. Independence with free association garnered more than 128,000 votes, or 12%.

While Puerto Ricans are U.S. citizens, they are not allowed to vote in presidential elections, and officials with the New Progressive Party have noted the island receives unequal treatment when it comes to Medicaid, Medicare and other federal programs.

“Statehood means equality, and I want us to have that access to opportunities,” González said. “I want to have those opportunities here so that our people can move forward.”</description></item><item><title>5 things we know and still don’t know about COVID, 5 years after it appeared</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/covid-vaccine-variant-omicron-deaths-wuhan-lab-1ae8a7b3e6e034e03722f17e7aad34cb</link><description>Five years ago, a cluster of people in Wuhan, China, fell sick with a virus never before seen in the world.

The germ didn’t have a name, nor did the illness it would cause. It wound up setting off a pandemic that exposed deep inequities in the global health system and reshaped public opinion about how to control deadly emerging viruses.

The virus is still with us, though humanity has built up immunity through vaccinations and infections. It’s less deadly than it was in the pandemic’s early days and it no longer tops the list of leading causes of death. But the virus is evolving, meaning scientists must track it closely.

Where did the SARS-CoV-2 virus come from?

Denmark’s Jonas Vingegaard, left, and teammate Matteo Jorgenson, of the U.S., wear face masks to protect themselves from the Corona virus prior to the start of the fourteenth stage of the Tour de France cycling race over 151.9 kilometers (94.4 miles) with start in Pau and finish in Saint-Lary-Soulan Pla d’Adet, France, July 13, 2024. Several riders had to abandon the race after contracting COVID-19. (AP Photo/Daniel Cole, File) Denmark’s Jonas Vingegaard, left, and teammate Matteo Jorgenson, of the U.S., wear face masks to protect themselves from the Corona virus prior to the start of the fourteenth stage of the Tour de France cycling race over 151.9 kilometers (94.4 miles) with start in Pau and finish in Saint-Lary-Soulan Pla d’Adet, France, July 13, 2024. Several riders had to abandon the race after contracting COVID-19. (AP Photo/Daniel Cole, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Dr. Sydney Sewall fills a syringe with the COVID-19 vaccine at the Augusta Armory, Dec. 21, 2021, in Augusta, Maine. (AP Photo/Robert F. Bukaty, File) Dr. Sydney Sewall fills a syringe with the COVID-19 vaccine at the Augusta Armory, Dec. 21, 2021, in Augusta, Maine. (AP Photo/Robert F. Bukaty, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Cemetery workers in protective gear bury a person alongside rows of freshly dug graves at the Vila Formosa cemetery in Sao Paulo, Brazil, April 1, 2020. (AP Photo/Andre Penner, File) Cemetery workers in protective gear bury a person alongside rows of freshly dug graves at the Vila Formosa cemetery in Sao Paulo, Brazil, April 1, 2020. (AP Photo/Andre Penner, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

Nancy Rose, who contracted COVID-19 in 2021 and exhibits long-haul symptoms including brain fog and memory difficulties, pauses while organizing her desk space, Jan. 25, 2022, in Port Jefferson, N.Y. (AP Photo/John Minchillo, File) Nancy Rose, who contracted COVID-19 in 2021 and exhibits long-haul symptoms including brain fog and memory difficulties, pauses while organizing her desk space, Jan. 25, 2022, in Port Jefferson, N.Y. (AP Photo/John Minchillo, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

This undated electron microscope image made available by the U.S. National Institutes of Health in February 2020 shows the Novel Coronavirus SARS-CoV-2, yellow, emerging from the surface of cells, pink, cultured in the lab. Also known as 2019-nCoV, the virus causes COVID-19. The sample was isolated from a patient in the U.S. (NIAID-RML via AP, File) This undated electron microscope image made available by the U.S. National Institutes of Health in February 2020 shows the Novel Coronavirus SARS-CoV-2, yellow, emerging from the surface of cells, pink, cultured in the lab. Also known as 2019-nCoV, the virus causes COVID-19. The sample was isolated from a patient in the U.S. (NIAID-RML via AP, File) Share Share Copy Link copied

Email

Facebook

X

Reddit

LinkedIn

Pinterest

Flipboard

Print Read More

We don’t know. Scientists think the most likely scenario is that it circulated in bats, like many coronaviruses. They think it then infected another species, probably racoon dogs, civet cats or bamboo rats, which in turn infected humans handling or butchering those animals at a market in Wuhan, where the first human cases appeared in late November 2019.

That’s a known pathway for disease transmission and likely triggered the first epidemic of a similar virus, known as SARS. But this theory has not been proven for the virus that causes COVID-19. Wuhan is home to several research labs involved in collecting and studying coronaviruses, fueling debate over whether the virus instead may have leaked from one.

It’s a difficult scientific puzzle to crack in the best of circumstances. The effort has been made even more challenging by political sniping around the virus’ origins and by what international researchers say are moves by China to withhold evidence that could help.

The true origin of the pandemic may not be known for many years — if ever.

How many people died from COVID-19?

Probably more than 20 million. The World Health Organization has said member countries reported more than 7 million deaths from COVID-19 but the true death toll is estimated to be at least three times higher.

In the U.S., an average of about 900 people a week have died of COVID-19 over the past year, according to the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.

The coronavirus continues to affect older adults the most. Last winter in the U.S., people age 75 and older accounted for about half the nation’s COVID-19 hospitalizations and in-hospital deaths, according to the CDC.

“We cannot talk about COVID in the past, since it’s still with us,” WHO director Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus said.

What vaccines were made available?

Scientists and vaccine-makers broke speed records developing COVID-19 vaccines that have saved tens of millions of lives worldwide – and were the critical step to getting life back to normal.

Less than a year after China identified the virus, health authorities in the U.S. and Britain cleared vaccines made by Pfizer and Moderna. Years of earlier research — including Nobel-winning discoveries that were key to making the new technology work — gave a head start for so-called mRNA vaccines.

Today, there’s also a more traditional vaccine made by Novavax, and some countries have tried additional options. Rollout to poorer countries was slow but the WHO estimates more than 13 billion doses of COVID-19 vaccines have been administered globally since 2021.

The vaccines aren’t perfect. They do a good job of preventing severe disease, hospitalization and death, and have proven very safe, with only rare serious side effects. But protection against milder infection begins to wane after a few months.

Like flu vaccines, COVID-19 shots must be updated regularly to match the ever-evolving virus — contributing to public frustration at the need for repeated vaccinations. Efforts to develop next-generation vaccines are underway, such as nasal vaccines that researchers hope might do a better job of blocking infection.

Which variant is dominating now?

Genetic changes called mutations happen as viruses make copies of themselves. And this virus has proven to be no different.

Scientists named these variants after Greek letters: alpha, beta, gamma, delta and omicron. Delta, which became dominant in the U.S. in June 2021, raised a lot of concerns because it was twice as likely to lead to hospitalization as the first version of the virus.

Then in late November 2021, a new variant came on the scene: omicron.

“It spread very rapidly,” dominating within weeks, said Dr. Wesley Long, a pathologist at Houston Methodist in Texas. “It drove a huge spike in cases compared to anything we had seen previously.”

But on average, the WHO said, it caused less severe disease than delta. Scientists believe that may be partly because immunity had been building due to vaccination and infections.

“Ever since then, we just sort of keep seeing these different subvariants of omicron accumulating more different mutations,” Long said. “Right now, everything seems to locked on this omicron branch of the tree.”

The omicron relative now dominant in the U.S. is called XEC, which accounted for 45% of variants circulating nationally in the two-week period ending Dec. 21, the CDC said. Existing COVID-19 medications and the latest vaccine booster should be effective against it, Long said, since “it’s really sort of a remixing of variants already circulating.”

What do we know about long COVID?

Millions of people remain in limbo with a sometimes disabling, often invisible, legacy of the pandemic called long COVID.

It can take several weeks to bounce back after a bout of COVID-19, but some people develop more persistent problems. The symptoms that last at least three months, sometimes for years, include fatigue, cognitive trouble known as “brain fog,” pain and cardiovascular problems, among others.

Doctors don’t know why only some people get long COVID. It can happen even after a mild case and at any age, although rates have declined since the pandemic’s early years. Studies show vaccination can lower the risk.

It also isn’t clear what causes long COVID, which complicates the search for treatments. One important clue: Increasingly researchers are discovering that remnants of the coronavirus can persist in some patients’ bodies long after their initial infection, although that can’t explain all cases.

___

The Associated Press Health and Science Department receives support from the Howard Hughes Medical Institute’s Science and Educational Media Group. The AP is solely responsible for all content.</description></item><item><title>Impeached South Korean president issues defiant message as he faces possible detention</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/south-korean-yoon-martial-law-impeachment-detention-1779809dc6b2c7e5a9478bac17ca7585</link><description>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) — Impeached South Korean President Yoon Suk Yeol, in a message to conservative supporters rallying outside his Seoul residence, vowed to “fight to the end” against “anti-state forces,” while his legal team warned Thursday that police officers attempting to detain him could face arrest by his presidential security service or even civilians.

Yoon’s latest statement of defiance came as the Corruption Investigation Office for High-Ranking Officials prepared to execute a detainment warrant against him that was issued by a Seoul court on Tuesday and is valid for one week. The warrant was issued after Yoon evaded multiple requests to appear for questioning and blocked searches of his office, hindering an investigation into whether his hourslong martial law imposition on Dec. 3 amounted to rebellion.

Oh Dong-woon, the anti-corruption agency’s chief prosecutor, has indicated that police forces might be deployed if Yoon’s security service resists the detention attempt, which could occur as early as Thursday. But it remains unclear whether Yoon can be compelled to submit to questioning.

Yoon’s legal team issued a statement on Thursday warning that any attempt by the anti-corruption agency to use police units for his detention would exceed their legal authority. The lawyers said police officers could face arrest by either the “presidential security service or any citizens” if they try to detain Yoon. They didn’t elaborate further on the claim.

South Korean law permits anyone to make an arrest to stop an active crime, and critics accused Yoon of inciting his supporters to obstruct attempts to detain him.

In a message to supporters gathered outside his residence Wednesday evening, Yoon said he would continue to fight against anti-state forces “violating our sovereignty” and putting the nation in “danger.” He applauded his supporters for their efforts to protect “liberal democracy and constitutional order” and said he was watching their protests on live YouTube broadcasts, according to a photo of the message shared by Yoon’s lawyers.

Yoon Kap-keun, the president’s lawyer, filed a challenge with the Seoul Western District Court on Thursday to block both the detention warrant for Yoon Suk Yeol and a related search warrant for his residence. The lawyer argued that both warrants violate criminal laws and the constitution.

The liberal opposition Democratic Party, which drove the legislative vote that impeached Yoon Suk Yeol on Dec. 14 over his imposition of martial law, accused the president of trying to mobilize his supporters to block his detention and called for law enforcement authorities to execute the warrant immediately.

Braving subfreezing temperatures, thousands of Yoon’s supporters rallied for hours near his residence on Thursday amid a heavy police presence, waving South Korean and American flags while chanting, “Nullify the impeachment!” and “We will protect President Yoon Suk Yeol!” Officers removed some protesters who laid down on a road leading to the entrance of Yoon’s residence, but there were no immediate reports of major clashes.

“The Corruption Investigation Office must detain him immediately, and the presidential security service must cooperate with the lawful execution of the detainment warrant,” said Park Chan-dae, the Democrats’ floor leader.

“They should be aware that obstructing the execution of the detainment warrant could result in punishment for interference with official duties and complicity in rebellion,” he said.

Yoon’s lawyers have argued that the court’s detainment warrant is invalid, claiming that the anti-corruption agency lacks the legal authority to investigate rebellion charges. They also accuse the court of bypassing a law that says locations potentially linked to military secrets cannot be seized or searched without the consent of the person in charge.

Some experts believe the anti-corruption agency, which is leading a joint investigation with police and military authorities, would not risk clashing with Yoon’s security service, which has said it will provide security to Yoon in accordance with the law. The office may instead issue another summons for Yoon to appear for questioning if they are not able to execute the detainment warrant by Jan. 6.

If Yoon is detained, the anti-corruption agency will have 48 hours to investigate him and either request a warrant for his formal arrest or release him. Yoon’s defense minister, police chief and several top military commanders have already been arrested over their roles in the martial law enactment.

Yoon’s presidential powers were suspended following a National Assembly vote to impeach him on Dec. 14 over his imposition of martial law, which lasted only hours but has triggered weeks of political turmoil, halted high-level diplomacy and rattled financial markets. Yoon’s fate now lies with the Constitutional Court, which has begun deliberations on whether to uphold the impeachment and formally remove Yoon from office or reinstate him.

To formally end Yoon’s presidency, at least six justices on the nine-member Constitutional Court must vote in favor.

The National Assembly voted last week to also impeach Prime Minister Han Duck-soo, who became acting president after Yoon’s powers were suspended, over his reluctance to fill three Constitutional Court vacancies ahead of the court’s review of Yoon’s case.

Facing growing pressure, the new acting president, Deputy Prime Minister Choi Sang-mok, appointed two new justices on Tuesday, which possibly increased the chances of the court upholding Yoon’s impeachment.

Cho Han-chang, one of the newly appointed justices, said Thursday that he began his job with a “heavy heart.” Jeong Gye-seon, the other new justice, expressed hope that the remaining vacancy would be filled.

Yoon’s imposition of martial law ended after only six hours when the National Assembly voted 190-0 to lift it despite attempts by heavily armed soldiers to prevent them from voting.

Yoon has defended his martial law decree as a necessary act of governance, portraying it as a temporary warning against the Democratic Party, which he has described as an “anti-state” force obstructing his agenda with its legislative majority.</description></item><item><title>‘Dinosaur highway’ tracks dating back 166 million years are discovered in England</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/uk-dinosaur-tracks-discovery-9fd0499419db0950099e6413a1936488</link><description>LONDON (AP) — A worker digging up clay in a southern England limestone quarry noticed unusual bumps that led to the discovery of a “dinosaur highway” and nearly 200 tracks that date back 166 million years, researchers said Thursday.

The extraordinary find made after a team of more than 100 people excavated the Dewars Farm Quarry, in Oxfordshire, in June expands upon previous paleontology work in the area and offers greater insights into the Middle Jurassic period, researchers at the universities of Oxford and Birmingham said.

“These footprints offer an extraordinary window into the lives of dinosaurs, revealing details about their movements, interactions, and the tropical environment they inhabited,” said Kirsty Edgar, a micropaleontology professor at the University of Birmingham.

Four of the sets of tracks that make up the so-called highway show paths taken by gigantic, long-necked, herbivores called sauropods, thought to be Cetiosaurus, a dinosaur that grew to nearly 60 feet (18 meters) in length. A fifth set belonged to the Megalosaurus, a ferocious 9-meter predator that left a distinctive triple-claw print and was the first dinosaur to be scientifically named two centuries ago.

An area where the tracks cross raises questions about possible interactions between the carnivores and herbivores.

“Scientists have known about and been studying Megalosaurus for longer than any other dinosaur on Earth, and yet these recent discoveries prove there is still new evidence of these animals out there, waiting to be found,” said Emma Nicholls, a vertebrate paleontologist at the Oxford University Museum of Natural History.

Nearly 30 years ago, 40 sets of footprints discovered in a limestone quarry in the area were considered one of the world’s most scientifically important dinosaur track sites. But that area is mostly inaccessible now and there’s limited photographic evidence because it predated the use of digital cameras and drones to record the findings.

The group that worked at the site this summer took more than 20,000 digital images and used drones to create 3-D models of the prints. The trove of documentation will aid future studies and could shed light on the size of the dinosaurs, how they walked and the speed at which they moved.

“The preservation is so detailed that we can see how the mud was deformed as the dinosaur’s feet squelched in and out,” said Duncan Murdock, an earth scientist at the Oxford museum. “Along with other fossils like burrows, shells and plants we can bring to life the muddy lagoon environment the dinosaurs walked through.”

The findings will be shown at a new exhibit at the museum and also broadcast on the BBC’s “Digging for Britain” program next week.</description></item><item><title>Tesla reports 1.1% sales drop for 2024, first annual decline in at least 9 years</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/tesla-sales-2024-drop-electric-vehicles-69af17c4e606625694af8293db25b2f3</link><description>DETROIT (AP) — Tesla posted its first annual sales drop in more than a dozen years Thursday, sinking a stock that has soared since Donald Trump’s victory on optimism Elon Musk’s close relationship to the president-elect will help the company.

Tesla’s global vehicle sales rose 2.3% in the final quarter thanks to 0% financing, free charging and low-priced leases. But that was not enough for billionaire Musk’s most valuable holding to overcome a sluggish start to 2024.

The Austin, Texas, company sold 495,570 vehicles from October through December, boosting deliveries to 1.79 million for the full year. That was 1.1% below 2023 sales of 1.81 million as overall demand for electric vehicles in the U.S. and elsewhere slowed.

The year-over-year global sales drop is Tesla’s first since 2011, according to figures from analytics firm Global Data. The company sold 1,306 vehicles in 2010, but that dropped slightly to 1,129 the following year.

The fourth-quarter boost came with a cost. Analysts polled by FactSet expected Tesla’s average sales price to fall to just over $41,000 in the quarter, the lowest in at least four years.

That doesn’t bode well for Tesla’s fourth-quarter earnings on Jan. 29 and Tesla’s stock fell more than 7% Thursday.

Musk donated more than $250 million to Trump’s campaign and is a regular guest at Trump’s Mar-a-Lago resort in Florida. Tesla investors have pushed the stock up more than 50% since the election on hopes the new administration will streamline electric vehicle regulations and address other Musk policy priorities.

In 2022, Tesla predicted that its sales would grow 50% most years, but the prediction ran into an aging model lineup and increased competition in China, Europe and the U.S. In the U.S., analysts say most early adopters of technology already own electric vehicles, and more mainstream buyers have concerns about range, price and the ability to find charging stations on longer trips.

The fourth-quarter deliveries fell thousands short of Wall Street expectations. Analysts polled by data provider FactSet expected sales of 498,000 vehicles.

Falling sales early in the year led to once-unheard of discounts for the automaker, cutting into its industry leading profit margins.

Competition from legacy and startup automakers is also growing as they try to nibble away at the company’s market share.

Daniel Ives, a financial analyst at Wedbush, said he thinks the stock should be valued more on its promise of creating fully self-driving, autonomous vehicles and its AI technology and is still worth buying despite the sales drop.

“We have never viewed Tesla simply as a car company...instead we have always viewed Musk and Tesla as a leading disruptive technology global player,” wrote Ives. “And the first part of this grand strategic vision has taken shape.”

The fourth-quarter sales, while a record for Tesla, show that the company’s aging model lineup is reaching saturation in the entry level luxury vehicle market, said Morningstar Analyst Seth Goldstein.

Aside from the Cybertruck, which has had limited appeal, Tesla’s newest consumer model is the Y small SUV which first went on sale in 2020.

To meet Tesla management’s guidance of 20% to 30% annual sales growth this year, the company will need to come out with a vehicle priced in the mid $30,000s to appeal to more mainstream buyers who might be considering gas, electric or hybrid vehicles, Goldstein said.

Tesla has floated the possibility of a new version of the Model Y that would cost in the mid $30,000s that may be smaller inside than the current Y with fewer features, Goldstein said.

“At that point you’re comparable to some Hondas and Fords and GMs,” Goldstein said. “It takes you out of the luxury market to the more affordable vehicle market.”

Jeff Schuster, vice president of automotive research Global Data, said Tesla faces intense competition worldwide from EV makers in China, the U.S. and elsewhere, many of which are selling EVs to more mainstream buyers. “If they want to continue to see the growth they had, they need to expand to other sizes and price points,” he said.

Also, Musk’s support of Trump for U.S. president also could be turning off some buyers who may be more environmentally conscious and lean toward Democrats, Schuster said. A broader, less costly lineup would appeal to a larger group of buyers, he said. “I suppose the choices that he’s made on the political front don’t line up with a good portion of his buyers’ profile,” Schuster said.

Industry experts say that Tesla used to be the only automaker with credible electric vehicles, but now others such as China’s BYD now have more to offer.

At present, automakers have 75 electric vehicle models for sale in the U.S. Through the first nine months of last year, electric vehicle sales slowed in the U.S., but they are still growing.

Through September, new EV sales rose 7.2% to about 936,000 in the U.S., according to Motorintelligence.com. That’s slower growth than the 47% increase in 2023. But EV sales this year still are likely to surpass last year’s record of 1.19 million. Most other automakers will report full-year sales on Friday.

Nearly all of Tesla’s sales last quarter came from the smaller and less-expensive Models 3 and Y, with the company selling only 23,640 of its more expensive models that include X and S, as well as the new Cybertruck.

Tesla’s global electric vehicle sales edged out Chinese rival BYD, which announced Thursday that total soared 41% last year including 1.77 million EVs. The company is vying with Tesla for the world’s top selling EV maker.

Fourth quarter production of 459,445 vehicles was below total deliveries for the quarter, and full year production of 1.77 million was less than the year’s sales.

____

AP reporter Bernard Condon reported from New York City.</description></item><item><title>The man who died in a Tesla Cybertruck explosion was an active-duty US Army soldier, officials say</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/trump-hotel-explosion-tesla-cybertruck-5c5a8fd13a50e2bcde46370ae926d427</link><description>LAS VEGAS (AP) — The highly decorated U.S. Army soldier inside the Tesla Cybertruck that burst into flames outside President-elect Donald Trump’s Las Vegas hotel shot himself in the head before the explosion and likely planned to cause more damage but the steel-sided vehicle absorbed much of the force from the rudimentary explosive, officials said Thursday.

Clark County Sheriff Kevin McMahill said at a news conference that a handgun was found at the feet of the man in the driver’s seat, who officials believe is Matthew Livelsberger, 37, of Colorado. The shot appeared to be self-inflicted, officials said.

Damage from the blast was mostly limited to the interior of the truck. The explosion “vented out and up” and didn’t hit the Trump hotel doors just a few feet away, the sheriff said.

“The level of sophistication is not what we would expect from an individual with this type of military experience,” said Kenny Cooper, a special agent in charge for the the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives.

Among other charred items found inside the truck were a second firearm, a number of fireworks, a passport, a military ID, credit cards, an iPhone and a smartwatch, McMahill said. Authorities said both guns were purchased legally.

The remains were burned beyond recognition and investigators have not definitively identified them as Livelsberger, but the IDs and tattoos on the body “give a strong indication that it’s him,” the sheriff said.

Livelsberger served in the Green Berets, highly trained special forces who work to counter terrorism abroad and train partners. He had served in the Army since 2006, rising through the ranks with a long career of overseas assignments, deploying twice to Afghanistan and serving in Ukraine, Tajikistan, Georgia and Congo, the Army said.

He was awarded a total of five Bronze Stars, including one with a valor device for courage under fire, a combat infantry badge and an Army Commendation Medal with valor. Livelsberger was on approved leave when he died, according to the statement.

McMahill said Livelsberger rented the Tesla electric vehicle in Denver on Saturday and the sheriff displayed a map showing that it was charged in the Colorado town of Monument near Colorado Springs on Monday. On New Year’s Eve, it was charged in Trinidad, Colorado, and the towns of Las Vegas, Albuquerque and Gallup in New Mexico, along the Interstate 40 corridor.

Then on Wednesday, the day of the explosion, it was charged in the Arizona towns of Holbrook, Flagstaff and Kingman before video showed it on the Las Vegas Strip about 7:30 a.m.

McMahill said investigators obtained charging station photos showing Livelsberger “was the individual that was driving this vehicle” and was alone.

“We’re not aware of any other subjects involved in this particular case,” the sheriff said.

The FBI said Thursday in a post on X that it was “conducting law enforcement activity” at a home in Colorado Springs related to Wednesday’s explosion but provided no other details.

The explosion of the truck, packed with firework mortars and camp fuel canisters, came hours after 42-year-old Shamsud-Din Bahar Jabbar rammed a truck into a crowd in New Orleans’ famed French Quarter early on New Year’s Day, killing at least 15 people before being shot to death by police. That crash was being investigated as a terrorist attack. The FBI said Thursday that they believe Jabbar acted alone, reversing its position from a day earlier that he likely worked with others.

Both Livelsberger and Jabbar spent time at the base formerly known as Fort Bragg, a massive Army base in North Carolina that is home to multiple Army special operations units. However, one of the officials who spoke to the AP said there is no overlap in their assignments at the base, now called Fort Liberty.

Chris Raia, FBI deputy assistant director, said Thursday that officials have found ‘no definitive link’ between the New Orleans attack and the truck explosion in Las Vegas.

Seven people nearby suffered minor injuries when the Tesla truck exploded. Video showed a tumble of charred fireworks mortars, canisters and other explosive devices crowded into the back of the pickup. The truck bed walls were still intact because the blast shot straight up rather than to the sides.

Tesla CEO Elon Musk said Wednesday afternoon on X that “we have now confirmed that the explosion was caused by very large fireworks and/or a bomb carried in the bed of the rented Cybertruck and is unrelated to the vehicle itself.”

Musk has recently become a member of Trump’s inner circle. Neither Trump nor Musk was in Las Vegas early Wednesday. Both had attended Trump’s New Year’s Eve party at his South Florida estate.

Musk spent an estimated $250 million during the presidential campaign to support the former president. He was at Trump’s resort on election night and has been a frequent guest there. Trump has named Musk, the world’s richest man, to co-lead a new effort to find ways to cut the government’s size and spending.

___

Copp, Richer and Long contributed from Washington. Associated Press writers Rio Yamat and Ken Ritter in Las Vegas and Christopher Weber in Los Angeles contributed.</description></item><item><title>10 people are wounded in a shooting outside a New York City nightclub</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/jamaica-queens-amazura-nightclub-shooting-new-years-59d4a53ada5718aba369995c9e6274b0</link><description>NEW YORK (AP) — Ten people were wounded in a shooting outside a New York City nightclub while they were waiting to get into a private event, police said.

About 15 people were standing outside Amazura Concert Hall at 11:15 p.m. Wednesday in Jamaica, Queens, when four men on foot approached the group of 16- to 20-year-olds. Three or four men opened fire on the group, New York Police Department Chief of Patrol Philip Rivera said during an early Thursday news conference.

About 30 shots were fired before the gunmen fled on foot. They were then seen getting into a sedan with out-of-state plates.

There is “zero tolerance for these senseless shootings,” Rivera said.

Six females and four males were taken to hospitals with injuries that were not life-threatening, he said.

A massive police presence and several ambulances were seen outside Amazura in footage posted on social media.

The motive was not immediately known, but Rivera said: “This is not terrorism.”

Amazura Concert Hall urged the public to contact police with any information about the shooting.

“We are deeply saddened by the recent and unfortunate isolated incident that occurred. Our hearts go out to all those affected by this senseless act,” the venue said in an Instagram post.</description></item><item><title>Biden is giving the 2nd highest civilian award to the leaders of the Jan. 6 congressional committee</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/biden-citizens-medals-jan-6-cheney-thompson-f725b7003ea11239b90962a8cf0d5305</link><description>President Joe Biden is bestowing the second highest civilian medal on Liz Cheney and Bennie Thompson, leaders of the congressional investigation into the Capitol riot who Donald Trump has said should be jailed for their roles in the inquiry.

Biden will award the Presidential Citizens Medal to 20 people in a ceremony Thursday at the White House, including Americans who fought for marriage equality, a pioneer in treating wounded soldiers, and two of the president’s longtime friends, former Sens. Ted Kaufman, D-Del., and Chris Dodd, D-Conn.

“President Biden believes these Americans are bonded by their common decency and commitment to serving others,” the White House said in a statement. “The country is better because of their dedication and sacrifice.”

Biden last year honored people who were involved in defending the Capitol from a mob of angry Trump supporters on Jan. 6, 2021, or who helped safeguard the will of American voters during the 2020 presidential election, when Trump tried and failed to overturn the results.

Cheney, a former Wyoming congresswoman, and Thompson, a Mississippi Democrat, led the House committee that investigated the insurrection. The committee’s final report asserted that Trump criminally engaged in a “multi-part conspiracy” to overturn the lawful results of the election he lost to Biden and failed to act to stop his supporters from attacking the Capitol. Thompson wrote that Trump “lit that fire.”

Cheney, who lost her seat in the GOP primary in August, later said she would vote for Democrat Kamala Harris in the 2024 presidential race and campaigned with the Democratic nominee, raising Trump’s ire. Biden has been considering whether to offer preemptive pardons to Cheney and others Trump has targeted.

Trump, who won the 2024 election and will take office Jan. 20, still refuses to back away from his lies about the 2020 presidential race and has said he would pardon the rioters once he is back in the White House.

During an interview with NBC’s “Meet the Press,” the president-elect said that “Cheney did something that’s inexcusable, along with Thompson and the people on the un-select committee of political thugs and, you know, creeps,” claiming without evidence they “deleted and destroyed” testimony they collected.

“Honestly, they should go to jail,” he said.

Cheney and Thompson were “an embarrassment to this country” for their conduct on the committee, Trump’s communications director Steven Cheung asserted.

Biden is also giving the award to attorney Mary Bonauto, who fought to legalize same-sex marriage, and Evan Wolfson, a leader of the marriage equality movement.

Other honorees include Frank Butler, who set new standards for using tourniquets on war injuries; Diane Carlson Evans, an Army nurse during the Vietnam War who founded the Vietnam Women’s Memorial Foundation; and Eleanor Smeal, an activist who led women’s rights protests in the 1970s and fought for equal pay.

He’s also giving the award to photographer Bobby Sager, academics Thomas Vallely and Paula Wallace, and Frances Visco, the president of the National Breast Cancer Coalition.

Other former lawmakers being honored include former Sen. Bill Bradley, D-N.J.; former Sen. Nancy Kassebaum, the first woman to represent Kansas; and former Rep. Carolyn McCarthy, D-N.Y., who championed gun safety measures after her son and husband were shot to death.

Biden will honor four people posthumously: Joseph Galloway, a former war correspondent who wrote about the first major battle in Vietnam in the book “We Were Soldiers Once … and Young"; civil rights advocate and attorney Louis Lorenzo Redding; former Delaware judge Collins Seitz; and Mitsuye Endo Tsutsumi, who was held with other Japanese Americans during World War II and challenged the detention.

The Presidential Citizens Medal was created by President Richard Nixon in 1969 and is the country’s second highest civilian honor after the Presidential Medal of Freedom. It recognizes people who “performed exemplary deeds of service for their country or their fellow citizens.”</description></item><item><title>Why Mike Johnson’s bid to remain House speaker could be a struggle despite Trump’s support</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/house-speaker-mike-johnson-trump-mccarthy-0e0b5613f1d39f4e1405a475fdfea8ea</link><description>WASHINGTON (AP) — Mike Johnson is fighting for his political life, again.

The Louisiana Republican’s hold on the House speaker’s gavel and his position as second in line to the presidency will be tested Friday when a new Congress convenes and House Republicans weigh whether to reelect him to the post.

The challenge, as always, is that Johnson will need almost every Republican vote to win.

Johnson has a singular asset in his favor: President-elect Donald Trump endorsed him for speaker in a social media post at the start of the week. But it’s uncertain whether Trump’s blessing will be enough to persuade far-right Republicans who have at times grown frustrated with Johnson’s leadership and who are prone to demand concessions when their votes become essential.

Johnson, 52, ascended to the speakership in October 2023 almost by accident after Republicans struggled to replace Kevin McCarthy following the unprecedented removal of the California Republican from the job. Several contenders tried and failed before Republicans settled on Johnson, who is well liked across the conference.

But Johnson’s handling of major funding fights, including passage of aid to Ukraine last spring and, most recently, a short-term spending bill, has turned at least a few allies into detractors.

With Republicans holding a narrow 220-215 majority in the House, it would take only two GOP lawmakers voting for other candidates to deny Johnson a majority for the speakership, forcing more rounds of voting.

Here’s what to know about how the House elects a speaker:

No House without a speaker

Electing a speaker is the first order of business for the House after a new session of Congress begins at noon. It’s a vote that members take even before being sworn into office.

The House cannot organize until it has a speaker because that person effectively serves as the House’s presiding officer and the institution’s administrative head. The House can elect a new speaker at any time if the person occupying that role dies, resigns or is removed from office. The speakership has been vacant only 13 times in U.S. history, according to the nonpartisan Congressional Research Service. No speaker had ever been removed until eight Republicans joined with Democrats to oust McCarthy.

Barring those instances, a speaker is normally elected at the start of a new Congress and serves in the job for the full two-year session.

The House clerk presides over the speaker’s election. Lawmakers call out the name of their choice for speaker from the floor, a rare and time-consuming roll call that heightens the drama on the floor. Members often liven up the proceedings by shouting or standing when casting their vote.

Who can be nominated?

Any name can be called out from the House floor. While it has been the tradition for the speaker to be a member of the House, it is not required.

In past years, Democratic President Joe Biden, Trump and even a senator, Republican Rand Paul of Kentucky, have received votes for House speaker. None received the majority of the vote. And generally, a party’s official nominee for speaker is who ends up with the gavel.

Republicans chose Johnson as their nominee for speaker in a closed-door vote in November. A week later, Democrats unanimously chose Rep. Hakeem Jeffries, D-N.Y., to remain their leader despite the party’s electoral losses.

Lawmakers are not obligated to vote for their party’s nominated candidate. And that is why the process can quickly get messy.

Let the voting begin

Once the House is in a quorum — meaning the minimum number of members are present to proceed — nominating speeches will be made on behalf of the nominees for speaker. The clerk appoints lawmakers from each party as tellers to tally the votes before the roll call begins.

To become speaker, a candidate needs a majority of the votes from House members who are present and voting.

Historically, the magical number has been 218 out of the 435 members of the House. But many previous speakers, including McCarthy, have won with fewer votes because members sometimes vote “present” instead of calling out a name. Every lawmaker voting “present” lowers the overall tally needed to reach a majority.

It remains to be seen whether Johnson will reach a majority to become speaker on the first ballot. Should he come up short, it is likely the clerk will move to start another roll call vote.

McCarthy went through a grueling 15 ballots over four days before he gained enough support to become the 55th speaker in January 2023.

Passing of the gavel

Once a speaker candidate wins a majority of those present and voting, the clerk will announce the results of the election.

A bipartisan committee, usually consisting of members from the home state of the chosen candidate, will escort the speaker-elect to the chair on the dais where the oath of office is administered. The oath is identical to the one new members will take once a speaker is chosen.

The outgoing speaker usually joins the successor at the speaker’s chair, where the gavel is passed as a nod to the peaceful transition of power from one party leader to another. But this time around, given that Johnson is already the speaker, it will likely be Jeffries who would once again hand Johnson the gavel.</description></item><item><title>What we know about the attack</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/new-orleans-car-bourbon-street-1685016388d65039ce62e720aab2ba14</link><description>NEW ORLEANS (AP) — Investigators now believe the driver who barreled through a crowd of New Year’s Day revelers in New Orleans acted alone and found he posted several videos on social media pledging his support for the Islamic State group, the FBI said Thursday.

The FBI called Wednesday’s attack, which left 14 victims dead, an act of terrorism. The driver, Shamsud-Din Jabbar, a U.S. citizen from Texas, also died in a shootout with police.

Investigators found guns and what appeared to be an improvised explosive device in the vehicle — which bore the flag of the Islamic State group — along with other explosive devices elsewhere in the French Quarter.

The attack unfolded on Bourbon Street, known worldwide as one of the largest destinations for New Year’s Eve parties. Large crowds had gathered in the city ahead of the College Football Playoff quarterfinal at the Sugar Bowl, which was postponed to Thursday afternoon.

Here’s what we know about the attack:

What happened on New Year’s?

Police said Jabbar sped around a police blockade and raced through a crowd around 3:15 a.m. Wednesday along Bourbon Street, where people had gathered to celebrate the New Year. In addition to the dead, 35 people were injured. Two police officers were wounded in the shootout.

Who was the driver?

The FBI said Jabbar is an Army veteran from Texas. He enlisted in 2007, working in both human resources and information technology. He deployed to Afghanistan in February 2009 for nearly a year, and later transferred into the U.S. Army Reserve, the service said in a statement. Jabbar left the military in 2020 with the rank of staff sergeant.

Court records show Jabbar faced a deteriorating financial situation in 2022 while separating from his then-wife. Jabbar said he was behind on house payments and had accumulated credit card debt and wanted to quickly finalize the divorce.

At the time, court documents show he made about $10,000 a month doing business development and other work for the consulting firm Deloitte. In a statement, Deloitte said Jabbar had “served in a staff-level role” since being hired in 2021 and that the company was doing all it could to assist authorities.

Are there clues about his motive?

A driver behind the wheel of a pickup truck raced into a crowd in New Orleans on New Year’s Day, killing at least 10 people in what the FBI is investigating as an act of terrorism. An Islamic State group flag was recovered in the vehicle used by the attacker.

Five videos Jabbar posted on his Facebook account in the hours before the attack showed him previewing the violence that he would soon carry out, the FBI said Thursday. He also proclaimed his support for the Islamic State and said he joined the militant group before last summer, the FBI said.

Surveillance videos the FBI obtained showed Jabbar placing potential explosive devices concealed in coolers in the French Quarter, the agency said Thursday. Initially, investigators believed that others had left behind the improvised explosive devices.

How has the suspect’s family reacted?

Abdur-Rahim Jabbar, Jabbar’s younger brother, told The Associated Press that it “doesn’t feel real” that his brother could have done this.

He said Thursday that his brother had been isolated in the last few years, but that he had also been in touch with him and he didn’t see any signs of radicalization.

Was this connected to the Las Vegas explosion outside a Trump hotel?

The FBI said Thursday that so far they have found no connection between an explosion outside a Las Vegas hotel owned by President-elect Donald Trump and the New Orleans attack.

Investigators found fireworks and camp fuel canisters in a Tesla Cybertruck that blew up outside the Trump International Hotel early Wednesday, killing a suspect inside the vehicle. The person who died was an active-duty U.S. Army soldier, three U.S. officials told The Associated Press.

Who were the victims?

A young woman who dreamed of becoming a nurse, a former Princeton football player, and audiovisual technician at the Superdome were among those killed.

The French Quarter was filled with people toasting the start of 2025 and in the city for the college football playoff.

When did Bourbon Street reopen?

Bourbon Street reopened early Thursday afternoon, hours after authorities finished processing the scene and removing the last of the bodies earlier in the morning.

Jamal LeBlanc, 40, an employee at the Royal Sonesta hotel near the crash scene, said dozens of guests had checked out early and the atmosphere outside remained somber.

“I was feeling a lot of uncertainty and anxiety this morning,” LeBlanc said Thursday. “But we are a resilient people, we’re strong, we bounce back.”

How did security handle the Sugar Bowl?

A fleet of armored vehicles and officers with dogs trained to sniff for explosive devices screened football fans arriving at the Superdome a day later than scheduled for the Sugar Bowl.

The College Football Playoff quarterfinal between Notre Dame and Georgia was pushed back to Thursday afternoon in the wake of the attack. While many traveling fans extended their stay to attend the game, some couldn’t change their travel plans and were forced to miss the game.

“Of course we’re disappointed to miss it and to lose so much money on it, but at the end of the day it doesn’t matter,” said Lisa Borrelli, a 34-year-old Philadelphia resident who came with her fiancé, a Notre Dame graduate.

___

This story has been corrected to show that the Sugar Bowl was moved to Thursday afternoon, not Thursday night.</description></item><item><title>An aspiring nurse, a football star, a single mother and a father of 2 among those killed</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/new-orleans-killed-crash-terrorist-attack-9f2fbcc3e48d8b391590f60969e80e61</link><description>An 18-year-old woman dreaming of becoming a nurse, a single mother, a father of two and a former Princeton football star were killed when the driver of a white pickup truck sped down Bourbon Street, packed with holiday revelers.

Officials have not yet released the names of the 14 people killed in the New Orleans New Year’s Day truck attack, but their families and friends have started sharing their stories.

New Orleans Coroner Dr. Dwight McKenna said in a statement late Wednesday that the names of the dead will be released once autopsies are complete and they’ve talked with the next of kin. A spokesperson for the coroner said Thursday that there were no updates. About 30 people were injured.

Hubert Gauthreaux

Archbishop Shaw High School, in Marrero, Louisiana, posted on Facebook that class of 2021 alum Hubert Gauthreaux, was among the victims.

Gauthreaux “was tragically killed in the senseless act of violence that occurred early this morning in the French Quarter. He was 21 years old,” the Catholic boys school posted Wednesday evening. “We are asking the entire Archbishop Shaw family to pray for the repose of Hubert’s soul, his family and friends during this difficult time, and all those affected by this tragedy.”

Kareem Badawi

University of Alabama freshman Kareem Badawi was among those killed in the attack. A native of Louisiana and a graduate of the Episcopal School of Baton Rouge, Badawi had started at the Alabama university this fall.

“It is with great sadness and grief, and with hearts satisfied with Allah’s decision and destiny, I announce the death of my son, Karim Bilal Badawi, who died early today in the morning as a result of a tragic accident in New Orleans,” his father, Belal Badawi, posted on Facebook. “We ask Allah Almighty to shower his mercy on him, and give us patience and strength.”

His father had posted in May celebrating his son’s high school graduation and plans to attend the University of Alabama.

The university issued a statement confirming Badawi’s death.

“I grieve alongside family and friends of Kareem in their heartbreaking loss,” University of Alabama President Stuart R. Bell said.

Drew Dauphin

Christopher B. Roberts, president of Auburn University in Auburn, Alabama, said on the social platform X that 2023 graduate Drew Dauphin died in the attack.

“Words cannot convey the sorrow the Auburn Family feels for Drew’s family and friends during this unimaginably difficult time,” Roberts said. “Our thoughts are with the Dauphin family and the families of all the victims of this senseless tragedy.”

Dauphin was a supplier process engineer at the American Honda Motor Company in Birmingham, Alabama, according to his LinkedIn profile.

Matthew Tenedorio

The parents of Matthew Tenedorio told NBC News that their son was one of the people killed in the attack.

“He was 25 years old. He was just starting life. He had the job of his dreams,” Cathy Tenedorio said. “It’s just very sad.”

A GoFundMe page created by a cousin says he was an audiovisual technician at the Superdome.

“He was a wonderful kid,” Louis Tenedorio added. “He loved people. He loved animals. He always had a smile. So many friends. He had so many friends.”

Cathy Tenedorio said she had spent New Year’s Eve with Matthew and another one of her sons.

“We had dinner and we did fireworks outside, and just laughing and hugging each other and telling each other we loved each other,” she said. She added that they had tried to dissuade him from going into the city.

“They don’t think about risk,” she said.

Nikyra Dedeaux

Zion Parsons, of Gulfport, Mississippi, had been celebrating New Year’s Eve at his first night on Bourbon Street when a vehicle appeared and plowed into his friend, 18-year-old Nikyra Dedeaux, who he said had dreamed of becoming a nurse.

“A truck hit the corner and comes barreling through throwing people like in a movie scene, throwing people into the air,” Parsons told The Associated Press. “It hit her and flung her like at least 30 feet and I was just lucky to be alive.”

As the crowd scattered in the chaos he ran through a gruesome aftermath of bleeding and maimed victims, hearing gunshots and explosive sounds.

“Bodies, bodies all up and down the street, everybody screaming and hollering” Parsons said. “People crying on the floor, like brain matter all over the ground. It was just insane, like the closest thing to a war zone that I’ve ever seen.”

Dedeaux was a responsible daughter who helped take care of her siblings, Parsons said. Dedeaux had a job at a hospital and was set to start college and begin working towards her goal of becoming a registered nurse.

“She had her mindset — she didn’t have everything figured out but she had the plan laid down,” Parsons said.

Reggie Hunter

A 37-year-old father of two from Baton Rouge, Reggie Hunter had just left work and headed to celebrate New Year’s with a cousin when the attack happened, his first cousin Shirell Jackson told Nola.com.

Hunter died and his cousin was injured, Jackson said.

Tiger Bech

A former high school and college football player from Louisiana was among those who died, according to an education official.

Tiger Bech, 27, died Wednesday morning at a New Orleans hospital, according to local media outlets citing Kim Broussard, the athletic director at St. Thomas More Catholic High School in Lafayette. Bech attended the high school, where he played wide receiver, quarterback, punt returner and defensive back, NOLA.com reported.

Bech played football at Princeton University before graduating in 2021. Most recently he was working as an investment trader at a New York brokerage firm.

Marty Cannon, STM principal and former coach of Bech, said he was charismatic, intelligent and an incredibly talented football player. He regularly returned home to visit his tight-knit family, close friends and people at the school. He was home over Christmas.

“We live in a relatively small community here where not a lot of people leave but many do,” Cannon said. “I’m not surprised at all that Tiger could take off from south Louisiana and go off and get an amazing education at a place like Princeton and then lock himself into a community up there and just flourish. He’s that kind of guy.”

Princeton football coach Bob Surace said Wednesday that he had been texting with Bech’s father, sharing memories of the player, who was a school kick returner and receiver from 2017 to 2019. He earned All-Ivy League honors as a returner.

“He might be the first Tiger to ever play for us, and that nickname kind of described him as a competitor,” Surace told ESPN. The school’s mascot is the tiger. “He was somebody that somehow, like in the key moments, just excelled and was full of energy, full of life.”

Bech has been working at Seaport Global, where company spokesperson Lisa Lieberman could not confirm his death. She told the AP “he was extremely well regarded by everybody who knew him.”

Bech’s younger brother, Jack, is a top wide receiver at Texas Christian University.

In a response to a KLFY-TV report posted on X about Tiger Bech’s death, a post from an account for a Jack Bech on the social media site said: “Love you always brother ! You inspired me everyday now you get to be with me in every moment. I got this family T, don’t worry. This is for us.”

Nicole Perez

Nicole Perez was a single mother to a 4-year-old son working hard to make life better for her family when she was killed, according to her employer.

Perez, who was in her late 20s, was recently promoted to manager at Kimmy’s Deli in Metairie, Louisiana, and “was really excited about it,” deli owner Kimberly Usher said in a phone interview with the AP. Usher confirmed Perez’s death through her sister, who also works for her.

Usher said Perez would walk in the morning to the deli, which opened at breakfast time, and ask lots of questions about the business side of the operations. She also was permitted to bring her son, Melo, to work.

“She was a really good mom,” said Usher, who started a GoFundMe account to cover Perez’s burial costs and to help with expenses for her son that “he will need to transition into a new living situation,” the donation request says.

Injured in the Attack

— Heaven Sensky-Kirsch said her father, Jeremi Sensky, endured 10 hours of surgery for injuries that included two broken legs. He was taken off a ventilator Thursday.

Jeremi Sensky was ejected from the wheelchair he was using and had bruises to his face and head, Sensky-Kirsch said in a phone interview from a hospital intensive care unit.

“He’s talking right now,” Sensky-Kirsch said late Thursday morning.

Sensky, 51, who works in the family’s tree service business, had driven from his home in Canonsburg, Pennsylvania, to New Orleans to celebrate the holiday.

Before the attack, Sensky and the two friends had been having pizza, his daughter said. Sensky left them to return to his hotel on Canal Street because he felt cold, she said.

Sensky-Kirsch said others could see the attacker coming and were able to run out of the way, but her father “was stuck on the road.” His wheelchair can been seen in some images lodged against a crane.

When he didn’t return to the hotel, they went to look for him, she said.

“We thought he was dead,” Sensky-Kirsch said. “We can’t believe he’s alive.”

— Ryan Quigley, who was a teammate of Bech’s at Princeton, was with him when they were struck by the truck. Quigley was injured, according to family and friends.

“Ryan is doing okay. He is stable and resting in the company of his family and friends,” the Quigleys said in an update on a GoFundMe page set up by his friends. “Ryan loves you all. Please keep the Bech family, the other families, and all of those affected by this tragedy in your prayers. Thank you all.”

— University of Georgia President Jere W. Morehead said on X that a student was critically injured in the attack and is receiving medical treatment. He did not name the student.

— The Israeli Ministry of Foreign Affairs said on X that two Israeli citizens were injured in the attack.

— University of Mississippi Chancellor Glenn Boyce said Thursday that one of the university’s students was critically injured in New Orleans. Boyce did not identify the student.

___

The story has been updated to correct Tiger Bech’s age from 28 to 27, and to correct the spelling of Metairie, Louisiana, from Metarie.

___

Jack Brook in New Orleans, Gary Robertson in Raleigh, North Carolina, Emily Wagster Pettus in Jackson, Mississippi, Travis Loller in Nashville and Kimberly Chandler in Montgomery, Alabama contributed to this report. Bellisle reported from Seattle.</description></item><item><title>New Orleans plans to reopen Bourbon Street</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/new-orleans-car-attack-bourbon-street-5bbf5fdc715c4d0d4c8764dd8da22720</link><description>NEW ORLEANS (AP) — The U.S. Army veteran who drove a pickup truck into a crowd of New Year’s revelers acted alone, the FBI said Thursday, reversing its position from a day earlier that he likely worked with others in the deadly attack that officials said was inspired by the Islamic State group.

The FBI also revealed that the driver, Shamsud-Din Jabbar, a U.S. citizen from Texas, posted five videos on his Facebook account in the hours before the attack in which he proclaimed his support for the militant group and previewed the violence that he would soon unleash in the city’s famed French Quarter district.

“This was an act of terrorism. It was premeditated and an evil act,” said Christopher Raia, the deputy assistant director of the FBI’s counterterrorism division, calling Jabbar “100% inspired” by the Islamic State.

The attack killed 14 revelers, along with Jabbar, who was fatally shot in a firefight with police after steering his speeding truck around a barricade and plowing into the crowd.

It was the deadliest IS-inspired assault on U.S. soil in years, laying bare what federal officials have warned is a resurgent international terrorism threat and coming as the FBI and other agencies brace for dramatic leadership upheaval — and likely policy changes — after President-elect Donald Trump’s administration takes office.

Seeking to assuage concerns about any broader plots, Raia stressed that there was no indication of a connection between the New Orleans attack and the explosion Wednesday of a Tesla Cybertruck filled with explosives outside Trump’s Las Vegas hotel. The person inside that truck, a decorated U.S. Army Green Beret, sustained a gunshot wound to the head before the explosion, and a handgun was found at his feet inside the charred vehicle, authorities said Thursday.

The FBI continued to hunt for clues about the 42-year-old Jabbar, but said that a day into its investigation, it was now confident that he was not aided by anyone else in the attack, which killed an 18-year-old aspiring nurse, a single mother, a father of two and a former Princeton University football star, among others.

Officials have concluded that none of the individuals seen in surveillance video standing near an improvised explosive device that Jabbar placed in a cooler along the city’s Bourbon Street, where the attack occurred, were involved “in any way,” though investigators do want to speak with them as witnesses, Raia said.

The device in the cooler and another explosive device were rendered safe at the scene. Others were determined to be nonfunctional.

Investigators were also trying to understand more about Jabbar’s path to radicalization, which they say culminated with him picking up a rented truck in Houston on Dec. 30 and driving it to New Orleans the following night.

The FBI recovered a black Islamic State flag from his rented pickup and reviewed five videos posted to Facebook, including one in which he said he originally planned to harm his family and friends, but was concerned that news headlines would not focus on the “war between the believers and the disbelievers,” Raia said. He also left a last will and testament, the FBI said.

Jabbar joined the Army in 2007, serving on active duty in human resources and information technology and deploying to Afghanistan from 2009 to 2010, the service said. He transferred to the Army Reserve in 2015 and left in 2020 with the rank of staff sergeant.

Abdur-Rahim Jabbar, Jabbar’s younger brother, told The Associated Press on Thursday that it “doesn’t feel real” that his brother could have done this.

“I never would have thought it’d be him,” he said. “It’s completely unlike him.”

He said that his brother had been isolated in the last few years, but that he had also been in touch with him and he didn’t see any signs of radicalization.

“It’s completely contradictory to who he was and how his family and his friends know him,” he said.

In New Orleans on Thursday, a still-reeling city inched back toward normal operations. Authorities finished processing the scene early in the morning, removing the last of the bodies, and Bourbon Street — famous worldwide for music, open-air drinking and festive vibes — reopened for business by early afternoon.

The Sugar Bowl college football game between Notre Dame and Georgia, initially set for Wednesday night and postponed by a day in the interest of national security, was still on for Thursday. The city also planned to host the Super Bowl next month.

New Orleans “is not only ready for game day today, but we’re ready to continue to host large-scale events in our city because we are built to host at every single turn,” New Orleans Mayor LaToya Cantrell said.

___

Tucker reported from Washington, and Mustian reported from Black Mountain, North Carolina. Associated Press reporters Stephen Smith, Chevel Johnson and Brett Martel in New Orleans; Jeff Martin in Atlanta; Alanna Durkin Richer, Tara Copp and Zeke Miller in Washington; Darlene Superville in New Castle, Delaware; Colleen Long in West Palm Beach, Florida; and Michael R. Sisak in New York contributed to this report.</description></item><item><title>Live updates: FBI now says New Orleans truck attacker acted alone</title><link>https://apnews.com/live/new-orleans-truck-attack-updates</link><description>Chris Pousson, of Beaumont, Texas, said he became friends with Shamsud-Din Jabbar in middle school and recalled him as quiet and reserved.

“This is a complete shock,” Pousson said. “Everyone I spoke with, all of our classmates, we’re all just in disbelief really.”

He said that after high school, they reconnected on Facebook around 2008 or 2009 and would message back and forth until around 2018 or 2019.

“He was always like glory to God and all that stuff, praise to the highest,” Pousson, 42, said. “He was always promoting his faith in a positive manner. It was never anything negative.”

Pousson, who is retired after serving 16 years in the Air Force, where he worked in anti-terrorism, said,

“I never saw this coming.”

“If any red flags would have popped off, I would have caught them and I would have contacted the proper authorities,” he said. “But he didn’t give anything to me that would have suggested that he is capable of doing what happened.”</description><enclosure url="https://dims.apnews.com/dims4/default/1b87170/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5910x3937+0+1/resize/767x511!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fassets.apnews.com%2Faa%2F4b%2Fbccb34a0abf552e1a167de6f25f4%2Ff343e51b82094959b034a0ba53ab005c" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/></item></channel></rss>
